<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>Animation Techniques in BRL-CAD</title>
    <author>
      <personname>
       <firstname>  Christine</firstname>
  <surname>Murdza</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
    <firstname>Lee</firstname>
  <surname>A. Butler</surname>

      </personname>
  </author>

</info>
<section>
<title>
Introduction
</title>
<section xml:id="Introduction">
<title>Introduction</title>
<para>Moving pictures are created by presenting the viewer with a sequence of still images in quick succession. Objects which occur in an orderly succession of slightly different locations within a sequence of images appear to be in motion to the viewer. Such an object is said to be ``animated.'' Preparing a moving picture of animated objects requires a large number of still images (often called ``frames'').
</para>
<para>
Still images of computer models are relatively easy to create within BRL-CAD. *|* The program rt uses the technique of ray-tracing to create images of geometric models. *|* A moving picture or ``animation'' of the model can be created by using rt to create a series of still images, each of which forms a frame of the final moving picture. The difficulty arises in specifying each frame for rt to create. Some tools have been created to help make this process easier.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Preliminaries">
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<para>
Before there can be motion there must first be form. This means a description of geometry to be animated must exist. To keep things simple, we will use the ``moss'' database distributed with BRL-CAD. Assuming that the distribution is stored in the directory /cadsrc the following command will create a local copy of the database for use with the examples presented here:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">% asc2g&#60; &#47;cadsrc&#47;db&#47;moss&#46;asc&#62;moss&#46;g</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
Examples such as the one above are presented with the portion typed by the user shown in <emphasis role="bold">bold</emphasis> typeface.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Simple_Camera_Motion">
<title>
Simple Camera Motion
</title>
<section xml:id="Key_Frames">
<title>Key Frames</title>
<para>
The first step in creating an animation sequence is the definition of ``key-frames.'' These are descriptions of what the scene should look like at ``key'' moments in the animation sequence. Some key-frames are readily recognized. The frame in which the camera or an object starts or stops moving is important. Likewise, the moment when an object changes direction or velocity is also important. It is good to define one or two key-frames before and after each of these points of change.
</para>
<para>
Generating key-frames with mged is easy. The user displays the wireframe of the desired geometry and manipulates the display until the desired view is achieved. To save the key-frame information in a file, the mged keyboard command ``saveview'' is used. This command creates a shell script with the proper invocation of the rt program to render the current scene. The argument to the ``saveview'' command is the filename for the shell script. Note that the keyboard command ``saveview'' is distinct and different from the menu option visible in the button menu on the geometry display.
</para>
<para>
To keep things orderly and make later processing easier, it is recommended that the user specify key-frame filenames which have a common prefix followed by a number indicating the time in the animation sequence at which the key-frame occurs.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Generating_Key_Frames_with_MGED">
<title>Generating Key Frames with MGED</title>
<para>
For our first example, we will create a simple animation with the ``moss.g'' model. The objective is to begin the animation sequence with a view of the geometry from the front corner of the platform. As time goes by, the viewer's location (the ``eye point'' or ``eye_pt'') moves upward in an arc over the geometry until the viewer is looking directly down on the center of the platform. To give a natural feeling of flight, the eye point should accelerate and decelerate at the beginning and end of its travel respectively. This is achieved by adjusting the number of degrees of elevation the eye will raise in each second of the animation. In the first (and last) three quarters of a second of the animation, the eye raises only 2 degrees of elevation above the plane. In the following second 8 degrees of arc are covered. At the 4 second mark the eye is looking down at a 45 degree angle.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">mged moss.g</emphasis>
<literallayout>
BRL-CAD Release 4.1   Graphics Editor (MGED)
     Tue Oct 20 14:19:59 EDT 1992, Compilation 5
     stay&#64;vail&#58;&#47;n&#47;wolf&#47;m&#47;dist4&#46;1&#47;mged
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
attach (nu|tek|tek4109|ps|plot|sgi|X)[nu]? <emphasis role="bold">sgi</emphasis>
ATTACHING sgi (SGI 4d)
Gary Moss's "World on a Platter" (units=mm)
mged> <emphasis role="bold">e all.g</emphasis>
408 vectors in 1 sec
mged> <emphasis role="bold">center 20 0 0</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">size 200</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 0</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_0</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 2</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_0.75</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 10</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_1.75</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 45</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_4</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 80</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_6.25</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 88</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_7.25</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">ae 45 90</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">saveview moss_8</emphasis>
mged> <emphasis role="bold">q</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
At this stage there are seven key-frame files in the current directory with the names:
</para>
<para>
	<programlisting>
	moss_0		moss_1.75	moss_6.25	moss_8
	moss_0.75	moss_4		moss_7.25

	</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
A look at the contents of one of the key-frame files shows that the scene is stored as four separate elements. These elements are the geometry being displayed, the size of the viewing cube or ``viewsize'', the location in 3 dimensional space of the camera or ``eye_pt'', and the ``orientation'' of the geometry within space. All animations which involve the observer moving about a static object can be generated from these parameters.
</para>
<para>
Recall that these key-frames do not represent all of the images necessary to produce the animation. They only specify the significant moments in the animation. It is necessary to generate the ``in-between'' frames as well to turn the key-frames into a smooth animation. The values for the ``viewsize,'' ``eye_pt'' and ``orientation'' attributes of these ``in-between'' frames are generated by interpolating the values which describe the key-frames.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="Key_Frame_Interpolation">
<title>Key Frame Interpolation</title>
<para>
The first step in creating an animation sequence is the definition of ``key-frames.'' These are descriptions of what the scene should look like at ``key'' moments in the animation sequence. Some key-frames are readily recognized. The frame in which the camera or an object starts or stops moving is important. Likewise, the moment when an object changes direction or velocity is also important. It is good to define one or two key-frames before and after each of these points of change.
</para>
<para>
Generating key-frames with mged is easy. The user displays the wireframe of the desired geometry and manipulates the display until the desired view is achieved. To save the key-frame information in a file, the mged keyboard command ``saveview'' is used. This command creates a shell script with the proper invocation of the rt program to render the current scene. The argument to the ``saveview'' command is the filename for the shell script. Note that the keyboard command ``saveview'' is distinct and different from the menu option visible in the button menu on the geometry display.
</para>
<para>
To keep things orderly and make later processing easier, it is recommended that the user specify key-frame filenames which have a common prefix followed by a number indicating the time in the animation sequence at which the key-frame occurs.
</para>
<para>
BRL-CAD has a utility for performing interpolation called <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link>. It operates on files containing columns of numbers. The left-most column is always used to hold the time in the animation at which the data in the other columns occurs. A column is referred to as a ``channel.'' Lines beginning with a ``#'' character are considered to be comments, and are ignored by <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link>. Table A shows an example input file for <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link>.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
	#Time	X	Y	Z
	0	100	0	0
	1	 74.24	51.98	42.23
	2	-91.85	91.85	75

</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
This table has four channels (columns). The leftmost channel is always the ``time channel''. In this instance the ``time channel'' has the values 0, 1, and 2. The time channel has no inherent unit associated with it. These values could represent microseconds, seconds, minutes, etc. depending upon the motion being specified. The second column contains the first actual data channel in this file. In this instance it is an X coordinate. There are three data channels in this file. The contents of the file are said to form an interpolation table.
</para>
<para>
To create the ``in-between'' frames of our animation, we need to extract the values which are arguments to the ``viewsize'', ``eye_pt'', and ``orientation'' commands to rt stored in the key-frame files. These values must be tabulated for input to <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link>.
</para>
<para>
While it would be possible to concatenate the key-frame files and edit the result by hand to create the table, this would be tedious for all but the simplest animations. Instead it is recommended that a shell script such as the ``key-chans'' shown below be employed to do the work.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
 #!/bin/sh
    if [ "$#" != "1" ] ; then
      echo "Usage: $0 basename"
      exit
    fi
    awk '/^viewsize/ { print FILENAME " " $2}'  $1* | \
        sed -e 's/;//' -e "s/^$1//" | sort -n > chans.vsize

    awk '/^eye_pt/ { print FILENAME " "  $2  " " $3 " " $4}' $1* | \
        sed -e 's/;//' -e "s/^$1//" | sort -n > chans.eyept
    awk '/^orient/ { print FILENAME " " $2 " " $3 " " $4 " " $5}' $1* | \
        sed -e 's/;//' -e "s/^$1//" | sort -n > chans.orient
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
This shell script creates the three files <link linkend='vsize'>``chans.vsize'',</link><link linkend='eypet'> ``chans.eyept''</link>, and <link linkend='orient'>``chans.orient''</link> from key-frame files which share the same basename (such as ``moss_''). The shared basename is specified on the command line.</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">% key-chans moss</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The files <link linkend='vsize'>``chans.vsize,</link>'' <link linkend='eypet'>``chans.eyept,</link>'' <link linkend='orient'>``chans.orient</link>'' now contain the values needed for interpolation. The file <link linkend='vsize'>``chans.vsize</link>'' contains the argument to the ``viewsize'' directive in the key-frame files. Likewise, <link linkend='eypet'>``chans.eyept''</link> contains the X, Y, and Z arguments to the ``eye_pt'' directive and <link linkend='orient'>``chans.orient</link>'' contains the quaternion *|* argument to the ``orientation'' directive.
</para>
<para>
Now the key-frame data can be interpolated. The <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> program reads commands from standard input until end-of-file is found. Commands specify files from which interpolation tables should be read, which channels in the tables should be used, what type of interpolation should be applied, and the range of time over which values are needed. When end of file is reached, <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> performs any interpolations requested and writes out the requested results.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">% <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> &#60;&#60;EOF&#62;&#62; chans.
all
file chans.vsize 0;
file chans.eyept 1 2 3;
file chans.orient 4 5 6 7;
times 0 8 3;
interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7;
EOF  </emphasis>
cmd: file chans.vsize 0
chan 0:  File 'chans.vsize', Column 1
cmd: file chans.eyept 1 2 3
chan 1:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 1
chan 2:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 2
chan 3:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 3
cmd: file chans.orient 4 5 6 7
chan 4:  File 'chans.orient', Column 1
chan 5:  File 'chans.orient', Column 2
chan 6:  File 'chans.orient', Column 3
chan 7:  File 'chans.orient', Column 4
cmd: times 0 8 3
cmd: interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
performing interpolations
writing output
%
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
In this instance, the data from the ``viewsize'' interpolation table is read into channel 0 of <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link>. The eye point data is acquired from another file to fill channels 1, 2, and 3. The orientation table data are read into channels 4, 5, 6, and 7. The user command ``times 0 8 3'' indicates that interpolation is to be performed for the time sequence starting at time 0, through time 8 with 3 frames per time step. If each time step represents a second, this is not enough frames per second for a finished product such as a videotape, but it will be sufficient to create a preview of the sequence. It would not be wise to expend the CPU time required to compute all of the frames before we are certain that we have the sequence correct.
</para>
<para>
The last command to <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> selects a spline interpolation for channels 0 through 7. When <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> runs out of commands to process it performs the interpolation. The file ``chans.all'' contains the result of the interpolation.
</para>
<para>
Each column in chans.all represents one channel from the <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> session. The leftmost column is always the time channel. The column next to that is data channel 0 from the <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> session. An examination of the time channel on the left will reveal that the sequence runs from time 0 through time 8 and that there are 3 lines (frames) for every integer time step.
</para>
<para>
This example used only spline interpolation. There are other interpolation techniques available including step, linear, and circular spline (cspline). With step interpolation, a channel value is simply copied to intermediate time points until a new value is encountered. The circular spline technique makes certain that the starting and stopping conditions of the time sequence are identical. The second derivative of the curve at the endpoints are made to be the same. This is useful when a seamless loop of values is desired.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Building_the_RT_Animation_Script">
<title>Building the RT Animation Script</title>
<para>
The program tabsub uses the output from a run of <link linkend='tabinterp'>tabinterp</link> along with a template file to write an animation script for rt. There are many types of ``macros'' which tabsub recognizes in the template. An understanding of two of these is necessary for the current example. The character ``@'' followed by an integer (such as @2) is replaced by data from the interpolation channel of that number. Note that ``@0'' refers to values from the first data channel from the interpolation. It does not refer to the time channel. The macro ``@(line)'' is replaced with the line number of the file from which the data was read. The @(line) macro serves primarily to indicate the animation frame number. A template file (``moss.proto'' for this example) should be created:
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">%  cat moss.proto </emphasis>
viewsize @0;
eye_pt @1 @2 @3;
orientation @4 @5 @6 @7;
start @(line);
end;
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
This file can be used in conjunction with tabsub to create an animation script for rt.
</para>
<para>
% tabsub moss.proto chans.all > moss.rtanim
</para>
<para>
The resultant file ``moss.rtanim'' is rather long, so for illustration purposes only the commands for the first two frames are shown here.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
% head -n 12 moss.rtanim
viewsize 200;
eye_pt 90.7107 70.7107 0;
orientation 0.270598 0.653281 0.653281 0.270598;
start 0;
end;

viewsize 200;
eye_pt 90.6992 70.6992 1.11757;
orientation 0.26908 0.649617 0.656908 0.2721;
start 1;
end;
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Previewing_Animations_with_MGED">
<title>Previewing Animations with MGED</title>
<para>Under a future version of BRL-CAD and beyond, the user will have the ability to preview animations using mged. Users running a 4.[012] release should skip this section. This is a useful check to run before expending the CPU time to compute the images with rt.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">  %mged moss.g </emphasis>
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
BRL-CAD Release    Graphics Editor (MGED)
    Wed Nov 11 00:36:43 EST 1992, Compilation 770
    mike@wolf.arl.mil:/m/cad/.mged.5d
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
attach (nu|tek|tek4109|ps|plot|sgi)[nu]? <emphasis role="bold">sgi</emphasis>
ATTACHING nu (Null Display)
Gary Moss's ``World on a Platter'' (units=mm)
mged>  <emphasis role="bold">preview moss.rtanim</emphasis>
tree
eyepoint at (0,0,1) viewspace
db_lookup:  could not find 'EYE_PATH*'
mged>  <emphasis role="bold">e all.g</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Don't let the ``db_lookup'' message frighten you. This is just mged telling you that there wasn't an EYE_PATH overlay prior to your first ``preview'' command. This is the name of the ``pseudo-object'' that mged creates for storing the overlay. This object is not written into the geometry database. The preview command paints a small ``L'' shape at the eye point for each frame and connects all the corners together. The location of the ``L'' indicates the location of the eye for the frame. The orientation of the ``L'' is in the plane perpendicular to the viewing direction for the frame.
</para>
<para>
Look carefully at the path the eye will take during the animation. In this instance we want the path to form an arc from near one of the corners of the platform to a point directly over the top of the platform. Does it look like what was intended? Does the arc seem to pass through any of the objects? On a machine which supports fast polygon rendering, such as the Silicon Graphics Iris, displaying the geometry with the ``ev'' command instead of the ``e'' command will make finding eye/geometry collisions much easier.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Creating_Postage_Stamp_Animations">
<title>Creating Postage Stamp Animations</title>
<para>
Once you are convinced that the eye path is correct you are ready to produce a test animation. The file ``moss.rtanim'' can be fed directly to rt either from the command line or in a shell script. The invocation of moss.rt shown below will generate images that are 200 pixels square. This is a good size to use for an initial rendering. It will let us preview our animation before committing the resources to generate the complete animation.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">% cat moss.rt</emphasis>
#!/bin/sh
rt -M $* -o moss.pix moss.g 'all.g' 2>> moss.log &#47; moss.rtanim

<emphasis role="bold">% moss.rt -s 200</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Once the frames have been computed, they can be turned into a ``postage stamp animation''. The ``pixtile'' program takes many small images and creates a bigger image from a mosaic of the small images. This image can then be displayed on a framebuffer, and the animation sequence played using the ``fbanim'' command.
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">
% mv moss.pix moss.pix.0
% fbserv -S 1024 0 /dev/sgip
% setenv FB_FILE :0
% pixtile -s 200 -S 1024 moss.pix | pix-fb -h
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24
% fbanim -S1024 -s200 -p5 200 25 3
</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/moss_sm.gif" width="300"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject><phrase>An illustration of the Pythagorean Theorem</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<link  xlink:href="../../articles/en/images/moss.mpg">
moss.mpg
</link>
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Object_Motion">
<title>
Object Motion
</title>
<para>Animations involving just camera motion through a static scene or around a static object are adequate for many different applications. Using only camera motion, the viewer can see what it would be like to walk through a building which exists only as a computer model. The view from the driver's seat of a new vehicle design can be created. Even a simulation of an object flying past the viewer can be created (by flying the viewer past the object instead).</para>
<para>
For a variety of applications, the true value of animation is realized only when the geometric objects themselves have motion. Perhaps a vehicle drives past a familiar stationary landmark and the eye follows the vehicle away after it enters the scene. As the vehicle drives over a bump in the road the suspension system is seen to flex and energy is transferred to the frame. Things which cannot ordinarily be seen can be made more visible by watching them change over time. As our vehicle crosses a bridge, its weight causes it to flex and vibrate even after the vehicle is gone. These effects could be made visible by amplifying them until they are readily observable.
</para>
<section xml:id="Matrix_Manipulations">
<title>Matrix Manipulations</title>
<para>
The animation of objects is accomplished by specifying matrix transformations to be applied to database elements before each image is calculated. This allows any solid or combination in the model to have its definition independently rotated, moved, or re-sized as the animation proceeds.
</para>
<para>
In BRL-CAD matrices are stored in a traditional mathematics form. This is different from (the transpose of) the form used in most texts on computer graphics. In BRL-CAD matrices are stored as follows:
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/matrix.gif" width="100" />
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

</para>
<para>
As a result, points and vectors in 3 dimensional space are represented as 4-tuple column vectors. Points and vectors are therefore properly transformed by the matrix equation:
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/equation.gif" width="300"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</para>
<para>
Individuals who are unfamiliar with matrix transformations in general and homogeneous coordinate systems in specific are urged to study one of the many texts on this subject.
</para>
<para>
The matrix operations in a BRL-CAD database can be thought of as living in the arcs of the directed acyclic graph. In slightly simpler terms, the matrix lives between an object (either primitive solid or combination record) and the parent combination record in the model tree. The model coordinate system is on the ``left'' end of a ``stack'' of matrix multiplications which is built up as the graph is traversed. When traversing the graph from the root to the leaves, matrices encountered on the arcs are applied to the ``right'' of the matrix equation. For example, the graph formed by ``all.g'' from our geometry file ``moss.g'' can be thought of as the following table:
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/dagtbl.gif" width="400" />
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</para>
<para>
Purists will note that MatrixA is not directly stored in the database. It exists as a conceptual aid to editing models and creating animations. In reality MatrixA will be combined with each of the matrices MatrixPr, MatrixBr, MatrixEr, MatrixCr, MatrixTr, MatrixLr from the table above.
</para>
<para>
The program rt would transform the origin (and other parameters) of ``tor'' with the following matrix equation:
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/trans.gif"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="The_RT_Matrix_Operations_for_Animation">
<title>The RT Matrix Operations for Animation</title>
<para>
Each of the matrices in the database can be altered individually during the animation. It is also possible to replace the ``stack'' matrix which has been accumulated. These operations are achieved with the ``anim'' command in the input script to rt. The command has the form:
</para>
<para>
anim Path matrix Operation  [Matrix];
where Path specifies the arc where the operation takes place. Either a specific use of the matrix within the model, or all uses of an arc within the model can be specified.
where Path specifies the arc where the operation takes place. Either a specific use of the matrix within the model, or all uses of an arc within the model can be specified.
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/animtbl.gif"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</para>
<para>
	For example, the following command always replaces the matrix on the arc between ``arm'' and ``hand'' with a new matrix:
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
		anim arm/hand matrix rarc
		1    0    0    0
		0    1    0    0
		0    0    1    0
		0    0    0    1
</programlisting>

 </para>
 <para>
 	Whereas in the next example the matrix will be replaced only when ``arm/hand'' occurs as a direct child of ``body/left'' in the database tree. This would permit the left and right hands to be modeled as different instances of a single hand prototype, and still allow the left hand to be manipulated without affecting the right hand.
</para>
<programlisting>
		anim body/left/arm/hand matrix rarc
		1    0    0    0
		0    1    0    0
		0    0    1    0
		0    0    0    1;
</programlisting>
<para>
	Finally, a command of the form:
</para>
<programlisting>
		anim hand matrix rarc
		1    0    0    0
		0    1    0    0
		0    0    1    0
		0    0    0    1;
	</programlisting>
<para>
operates on any arc which ends in a node called ``hand'' regardless of where it occurs in the model hierarchy. Note that element ``hand'' in these examples above is not a leaf node (primitive solid) in the model graph (With version 4.2 of BRL-CAD and beyond the user will be able to manipulate the matrices on the arcs between primitive solids and their parent combinations).
</para>
<para>
All object parameters in the database are stored using millimeters as the unit of measure. As a result, all matrix operations are carried out in units of millimeters. It is important to remember this when preparing matrices for use with the rt anim command. An example rt session will serve to illustrate the proper use of the anim command.
</para>
<para>
The following shell script ``trans.sh'' runs rt to create two separate images. The first is saved in the file ``trans.pix.1'' and is approximately the view selected for the key-frame ``moss_8'' in Section 2. The ``pix-fb'' utility can be used to display these images on the framebuffer.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
rt -M $* -o trans.pix moss.g 'all.g' 2>> trans.log &#60;&#60;EOF
viewsize 200;
eye_pt 20.0 0.0 100;
orientation 0.0 0.0 0.924 0.383;
start 1;
clean;
end;
start 2;
clean;
anim all.g/tor.r matrix rarc
        1 0 0  0
        0 1 0 80
        0 0 1  0
        0 0 0  1;
end
EOF
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/transboth.gif"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

The second image is saved in ``trans.pix.2'' and is the same except that the matrix on the arc between ``all.g'' and ``tor.r'' is replaced with a new matrix. This matrix has the effect of translating the torus 80 millimeters along the Y axis of the model coordinate system.

</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Preparing_an_Animation_with_Motion">
<title>Preparing an Animation with Motion</title>
<para>
It is time to re-visit the animation sequence we developed in Section 2. We are going to add animation of the objects in the scene to the existing eye-point movement already created. The ellipsoid will be given a constant velocity along a vector which will take it through the center of the torus.
</para>
<para>
To make the ellipsoid pass through the center of the torus we must determine the vector from the center vertex of ``ellipse.s'' to the center vertex of ``tor''
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">% mged moss.g </emphasis>
<literallayout>
BRL-CAD Release 4.1   Graphics Editor (MGED)
    Tue Oct 20 14:19:59 EDT 1992, Compilation 5
    stay@vail:/n/wolf/m/dist4.1/mged
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
attach (nu|tek|tek4109|ps|plot|sgi|X)[nu]? <emphasis role="bold">sgi</emphasis>
ATTACHING sgi (SGI 4d)
Gary Moss's "World on a Platter" (units=mm)
mged> <emphasis role="bold">l all.g</emphasis>
all.g:  all.g (len 6) --
  u platform.r
  u box.r [-23.6989,13.41,8.02399]
  u cone.r [22.0492,12.2349,2.11125e-07]
  u ellipse.r [14.6793,-41.6077,38.7988]
  u tor.r
  u light.r
mged> <emphasis role="bold">l ellipse.s</emphasis>
</programlisting>

</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
ellipse.s:  ellipsoid (ELL)
        V (16.1309, 46.6556, -3.72252)
        A (14.8761, 0, 0) mag=14.8761
        B (0, 8.98026, -8.98026) mag=12.7
        C (0, 8.98026, 8.98026) mag=12.7
        A direction cosines=(0.0, 90, 90)
        A rotation angle=0, fallback angle=0
        B direction cosines=(90.0, 45, 135)
        B rotation angle=90, fallback angle=-45
        C direction cosines=(90.0, 45, 45)
        C rotation angle=90, fallback angle=45

mged> <emphasis role="bold">l tor</emphasis>
</programlisting>

</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
tor:  torus (TOR)
        V (4.91624, -32.8022, 31.7118), r1=25.4 (A), r2=5.08 (H)
        N=(0, 1, 0)
        A=(0, 0, 1)
        B=(1, 0, 0)
        vector to inner edge = (0, 0, 20.32)
        vector to outer edge = (0, 0, 30.48)
mged> <emphasis role="bold">q</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Doing a little vector math we find the vertex of the ``ellipse.s'' as it is found in ``all.g'' is at:
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/v_eqn1.gif" width="300"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<link  xlink:href="../../articles/en/images/ell.mpg">
ell.mpg
</link>

</para>
<para>
Now we subtract this from the origin of ``tor'' to get a vector that will translate ``ellipse.s'' to the center of the torus. This vector is scaled by a factor to 2 to get a ``net displacement'' vector for the ellipsoid.
</para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/v_eqn2.gif" width="400"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>
We can now create a new interpolation table with motion values to be interpolated. The ellipse will start moving half a second after the sequence starts. It will reach its destination half a second before the end of the sequence. Assuming that the time channel is being specified in units of seconds, the following table results:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">chans.ellanim</emphasis>
<programlisting>
		0.5     0          0       0
	7.25  -51.78792  -75.7002 -6.72896
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
The interpolation is done much as it was in Section 2. The data from ``chans.ellanim'' is read into interpolation channels 8, 9, and 10 within tabinterp. The use of linear interpolation ensures that the ellipse will move at a constant rate to its destination.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
  <emphasis role="bold">
% tabinterp &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; chans.all
file chans.vsize 0;
file chans.eyept 1 2 3;
file chans.orient 4 5 6 7;
file chans.ellanim 8 9 10;
times 0 8 3;
interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7;
interp linear 8 9 10;
EOF </emphasis>
cmd: file chans.vsize 0
chan 0:  File 'chans.vsize', Column 1
cmd: file chans.eyept 1 2 3
chan 1:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 1
chan 2:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 2
chan 3:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 3
cmd: file chans.orient 4 5 6 7
chan 4:  File 'chans.orient', Column 1
chan 5:  File 'chans.orient', Column 2
chan 6:  File 'chans.orient', Column 3
chan 7:  File 'chans.orient', Column 4
cmd: file chans.ellanim 8 9 10
chan 8:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 1
chan 9:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 2
chan 10:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 3
cmd: times 0 8 3
cmd: interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
cmd: interp linear 8 9 10
performing interpolations
writing output
%
</programlisting>
An appropriate template such as the one below must be created for use with tabsub.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">
% cat ell.proto</emphasis>
viewsize @0;
eye_pt @1 @2 @3;
orientation @4 @5 @6 @7;
start @(line);
clean;
</programlisting>
<programlisting>
anim all.g/ellipse.r matrix rmul
  1 0 0 @8
  0 1 0 @9
  0 0 1 @10
  0 0 0 1;
end;
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">% tabsub ell.proto chans.all > ell.rtanim</emphasis>
</para>
<para>Note the use of the ``clean'' command to rt at the beginning of each frame in the template. This is required after the ``start'' for each frame in rt animation scripts which use the ``anim'' command. This command tells rt (librt actually) to forget any accumulated animation matrices, thereby restoring the geometry to the form it has in the database.</para>
<para>
We can preview the path that the ellipse will take by creating a plot file which can be used as an overlay in mged. (In version 4.2 of BRL-CAD and beyond the animation sequence can also be viewed using the mged ``preview'' command.)
</para>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">% awk '{print $2+30.8102 " " $3+5.0479 " " $4+35.07628}' chans.ellanim | \
xyz-pl > ell.pl</emphasis>

<emphasis role="bold">% mged moss.g</emphasis>
<literallayout>
BRL-CAD Release 4.2   Graphics Editor (MGED)
    Wed Nov 11 00:36:43 EST 1992, Compilation 770
    mike@wolf.arl.mil:/m/cad/.mged.5d
</literallayout>

<programlisting>
attach (nu|tek|tek4109|ps|plot|sgi|X)[nu]? <emphasis role="bold">sgi</emphasis>
ATTACHING sgi (SGI 4d)
Gary Moss's "World on a Platter" (units=mm)
mged> <emphasis role="bold">e all.g</emphasis>
408 vectors in 0.459896 sec
mged> <emphasis role="bold">overlay ell.pl</emphasis>
db_lookup:  could not find '_PLOT_OVER*'
mged>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
The ``overlay'' command creates pseudo entries of the form ``_PLOT_OVERLAY_'' in the version of the database in memory. These are used to store the vectors of the overlay. They are never actually objects in the geometric database on disk. The next time the overlay command is given, the ``_PLOT_OVER*'' objects are removed and re-created. As a result, the message:
</para>
<para>
db_lookup:  could not find '_PLOT_OVER*
is not a cause for concern.
</para>
<para>
Once again, a postage stamp animation can be created to view the positioning and motion of the camera and objects.
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">
% rt -M -s200 -o ell.pix moss.g 'all.g' >&#38; ell.log &#60; ell.rtanim
% mv ell.pix ell.pix.0
% pixtile -s 200 -S1024 ell.pix | pix-fb -h
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24
% fbanim -h -p 5 200 25 3
</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
<figure>
<mediaobject>
  <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="../../articles/en/images/ell_sm.gif" scale="50"/>
  </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

</para>
<para>
The pixtile program creates a mosaic of the smaller image on the framebuffer. The resultant framebuffer image is animated using the fbanim program.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Computing_Video_Frames">
<title>Computing Video Frames</title>
<section>
<title>Computing Video Frames</title>
<para>
With the animation tables used in the moving ellipsoid example from Section 3, we can create all the frames for a full-speed videotape recording. It is important to avoid file name conflicts between the images created for the postage stamp animation and the frames for the video. Either tell rt to create frames with different names, or the postage stamp frames must be renamed or removed before computing the video frames. Failure to do so will cause rt to believe that the postage stamp frames are completed frames for the video animation. In the following example, the frames will be created with the name ``ell_vid.pix'' to avoid conflict.
</para>
<para>
The arguments to the ``times'' command of tabinterp is slightly different from the previous example. The difference is the number of frames per integer time step (seconds) is increased from 3 to 30.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">% tabinterp &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; chans.all
file chans.vsize 0;
file chans.eyept 1 2 3;
file chans.orient 4 5 6 7;
file chans.ellanim 8 9 10;
times 0 8 30;
interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7;
interp linear 8 9 10;
EOF
</emphasis>
cmd: file chans.vsize 0
chan 0:  File 'chans.vsize', Column 1
cmd: file chans.eyept 1 2 3
chan 1:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 1
chan 2:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 2
chan 3:  File 'chans.eyept', Column 3
cmd: file chans.orient 4 5 6 7
chan 4:  File 'chans.orient', Column 1
chan 5:  File 'chans.orient', Column 2
chan 6:  File 'chans.orient', Column 3
chan 7:  File 'chans.orient', Column 4
cmd: file chans.ellanim 8 9 10
chan 8:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 1
chan 9:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 2
chan 10:  File 'chans.ellanim', Column 3
cmd: times 0 8 30
cmd: interp spline 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
cmd: interp linear 8 9 10
performing interpolations
writing output
The new prototype contains an invocation of the ``framedone.sh'' script to process each image as it is completed.
<emphasis role="bold">% cat ell.proto.2</emphasis>
viewsize @0;
eye_pt @1 @2 @3;
orientation @4 @5 @6 @7;
start @(line);
clean;
anim all.g/ellipse.r matrix rmul
  1 0 0 @8
  0 1 0 @9
  0 0 1 @10
  0 0 0 1;
end;
! framedone.sh ell_vid.pix @(line);
</programlisting>

<emphasis role="bold">% tabsub ell.proto.2 chans.all > ell.rtanim</emphasis>
It is likely to be quite a while before all the images are computed. The rendering should be done as a batch job or detached process using a script similar to the ``ell2.rt'' script below.
<emphasis role="bold">% cat ell2.rt</emphasis>
<programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
rt -M -w1440 -n 972 -V1440:972 -J1 -o ell_vid.pix moss.g all.g 2>> ell.log &#60; ell.rtanim
</programlisting>


<emphasis role="bold">% ell2.rt &#38;</emphasis>
For instance it took almost ten hours to compute and process the 241 1440x972 images of our trivial geometry for an 8 second animation on a Silicon Graphics 4D/280. The final compressed images occupied approximately 39 MB of disk space.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Recording_Videotape">
<title>Recording Videotape</title>
<section>
<title>Recording Videotape</title>
<para>Once all the frames have been computed it is time to record them onto videotape. There are a variety of tools and techniques for accomplishing this task. See [Kennedy91] for a description of some of the variety of equipment which has been used at the Army Research Laboratory for this purpose. Only one of these techniques will be covered here.
</para>
<para>
The Abekas A60 digital video disk stores 25 seconds or 750 frames of video on a high-performance disk. Frames on this disk can be played at full video speed. The A60 provides video output as both CCIR 601 digital video and an analog signal that is either R,G,B or Y,R-Y,B-Y. This analog signal can be readily converted to a format for input to a video tape recorder.
</para>
<para>
Frames can be stored on disk either from a video input or by loading individual frames through an ethernet interface. It is the latter which makes the device particularly useful in creating computer-generated video productions.
</para>
<para>
Under BRL-CAD, access to the Abekas A60 is achieved through the framebuffer library. *|* Conceptually, the A60 has 750 unique framebuffers. The framebuffer device ``/dev/ab'' supports the A60. There are two very important options to this particular framebuffer. The first specifies the host address of the A60 on the TCP/IP network. The host name or address for the A60 is specified by an at-sign ``@'' followed by the appropriate name or address. For example, the framebuffer device ``/dev/ab@vidisk'' specifies that an A60 connected to the network with the host name of ``vidisk'' should be used. The individual frame (or framebuffer) within the A60 is specified by a sharp-sign ``#'' followed by the integer frame number. Thus the full specification of a framebuffer device might be:
</para>
<para>
    /dev/ab@vidisk#27</para>
<para>
This specifies the frame 27 on the Abekas A60 with the host name ``vidisk''. This can be used with any of the framebuffer utilities, such as the ``pix-fb'' utility shown here:  </para>
<para><emphasis role="bold">% pix-fb -F/dev/ab@vidisk#27 -w 720 -n 486 ell_vid.pix.27</emphasis></para><para>
This loads the image file ``ell_vid.pix'' into frame number 27 on the A60 called ``vidisk''.
</para>
<para>
Two more options worth noting are the ``o'' and ``v'' options to the A60 framebuffer device. The ``o'' option indicates that this is an ``output only'' access of the framebuffer. The overhead of retrieving the image already in the framebuffer is skipped when this option is specified. The ``v'' option turns on verbose logging of the access to the framebuffer. This is primarily useful to enable the user to watch the progress of the framebuffer access.
</para>
<para>
This can be generalized into a shell loop to load the 241 ``ell_vid.pix'' images into the A60.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
<emphasis role="bold">
% mv ell_vid.pix ell_vid.pix.0
% foreach i (`loop 0 240`)
? pix-fb -F/dev/abov@vidisk#$i -w 720 -n 486 ell_vid.pix.$i
? end
</emphasis>
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
In this example successive images are loaded into successive video frames (framebuffers) in the A60. As each frame is loaded, the user will see output indicating that the image is converted to YUV format and then loaded into the A60.</para>
<para>
Once the entire sequence (or a 25 second segment) has been loaded into the A60, the sequence can be played and captured using a video tape recorder. A collection of 25 second video sequences can be edited together using a television studio or post-production facility to create longer sequences.
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Conclusion">
<title>Conclusion</title>
<section>
<para>Visualization of models in BRL-CAD need not be restricted to viewing static images. With the use of tabinterp and tabsub the task of creating motion picture sequences becomes quite manageable. The result is that models can be viewed from a variety of positions as they move, change, and evolve over time.
</para>
<para>
The tools discussed represent only one conceptual approach to the problem of specifying frames to be generated for an animation sequence. With the advent of ubiquitous desktop graphics displays, it should be possible to create the sequences using a more visual and interactive approach. Creating tools for this remains an area for further work.
</para>
<para>
The authors wish to thank Mike Muuss and Phil Dykstra for creating the animation capabilities within rt and mged. The authors also thank Mike Muuss for providing the documentation for tabinterp and tabsub that appears in Appendix A and Appendix B respectively.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<bibliography xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'>
<bibliodiv><title>Books</title>
<biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Benson85</abbrev>
  <title>Television Engineering Handbook</title>

  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <personname>
      <firstname>ed. K. Blair </firstname><surname>Benson</surname>
    </personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>McGraw-Hill Book Company</publishername>
  </publisher>
  <copyright><year>1986</year></copyright>
  <biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-07-004779-0</biblioid>

</biblioentry>
 <biblioentry>

  <abbrev>Deitz89</abbrev>
  <title>An Integrated Environment for Army Navy and Air Force Target Description Support'', in The Proceedings of the Tenth Annual Symposium on Survivability and Vulnerability of the American Defense Preparedness Association,</title>

  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <personname>
      <firstname>P. H.</firstname><surname> Deitz</surname>
      </personname>
      </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
    <firstname>W. H.</firstname><surname>  Mermagen</surname>
      </personname>
      </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
    <firstname>Jr., P. R.</firstname><surname>  Stay</surname>
      </personname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>held at the Naval Ocean Systems Center, San Diego, CA, May 10-12, 1988.
</publishername>
  </publisher>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
 <title>The Ballistic Research Laboratory CAD Package Release 4.0 Manuals, Volume I, BRL-CAD Philosophy'' Page V1S04A00</title>
</biblioentry>

 <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Foley92</abbrev>
  <title>Computer Graphics, Principles and Practice</title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <personname>
      <firstname>James D.</firstname><surname> Foley</surname>
       </personname>
       </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
      <firstname>Andries </firstname><surname>van Dam</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>Steven K.</firstname><surname> Feiner</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>John F. </firstname><surname>Hughes</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>   Addison-Wesley Publishing Company   </publishername>
  </publisher>
  <copyright><year>1992</year></copyright>
  <biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-201-12110-7</biblioid>
</biblioentry>
 <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Kennedy91</abbrev>
  <title>``Video Hardware for Making Movies'', in Proceedings of the 1991 BRL-CAD Symposium</title>
    <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>Charles M. </firstname><surname>Kennedy</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername> held at Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland</publishername>
  </publisher>
  <copyright><year>May 7-9 1991</year></copyright>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
    <title>``The Ballistic Research Laboratory CAD Package Release 4.0 Manuals, Volume V, Analyst's Manual'' Page V5S14A01</title>
</biblioentry>
 <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Muuss88a</abbrev>
  <title>``Understanding the Preparation and Analysis of Solid Models'', in ``Techniques for Computer Graphics'',</title>

    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>ed: Rogers &#32; Earnshaw, Springer Verlag,</firstname>
        </personname>
        </author>
        <address>New York,</address> <pagenums>pages 109-172. </pagenums>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>M.  </firstname><surname>Muuss</surname>
</personname>
</author>
    </authorgroup>
<biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-387-96492-4 also ISBN 3-540-96492-4</biblioid>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
<title>``The Ballistic Research Laboratory CAD Package Release 4.0 Manuals, Volume V, Analyst's Manual'' Page V5S08A05.
</title>
</biblioentry>
 <biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Muuss88b</abbrev>
  <title>``The RT Lighting Model''. in Proceedings of the BRL-CAD Symposium '88,held at the Ballistic Research Laboratory, Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland,  </title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>M.  </firstname><surname>Muuss</surname>
</personname>
</author>
    </authorgroup>
    <biblioset>
  <copyright><year>June 28, 1988.</year></copyright>
<biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-387-96492-4 also ISBN 3-540-96492-4</biblioid>
</biblioset>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
<title>The Ballistic Research Laboratory CAD Package Release 4.0 Manuals,</title>
<volumenum> Volume V Analyst's Manual</volumenum>
<pagenums>V5S10A03.</pagenums>
</biblioentry>

<biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Muuss90a</abbrev>
  <title>`Workstations, Networking, Distributed Graphics, and Parallel Processing'' in Computer Graphics Techniques: Theory and Practice,  </title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>M. J.</firstname><surname> Muuss</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>ed. D. F.</firstname><surname> Rogers,</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>R. A. </firstname><surname> Earnshaw, </surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <copyright><year>1990.</year></copyright>

<biblioid class="isbn">ISBN 0-387-97237-4</biblioid>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
<title>``The Ballistic Research Laboratory CAD Package Release 4.0 Manuals,</title>
<volumenum> Volume V, Analyst's Manual''</volumenum>
<pagenums>Page V5S10A03.</pagenums>
</biblioentry>

<biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Newman79</abbrev>
  <title>Principles of Interactive Computer Graphics, 2nd ed.,  </title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>W. M. </firstname><surname>Newman</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>R. F. </firstname><surname>Sproull</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>McGraw-Hill, New York,</publishername>
  </publisher>

  <copyright><year>1979.</year></copyright>

<biblioid class="isbn"> ISBN 0-07-046338-7</biblioid>
</biblioentry>

<biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Rogers90</abbrev>
  <title>Mathematical Elements for Computer Graphics, 2nd ed</title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>D. F. </firstname><surname>Rogers</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    <author>
<personname>
      <firstname>J. A. </firstname><surname>Adams</surname>
</personname>
    </author>
    </authorgroup>
  <publisher>
    <publishername>McGraw-Hill, New York,</publishername>
  </publisher>

  <copyright><year>1990.</year></copyright>

<biblioid class="isbn"> ISBN 0-07-053529-9 (hard cover) ISBN 0-07-053530-2 (soft cover)</biblioid>
</biblioentry>
<biblioentry>
  <abbrev>Shoemake85</abbrev>
  <title>Animating Rotation with Quaternion Curves Computer Graphics,</title>
<volumenum> . 18</volumenum>  <volumenum>No. 3,</volumenum> <copyright><year> July 1985,</year> <holder>SIGGraph '85 Proceedings</holder></copyright>
</biblioentry>
</bibliodiv>
</bibliography>
</section>
<section xml:id="Appendix_A">
<title>Appendix A</title>
<section xml:id='tabinterp'>

<title>NAME</title>
<para>tabinterp - combine and interpolate multiple data files to create an animation script</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SYNOPSIS1">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<para><emphasis role="bold">tabinterp > table.final</emphasis></para>
</section>
<section xml:id="DESCRIPTION1">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>tabinterp reads a series of commands from standard input which designate what parts of various data files should be used as input tables for various channels of animation parameters. Commands may extend across multiple lines, and are semi-colon (';') terminated. Each channel is then interpolated using one of a variety of interpolation techniques to provide an output table which has one line for each time step.</para>
<para>
The overall notion is based on parameter tables. Each table is arranged so that every row (line) represents the state of some set of parameters at a given time. Each column of the table represents a single parameter, or data channel, with the left-most column always representing time.
</para>
<para>
The first task in preparing to use tabinterp (1) is to assign specific purposes to each channel in the output table. For example, channels 0, 1, and 2 might be used to represent the X, Y, and Z positions of an object, respectively, while channels 3, 4, and 5 might be used to represent the "aim point" of the virtual camera, while channel 6 might be used to represent the brightness of one of the objects or light sources, and channel 7 might be used to represent the zoom factor (viewsize) of the virtual camera. Once the channel assignment has been decided upon, the source file containing the table of raw values for each channel must be identified. Several output channels may get their raw values from different columns of a single input table (file). Up to 64 columns of input may appear in an input table.
</para>
<para>
For each file which contains an input table, the file command is given to load the necessary columns of raw values into the output channels. If a channel number in the list is given as a minus ('-'), that input column is skipped. Using the output channel assignments given above as an example, if an input table named "table1" existed which consisted of five columns of values representing (time, brightness, objX, objY, objZ), then these values would be loaded with this command:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
file filename chan_num(s);

   file table1 6 0 1 2;
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
This command indicates that from the file "table1", the current time and four columns of parameters should be read into the raw output table, with the first input column representing the time, the second input column representing the value for output channel 6 (brightness), the third input column representing the value for output channel 0 (objX), etc. Each row of the input file must fit on a single (newline terminated) line of text, with columns separated by one or more spaces and tabs.
</para>
<para>
After all the file commands have been given, it is necessary to define over what range of time values found in the raw output table will be processed, and how many rows of interpolated output should be produced for each second (time unit) in the input file. This can be thought of as the "frames per second" rate of the interpolation, and is usually set to 24 for film (cine) work, 30 for NTSC video, and 60 for field-at-a-time NTSC video. Any positive integer value is acceptable. (In fact, any time unit can be used, as the time channel is dimensionless. Nothing depends on the units being seconds.) For example, the command:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
 times start stop fps;
   times 1 7.3 24;
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
would cause tabinterp to process data values from time 1 second to 7.3 seconds, producing 24 output rows uniformly separated in time for the passage of each second.
</para>
<para>
After the times command has been given, it is necessary to associate an interpolator procedure or a "value generator" procedure with each output channel. The available interpolator procedures are: step, linear, spline, cspline, and quat For example, the command:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
  interp type chan_num(s);

   interp linear 3 4 5;
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
would indicate that output channels 3, 4, and 5 (representing the camera aim point) would be processed using linear interpolation. If only a starting and ending values are given in the input (i.e. the input file had only two rows), then this is an easy way of moving something from one place to another. In this case, if more than two input rows had been provided, there would be a noticeable "jerk" as the camera passed through each of the input parameter values, an effect which is rarely desired. To avoid this, the spline interpolator can be used, which fits an interpolating spline (with open end conditions) through the given data values, resulting in smooth motion. If the starting and ending values are the same, a continuous spline (with closed end conditions) can be used instead by specifying cspline. Both of the spline interpolators require at least three rows to have been provided in the input file.</para>
<para>
If the output values are to "jump" from one input value to the next, (i.e. no interpolation at all is desired), then specify step. This can be useful for having lights switch between several intensities (for example, a 3-way bulb with 30, 70, and 100 watt settings), or for having objects "teleport" into position at just the right moment.
</para>
<para>
The interpolation method indicated on the interp command is assigned to all the output channels listed. One exception to this rule is the quat (Quaternion) interpolator. Quaternions are used to describe an orientation in space, and can be most easily thought of as containing a vector in space, from which they obtain a pointing direction, and a "twist" angle around that vector. To do this, quaternions are processed in blocks of four channels, which must be numbered sequentially (e.g. channels 7, 8, 9, 10). Giving the command
</para>
<para>
interp quat 7 15;
</para>
<para>
assigns the quaternion interpolator to two blocks of four channels, the block starting with channel 7 (e.g. channels 7, 8, 9, 10), and the block starting with channel 15.
tabinterp is strictly an interpolator. It will not extrapolate values before the first input value, nor after the last output value. The first or last value is simple repeated.
</para>
<para>
In addition to interpolation, it is possible to specify rate and acceleration based output channels. In cases where the exact running time of a scene is not known, the rate and accel commands can be quite useful. One command is given for each output channel. For example,
</para>
<para>

   rate chan_num init_value incr_per_sec;
</para>
<para>
   rate 6 1.5 0.5;
</para>
<para>
says to make channel 6 a rate based channel, with the initial value (at time=0) of 1.5, linearly increasing with an increment of 0.5 for the passing of every additional second. In this case, the value would be 2.0 at time=1, 2.5 at time=2, and so on. This can be used to establish linear changes where it is the increment and not the final value that is important. For example, the rotation angle of a helicopter rotor could be specified in this way.
Similarly, the command
</para>
<para>

   accel chan_num init_value mult_per_sec;
</para>
<para>
   accel 5 10 2;
</para>
<para>
says to make channel 5 an acceleration based channel, with the initial value at time=0 of 10.0, which is multiplied by 2 for every additional second. In this case, the value would be 20.0 at time=1, and 40.0 at time=2. This can be useful to create constant acceleration, such as a car accelerating smoothly away from its position at rest in front of a stop sign. If the initial value is zero, all subsequent values will also be zero.
</para>
<para>
Sometimes it is desirable to create an output channel which looks ahead (or behind) in time. For example, a good way to animate a rocket flying on a complex course would be to simply animate the position of the base of the rocket, and then look ahead in time to see where the rocket is going to go next in order to determine where to aim the nose of the rocket (by rotating it). This kind of lookahead is easily implemented using the next command. (See also the fromto directive in tabsub (1) which is used in conjunction with this). The command
</para>
<para>
   next dest_chan src_chan nsamp;
</para>
<para>
   next 4 5 +3;
</para>
<para>
says to fill channel 4 with the values that will be present in channel 5 at 3 output rows later on. Negative values are also permitted. Since the lookahead is defined in terms of output rows rather than time steps, this means that the values generated for this column will change as the frames per second (fps) value on the times command is changed. This is almost always the effect which is desired, since as the temporal resolution of the interpolation is increased, the accuracy of the look-ahead will increase as well. However, if the effect desired is one of "have the camera track where the main actor was three seconds ago", then the number of steps given here will have to be changed when the fps value is changed. Be careful of the values generated for the last (or first) nsamp output rows. Looking forward or backward in time beyond the bounds of the interpolation will retrieve the last (or first) output values. So it takes nsamp output rows to "prime the pumps".
</para>
<para>
Whenever a pound sign ('#') is encountered in the command input, all characters from there to the end of the input line are discarded. This is the same commenting convention used in the Bourne shell, sh (1).
</para>
<para>
When tabinterp encounters an end-of-file on its standard input, it computes the requested interpolations, and writes the output table on standard output. If no values have been assigned to an output channel, then the value given is a single dot ('.'). This preserves the positional white-space-separated columns nature of the output table. If this column is read as a numeric value by a downstream program, it will be accepted as a valid floating-point zero.
</para>
<para>
As an aid to debugging, it is possible to dump the raw values of columns of the output table before the interpolation is run:
</para>
<para>

   idump;
</para>
<para>
   idump chan_num(s);
</para>
<para>
If no output channel numbers are given, all channels are dumped, otherwise only the indicated channels are dumped.
The help command can be given to get a list of all available commands. (Don't forget the semi-colon).
</para>

</section>
<section xml:id="EXAMPLE1">
<title>EXAMPLE</title>
<para>
What follows here is a Bourne shell script which will generate two input tables using "here documents", and will then produce an interpolated output table of 8 channels.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
#!/bin/sh
cat &#60;&#60;   EOF &#62; table.aim
-1   0 0 0    42 250
3    1 2 3    28 300
7    3 4 5    17 350
EOF
cat &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; table.obj
0    17 38 44
2    43 47 3
4    99 23 18
EOF
tabinterp &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; table.final
# Channel allocations:
#  0,1,2  objX, objY, objZ  main actor position
#  3,4,5  aimX, aimY, aimZ  camera aim point
#      6  light brightness
#      7  viewsize
#
# Input table column allocations:
#   time, aimX, aimY, aimZ, junk, viewsize
file table.aim 3 4 5 - 7;
#
# Input table column allocations:
#   time, objX, objY, obxZ
file table.obj 0 1 2;
# Channel 6 is not read in here,
#   but is rate base.
#
# Tstart, Tstop, fps
times 0 4 30;
#
# Assign interpolators to output channels
rate 6 1000 50;
# 1000 lumen bulb keeps getting brighter...
interp linear 0 1 2;
interp spline 3 4 5;
interp spline 7;
EOF
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
Try clipping this example out of the manual page (usually found in /usr/brlcad/man/man1/tabinterp.1) and running it. This example will be continued in the manual page for tabsub (1).
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="POST_PROCESSING">
<title>POST PROCESSING</title>
<para>Because both the input and output tables consist of a single line of text for each time step, many of the standard UNIX tools can be brought to bear to assist in creating an animation. To visualize the exact position taken by the aim point in the example (output channels 3, 4, 5), a UNIX-plot file of that trajectory can be created with:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
   cut -f5,6,7 table.final | xyz-pl > aim.pl

   cut -f1,5,6,7 table.final | txyz-pl > aim.pl
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
Similarly, the position of the main object can be viewed with
</para>
<para>
   cut -f2,3,4 table.final | xyz-pl > obj.pl
</para>
<para>
tabinterp uses 0-based column numbering, while cut uses 1-based column numbering. Also, the first output column from tabinterp is always the time. The 0-th data column comes second.
The plot file just created can be viewed using pl-fb (1) or pl-sgi (1), or it can be viewed in mged (1) by giving the command
</para>
<para>
   overlay aim.pl
</para>
<para>
to mged. If the model geometry is brought into view using the mged e command, then the camera aim track (or any other spatial parameter) can be viewed in direct relationship to the three dimensional geometry which is going to be animated.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="PREPARING_INPUT_TABLES">
<title>PREPARING INPUT TABLES</title>
<para>The mged (1) savekey and saveview commands can be very useful for creating the input tables necessary for driving tabinterp. The details of doing this are beyond the scope of this manual page.
</para>
<para>
The awk (1) command can also be useful for routing through the output files of existing scientific analysis programs, and extracting the few gems of data buried in the heaps of "printout".
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SEE_ALSO">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
tabsub(1), xyz-pl(1), txyz-pl(1), cut(1), paste(1), rt(1), mged(1)</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="DIAGNOSTICS">
<title>DIAGNOSTICS</title>
<para>
In its present form, the program is a bit verbose, reporting on the progress of each command on standard error. This behavior will probably be placed under control of a -v flag in a future version.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="BUGS">
<title>BUGS</title>
<para>
You can't grep dead trees.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="AUTHOR">
<title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>
Michael John Muuss
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SOURCE">
<title>SOURCE</title>
<para>
The U. S. Army Research Laboratory
Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland  21005
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="BUG_REPORTS">
<title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>
Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic mail to devs@brlcad.org
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Appendix_B">
<title>Appendix B</title>
<section xml:id="NAME">
<title>NAME</title>
<para>tabsub - macro expand an input table into an animation script</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SYNOPSIS">
<title>SYNOPSIS</title>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">tabsub template_file &#60; table.final &#62;&#62; script</emphasis>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="DESCRIPTION">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>
tabsub takes as input a data table on standard input (such as might have been produced by tabinterp (1) or similar tool), and a template file named on the command line. For each row (line) of the input table, one complete copy of the template file is output on standard output. As the template is output, any macro invocations in the template file are replaced with the data values from the input table's current row. In the input table, any blank lines or lines with a pound sign ('#') as the first character are ignored, allowing comments to be added to the input table.
</para>
<para>
Macro invocations in the template file all begin with an at-sign ('@'). In order to send an at-sign through to the output, a second at-sign must immediately follow it, e.g. when '@@' is encountered in the template, a single '@' is output. To output the data value found in a given channel in the current input row of the data table, the at-sign is followed by the channel number, e.g. to output the value in channel four, specify '@4', and to output the value in channel 42, specify '@42'. In some circumstances it my be desirable to highlight the difference between channel value substitution, and literal numeric values. To facilitate this, the channel number may be enclosed in parenthesis to explicitly delimit the macro invocation. For example, channel four could also be specified as '@(4)', and channel 42 as '@(42)'. This second notation is generally preferred.
</para>
<para>
The tabsub program is intended primarily for creating scripts relating to animation. To facilitate this, a variety of more complex macros also exist.
</para>
<para>
   @(line)
</para>
<para>
will output the row (line) number of the input table which is currently being processed, with the first line being numbered zero. This is useful for creating frame numbers, or other sequence tags in the output.
</para>
<para>
   @(time)
</para>
<para>
will output the time value which is always found in the left-most column of the current row.
The more complex macros can also take arguments. If the first character of an argument is an at-sign ('@') (or percent-sign ('%'), for backwards compatibility), then the number that follows signifies an input channel substitution as before. Otherwise the value is taken literally.
</para>
<para>
The rot macro is used to convert three Euler angles given in degrees into a rotation expressed as a 4x4 homogeneous transformation matrix.
</para>
<para>
   @(rot x_angle y_angle z_angle)
</para>
<para>
The arguments may be either numeric constants, column value macros, or a combination of both. The matrix is generated by calling the librt (3) routine mat_angles which performs the rotation around the Z axis first, then Y, then X. For example, the macro
</para>
<para>
   @(rot 0 0 45)
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting>
creates the following matrix, a 45 degree rotation about Z:
7.071067812e-01 -7.071067812e-01 0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00
7.071067812e-01 7.071067812e-01 -0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00
0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00
0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+00
  </programlisting>

</para>
<para>
Similarly, the macro
</para>
<para>
   @(rot @4 @5 90)
</para>
<para>
creates a rotation matrix where the angle of rotation around X is taken from input channel four, the Y angle is taken from input channel five, and the Z angle is fixed at 90 degrees.
</para>
<para>
The xlate macro converts three distances (which must be specified in millimeters if the output script is destined for processing by rt (1) or mged (1)) into a translation expressed as a 4x4 homogeneous transformation matrix.
</para>
<para>
   @(xlate dx dy dz)
</para>
<para>
The matrix is generated by invoking the C macro MAT_DELTAS found in h/vmath.h. For example, the macro
</para>
<para>
   @(xlate 100 -20 300)
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting>

creates the following matrix:
1.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+02
0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 -2.000000000e+01
0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+00 3.000000000e+02
0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 0.000000000e+00 1.000000000e+00
  </programlisting>

</para>
<para>
Similarly, the macro
</para>
<para>
 @(xlate 13 @7 0)
</para>
<para>
creates a matrix where the origin is translated 13 units (mm) in X, and the number of units found in input channel 7 in Y. No translation occurs in Z.
</para>
<para>
The orient macro combines the operation of the rot zand xlate macros, and also offers optional scaling. The invocation is one of:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
   @(orient tx ty tz rx ry rz)

   @(orient tx ty tz rx ry rz scale)
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
where all rotation is done first, then the translation, and then the scaling (if given).
The ae command converts mged (1) style azimuth and elevation angle given in degrees into a rotation expressed as a 4x4 homogeneous transformation matrix.
</para>
<para>
   @(ae azimuth elevation)
</para>
<para>
The matrix is generated by calling the librt (3) routine mat_ae
The quat command converts a quaternion into a 4x4 homogeneous transformation matrix.
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
   @(quat x y z w)
The fromto command is used to rotate the given axis to point in the same direction as the vector formed by subtracting the 'next' point from the 'cur' point.

   @(fromto axis cur_x cur_y cur_z next_x next_y next_z)
</literallayout>
The axis argument must be one of these six strings: +X, -X, +Y, -Y, +Z, -Z, where the axis letter is capitalized. The matrix is generated by calling the librt (3) routine mat_fromto where the 'from' argument is derived from the axis given, and the 'to' argument is the unit-length difference 'next'-'cur'.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="Example">
<title>Example</title>
<para>Based upon the example started in the manual page for tabinterp (1), here is a Bourne shell script which will generate the necessary template file using a "here document", and then process the 8-channel output table left in the file "table.final".
</para>
<para>
  <programlisting>

#!/bin/sh
# This template will be instantiated
#  once for each frame to be made.
cat &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; template

start @(line);
clean;
lookat_pt @(3) @(4) @(5);
viewsize @(7);
anim all.g/actor.g matrix rmul
 @(xlate @0 @1 @2);
anim all.g/light.r material rparam
 inten=@(6) angle=70 invisible=1;
end;
! framedone.sh actor.pix.@(line);

EOF
# This is the start of the animation script,
# which will be appended to below.
cat &#60;&#60; EOF &#62; script
viewsize 3000;
eye_pt -4.429280979044739e+03
  -1.633722950749571e+03
  -1.624787858562220e+03;
orientation 5.435778713738288e-01
  4.980973490458696e-01
  4.564221286261679e-01
  4.980973490458693e-01;
#frame data follows
EOF
# Append the data for each frame
tabsub ./template &#60; table.final >> script
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
The frame number is taken from the input table line number, and substituted into the start command. The main actor position is taken from channels 0,1,2 and applied (as an "articulation") to the matrix located along the arc between "all.g" and "actor.g" in the mged database. The camera (eye) position stays fixed for this animation, but the camera orientation is changed by substituting channels 3,4,5 into the lookat_pt command, and the viewsize (zoom lens setting) is changed by substituting channel 7 into the viewsize command. The argument to the light region's material property string is replaced with a new string that spells out the current light parameters. After the end command, a rt (1) shell escape is constructed, which will run a script called "framedone.sh" with the given argument (which has been arranged to be the file name of the pix (5) file that rt (1) just wrote, so that it can be post-processed, compressed, sent to a video recorder, etc.
</para>
<para>
Try clipping this example out of the manual page (usually found in /usr/brlcad/man/man1/tabsub.1) and running it.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="EXAMPLE2">
<title>EXAMPLE2</title>
<para>
In the tabinterp (1) manual page, mention was made of animating the flight of a rocket. This partial example outlines how that might be accomplished.
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
tabinterp &#60;&#60; EOF > rocket.final
# Channel allocations:
#   0,1,2 position of base of rocket
#   3,4,5 next position of base of rocket
#
# Input table column allocations:  time, X, Y, Z
file rocket.table 0 1 2;
#
times 0 4 60;
#
# Assign interpolators to output channels
interp spline 0 1 2;
#
# Get +1 "look ahead" on values, for auto-guidance
next 3 0 1;
next 4 1 1;
next 5 2 1;
EOF
cat &#60;&#60; EOF > rocket.template

start @(line);
clean;
anim all.g/rot.g matrix rmul
 @(xlate @0 @1 @2);
anim rot.g/rocket.g matrix rmul
  @(fromto +Z @0 @1 @2 @3 @4 @5);
end;
EOF
tabsub ./rocket.template &#60; rocket.final >> script
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
The items worthy of note are the use of the tabinterp (1) next command to place the position look-ahead into channels 3,4,5 and the matching use of the tabsub fromto macro to convert the current and next positions into an appropriate rotation. In this case, the central axis of the rocket as found in the mged (1) database rises up the +Z axis. Translating the rocket into position is handled one matrix higher up the tree, using the xlate macro.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="POST_PROCESSING2">
<title>POST PROCESSING</title>
<para>
rt style animation scripts can be processed by rt (1) and remrt (1) by giving the -M option on the command line, and providing the script on standard input. For example, the rocket animation might be run like this:
</para>
<para>
<literallayout>
rt -M -V4:3 -w1440 -n972 -p90 -o rocket.pix \
  rocket.g all.g &#60; script
</literallayout>
</para>
<para>
to produce images in NTSC ("Academy" 4:3) aspect ratio at double the normal resolution, suitable for later processing by pixhalve (1).
</para>
<para>
The same animation can be previewed in near real-time using mged (1). For this example, mged (1) would be started with
</para>
<para>
   mged rocket.g
</para>
<para>
followed by attaching to an appropriate display device. Then, these commands would be given:
</para>
<para>
   e all.g
   preview script
</para>
<para>
mged (1) will process each frame as fast as it can, and update the screen.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SEE_ALSO2">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
tabinterp(1), xyz-pl(1), txyz-pl(1), cut(1), paste(1), rt(1), mged(1)
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="BUGS2">
<title>BUGS</title>
<para>
There is presently a compiled-in limit of 1023 channels in the input table.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="AUTHOR2">
<title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>
Michael John Muuss
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="SOURCE2">
<title>SOURCE</title>
<para>
The U. S. Army Research Laboratory
Aberdeen Proving Ground, Maryland  21005
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="BUG_REPORTS2">
<title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>
Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic mail to devs@brlcad.org
</para>
</section>
</section>
<section xml:id="Chains">
<title>
Chains
</title>
<section xml:id='vsize'>
<title>chains.vsize</title>
<para>
<programlisting>
0	2.000000000000000e+02
0.75	2.000000000000000e+02
1.75	2.000000000000000e+02
4	2.000000000000000e+02
6.25	2.000000000000000e+02
7.25	2.000000000000000e+02
8	2.000000000000000e+02
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id='eypet'>
<title>Chans Eypet</title>
<para>
<programlisting>
0	9.071067811865476e+01	7.071067811865474e+01	0.000000000000000e+00
0.75	9.066760308408352e+01	7.066760308408351e+01	3.489949670250149e+00
1.75	8.963642403200188e+01	6.963642403200188e+01	1.736481776669301e+01
4	6.999999999999997e+01	4.999999999999999e+01	7.071067811865471e+01
6.25	3.227878039689727e+01	1.227878039689727e+01	9.848077530122080e+01
7.25	2.246776707783357e+01	2.467767077833573e+00	9.993908270190957e+01
8	2.000000000000000e+01	0.000000000000000e+00	9.999999999999999e+01

</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id='orient'>
<title>chans.orient</title>
<para>
<programlisting>
0	2.705980500730985e-01	6.532814824381883e-01	6.532814824381883e-01	2.705980500730985e-01
0.75	2.658342495283891e-01	6.417806505547106e-01	6.645833184536355e-01	2.752794238304135e-01
1.75	2.459841687565966e-01	5.938583163412476e-01	7.077327819916303e-01	2.931525168369743e-01
4	1.464466094067262e-01	3.535533905932737e-01	8.535533905932737e-01	3.535533905932737e-01
6.25	3.335305878500257e-02	8.052140686538031e-02	9.203638919632243e-01	3.812272063696535e-01
7.25	6.678746798450165e-03	1.612392110047428e-02	9.237388211835743e-01	3.826251478247717e-01
8	0.000000000000000e+00	0.000000000000000e+00	9.238795325112867e-01	3.826834323650898e-01

</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id='all'>
<title>Chans All</title>
<para>
<programlisting>
0	200	90.7107	70.7107	0	0.270598	0.653281	0.653281	0.270598
0.33333	200	90.6992	70.6992	1.11757	0.26908		0.649617	0.656908	0.2721
0.66667	200	90.6764	70.6764	2.87542	0.266677	0.643815	0.662597	0.274457
1	200	90.6193	70.6193	5.86093	0.262565	0.633889	0.672216	0.278441
1.33333	200	90.4026	70.4026	10.2013	0.256455	0.619137	0.685929	0.284121
1.66667	200	89.8485	69.8485	15.7869	0.248331	0.599525	0.703018	0.291199
2	200	88.7905	68.7905	22.4928	0.238198	0.575062	0.722757	0.299376
2.33333	200	87.1626	67.1626	30.0787	0.226209	0.546117	0.744384	0.308334
2.66667	200	84.9511	64.9511	38.245	0.212592	0.513243	0.76712		0.317752
3	200	82.1425	62.1425	46.6914	0.197578	0.476996	0.790185	0.327305
3.33333	200	78.7234	58.7234	55.118	0.181396	0.437929	0.812799	0.336672
3.66667	200	74.6804	54.6804	63.2244	0.164276	0.396596	0.834181	0.345529
4	200	70	50	70.7107	0.146447	0.353553	0.853553	0.353553
4.33333	200	64.7064	44.7064	77.3298	0.128166	0.309419	0.870291	0.360486
4.66667	200	58.9743	38.9743	83.0475	0.109797	0.265073	0.884398	0.36633
5	200	53.0158	33.0158	87.8828	0.091731	0.221458	0.896032	0.371149
5.33333	200	47.0433	27.0433	91.8548	0.0743588	0.179518	0.905354	0.37501
5.66667	200	41.2689	21.2689	94.9823	0.0580711	0.140196	0.912522	0.377979
6	200	35.9048	15.9048	97.2844	0.0432589	0.104436	0.917696	0.380122
6.33333	200	31.1631	11.1631	98.7807	0.0303124	0.0731806	0.921036	0.381506
6.66667	200	27.2134	7.21344	99.5643	0.0195628	0.0472287	0.922821	0.382245
7	200	24.1443	4.1443	99.8707	0.011226	0.0271019	0.923556	0.382549
7.33333	200	22.0332	2.03323	99.9515	0.00550101	0.0132806	0.923773	0.382639
7.66667	200	20.7902	0.79024	99.9837	0.00213547	0.00515548	0.923852	0.382672
8	200	20	0	100	0		0		0.92388		0.382683
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
</section>
</article>
