<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<section>
<title>Application Development with BRL-CAD</title>
<para>
<link xlink:href="../presentations/en/brlcad-app-devel_2.html">
 <inlinemediaobject>
 	   <imageobject condition="web">
      <imagedata fileref="../presentations/images/brlcad_app_devel.png"/>
        </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>
</link>
</para>
<para>
A suite of utilities capable of interactively displaying, editing, and interrogating geometric models is known as BRL-CAD. BRL-CAD has become a powerful constructive solid geometry (CSG) modeling package. The package includes a large collection of tools and utilities including an interactive geometry editor, ray tracing and generic framebuffer libraries, a network-distributed image-processing and signal-processing capability, and an embedded scripting language.
</para>
<para>
A particular strength of the package lies in its ability to build and analyze realistic models of complex objects using a relatively small set of "primitive shapes." Another strength of the package is the speed of its ray tracer, which is one of the fastest in existence. Finally, BRL-CAD users can accurately model objects on scales ranging from the subatomic through the galactic and get "all the details, all the time."
BRL-CAD has been used for a wide variety of engineering and graphics applications. BRL-CAD is basically a collection of libraries, tools, and utilities that work together to create, raytrace, and interrogate geometry and manipulate files and data.
In BRL-CAD library, Each library fits into one of three categories:
<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
<para>
creating and/or editing geometry,
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
  raytracing geometry
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
	<para>
  image handling.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
The application side of BRL-CAD also offers a number of tools and utilities.
rt – the main raytracer for rendering images in BRL-CAD.
nirt – a package for firing rays interactively and getting information about what the rays run into.
remrt – a network-distributed ray tracing package.
</programlisting>
</para>
</section>
</article>
