<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="burst1" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>BURST</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv xml:id="burst_name">
    <refname>burst</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Prepare shotline and burst point library inputs for PDAM.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="burst_synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>burst</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-P</arg>
      <arg rep="norepeat">input_file</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

  <para>
    <command>burst</command> uses LIBRT raytracing to prepare inputs to the
    Point Burst Damage Assessment Model (PDAM) in the form of shotline files
    and burst point library files.  For more information about PDAM, see
    <link xlink:href="http://www.dtic.mil/docs/citations/ADA273171">ARL-CR-69:
    A Guide to FASTGEN Target Geometric Modeling</link>.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <command>burst</command> program is designed to allow many options to be
    configured before any outputs are calculated. Unless otherwise stated in the
    individual command descriptions, a given command will nullify any previous
    occurrence of the same directive until an <command>execute</command> command
    is given. For instance, the command <command>target-file</command>
    <parameter class='command'>tank1</parameter> followed by
    <command>target-file</command> <parameter class='command'>tank2</parameter> will
    nullify the reference to tank1. It is also important to remember that the
    <command>units</command> command impacts how subsequent physical quantities
    are read by other commands, and the output from an <command>execute</command>
    command will use whatever units are current. Once the input parameters are specified,
    the <command>execute</command> command will start a run.  Output will be
    reported using the current setting for <command>units</command> at the
    time the <command>execute</command> is run.  Many runs may occur during an instance of
    the <command>burst</command> program. One such instance is referred to as a session.
  </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="coil_options"><title>OPTIONS:</title>

  <variablelist remap="TP">
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>-p</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Plot points (default).
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>-P</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Plot lines.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_commands">
    <title>COMMANDS</title>
    <para>
      Commands are defined via an input file and passed to burst when it is first invoked.
      All commands to burst are composed of one or more words connected by hyphens and each command
      may require one or more arguments that must be separated by either spaces or tabs. A line that
      begins with the ‘#’ symbol is considered a comment and will be ignored. The following table
      provides a brief overview of the available commands, with subsequent sections covering key
      areas in more detail.  In the table, flag arguments have yes or no values, an angle is expressed
      in degrees as a floating-point quantity, distances and coordinates such as X, Y, Z, left,
      right, etc. are also floating-point numbers, and count represents an integer. Square brackets
      delimit optional arguments.

      <table>
	<title>Burst Commands</title>
	<tgroup cols="3">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Command</entry>
	      <entry>Arguments</entry>
	      <entry>Description</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry><command>attack-direction</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>azim_angle</parameter> <parameter class='command'>elev_angle</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>specify azimuth and elevation of attack relative to target</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>burst-air-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input burst air idents from file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>burst-armor-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input burst armor idents from file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>burst-coordinates</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>X</parameter> <parameter class='command'>Y</parameter> <parameter class='command'>Z</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input single burst point location in target coordinates</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>burst-distance</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>distance</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>offset burst point along shotline</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>burst-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>output burst point library to file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>cell-size</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>distance</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>specify shotline separation (equidistant horizontal and vertical)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>color-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input ident to color mapping from file (for graphics)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>cone-half-angle</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>angle</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>specify limiting angle for spall ray generation</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>critical-comp-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input critical component idents from file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>deflect-spall-cone</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>flag</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>deflect axis of spall cone half way towards exit normal</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>dither-cells</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>flag</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>if yes, randomly offset shotline within grid cell</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>enclose-target</command></entry>
	      <entry></entry>
	      <entry>generate rectangular grid of shotlines for full target envelope</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>enclose-portion</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>left</parameter> <parameter class='command'>right</parameter> <parameter class='command'>bottom</parameter> <parameter class='command'>top</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>generate partial envelope by specifying grid boundaries</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>error-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>divert all diagnostics to file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>execute</command></entry>
	      <entry></entry>
	      <entry>initiate a run (no output produced without this command)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>grid-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>save shotline locations (Y' Z') in file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>ground-plane</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>flag [Z +X -X +Y -Y]</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>if yes, burst on ground</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>help</command></entry>
	      <entry>display a list of available commands</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>histogram-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>write hit frequency histogram to file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>image-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>generate frame buffer image on a specified file or device</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>input-2d-shot</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>Y'</parameter> <parameter class='command'>Z'</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input single shotline location as grid offsets</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>input-3d-shot</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>X</parameter> <parameter class='command'>Y</parameter> <parameter class='command'>Z</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>input single shotline location in target coordinates</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>max-barriers</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>count</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>specify the maximum number of components to report along spall ray</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>max-spall-rays</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>count</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>specify the desired number of spall rays generated per burst point</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>plot-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>generate plot data in file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>quit</command></entry>
	      <entry>quit the application</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>read-2d-shot-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>read shot locations from file as grid offsets (see <command>input-2d-shot</command>)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>read-3d-shot-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>read shot locations from file in target coordinates (see <command>input-3d-shot</command>)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>read-burst-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>read burst point locations from file (see <command>burst-coordinates</command>)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>read-input-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>read key word commands from file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>report-overlaps</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>flag</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>if yes, log overlap diagnostics</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>shotline-burst</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>flag</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>if yes, generate burst points along shotlines</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>shotline-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>output shot line data to file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>target-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>read BRL-CAD database from file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>target-objects</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>object0</parameter> <parameter class='command'>[object1 object2 ...]</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>list objects from BRL-CAD database to interrogate</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>units</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>name</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>linear units (inches, feet, millimeters, centimeters,meters)</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry><command>write-input-file</command></entry>
	      <entry><parameter class='command'>file</parameter></entry>
	      <entry>save script of commands in file</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>#</entry>
	      <entry></entry>
	      <entry>any line beginning with the '#' character is a comment</entry>
	    </row>

	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_user_preferences">
    <title>User Preferences</title>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_units">
      <title>Units of Measure</title>
      <para>
	The <command>units</command> command will set the linear units for input and
	output. This command should be used before any scalar quantities such as
	coordinates, distances, or sizes are input. The units may be changed to	accommodate
	input files of differing units, but the output from a particular run will reflect
	whatever the units were set to when the <command>execute</command> command was
	given. One argument is expected out of the following list and must be spelled
	correctly: millimeters, centimeters, meters, inches and feet. The default units are
	millimeters.
      </para>
      <para>
	Note that when specifying angles as options to commands angles are always expressed
	in degrees, not radians.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_report_overlaps">
      <title>Region Overlap Reporting</title>
      <para>
	It is considered an error if two regions in a BRL-CAD .g file occupy the same space; we
	call this an overlap. The ray tracing library (librt) will report overlapping regions
	that are intersected by shotlines or burst rays to the burst application and the program
	will, by default, print out any that have a line of sight thickness of at
	least 0.25 millimeters (see <link linkend="burst_of_7">Error Log</link>). Although a target
	may only have a small number of overlapping regions, an error will be reported for each
	ray that intersects one of them.  Generally this results in the messages being repetitious.
	Although these diagnostics are important for fixing problems in the geometric description
	of the target, the user may wish to proceed with a production run and the printing of
	these errors can slow the execution time considerably. A yes or no argument to
	the <command>report-overlaps</command> command will turn the diagnostics on or off.
	Regardless of whether or not individual overlaps are reported, the total number detected
	will be logged.
      </para>
      <para>
	When overlap reporting is enabled, the full path name of both regions is printed as seen in the
	following example:

	<literallayout class="monospaced">
OVERLAP:
reg=/component/turret/tur.ext/tur.armor/tur.bot{{0}} isol=s2,
reg=/component/hull/hull.ext/hull.armor/r1.top{{0}} osol=ss4,
depth 544.21mm at (-471.784,812.8,0) x-2 y1 lvl0 purpose=shotline
OVERLAP:
reg=/component/turret/tur.ext/tur.ring{{0}} isol=ss2,
reg=/component/turret/tur.ext/tur.armor/tur.bot{{0}} osol=s2,
depth 25.39mm at (-418.907,812.8,0) x-2 y1 lvl1 purpose=normal thickness
OVERLAP:
reg=/component/turret/tur.ext/tur.ring{{0}} isol=ss2,
reg=/component/turret/tur.ext/tur.armor/tur.bot{{0}} osol=s2,
depth 52.88mm at (-418.907,-812.8,0) x-2 y1 lvl1 purpose=spall ray
         </literallayout>

	The zero enclosed in double curly brackets is intended to discriminate between instances.
	Theoretically, isol and osol are the names of the starting and ending solids associated
	with the boolean operations on the overlapping partition. In practice these solid names
	are typically not helpful in diagnosing the problem, but the region names should be
	sufficient. The depth is the line-of-sight thickness of the overlapping partition in
	millimeters. In parentheses, are printed the target coordinates of the intersection of
	the ray with the overlap. The x-2 and y1 reveal that the grid indices of the shotline
	are -2, 1; this means that the shotline was 2 cells to the left, and one cell above the
	grid origin. If lvl (meaning ray tracing recursion level) is zero, then the overlap
	resulted from a shotline, but if it is one, it could represent either a burst ray
	intersection or a probe to calculate the normal thickness of a component intersected by
	the shotline. The real purpose of the ray is stated last.
      </para>
    </refsection>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_shotlining_options">
    <title>Shotlining Options</title>
    <para>
      Shotlining is a technique whereby lines are described in the target coordinate system
      and information is requested about the geometry that intersects those lines in 3-space.
      This technique is useful for analysis programs that must simulate threat/target
      interactions, and therefore must sample the geometry along the threat path. Typically the
      lines are specified discretely, by a point and a direction, or a grid of lines is
      generated that is oriented perpendicular to the direction of attack. A grid is rectangular,
      but is subdivided along its height and width uniformly resulting in square cells.
      Gridding techniques include passing a line called a shotline through the center of each
      cell, or alternatively, dithering each shotline’s position within its respective
      cell’s boundaries (see <link linkend="burst_sh_4">Dithering Shotlines</link>).
    </para>
    <para>
      The user is faced with several choices for generating shotlines; full-target envelope,
      partial envelopes, or discrete shots. No matter what shotlining method is used, a grid
      always exists as a frame of reference for specifying 2-dimensional coordinates in the
      plane normal to the direction of attack. This 2-dimensional coordinate system is a
      projection of the shotline coordinate system (also referred to as the primed coordinate
      system). For the simple case of a zero azimuth, zero elevation attack, the X’, Y’, and Z’
      axes in the shotline coordinate system coincide with the X, Y, and Z axes of the target
      coordinate system and the shotline direction is parallel to the X’ axis and headed toward
      decreasing coordinates. Other orientations are described by rotating the X’, Y’, and Z’
      axes to keep the shotline direction always down the X’ axis. This transformation involves
      two rotations; first a rotation of the primed coordinate system about the coincident Z and
      Z’ axes by the specified azimuthal angle, followed by a rotation about the new Y’ axis by
      the specified elevation angle. Since the grid is a 2-d projection of the shotline
      coordinate system, it has no X coordinate; if the user’s viewpoint is from the direction
      of attack, the Y’ axis can be thought of as horizontal with increasing coordinates to the
      right, and the Z’ axis as vertical and increasing in the upward direction.
    </para>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_sh_1">
      <title>Attack Direction</title>
      <para>
	The orientation of shotlines with respect to the coordinate system of the target are
	described by azimuth and elevation angles. These angles must be specified in degrees
	as floating-point numbers via the <command>attack-direction</command>.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_sh_2">
      <title>Gridding</title>
      <para>
	An envelope refers to a grid that is dimensioned such that its rectangular area,
	projected normal to the grid, will cover optionally all or part of the target.
	The <command>enclose-target</command> option will generate a grid that is guaranteed
	to cover the entire target. Since BRL-CAD uses combinatorial solid geometry as one of
	its shape representation methods, the dimensions of the target are not known in advance.
	Therefore, a worst case bounding rectangular parallel piped (RPP) is used to generate the
	grid and the grid may be larger	than necessary. In addition, depending on the attack
	aspect, the presented area of some targets may not fill	up a rectangular grid well. This
	should not be a problem since ray tracing outside the target boundaries is cheap, but
	if desired the grid can be trimmed down with the partial envelope option
	<command>enclose-portion</command>. The	grid origin is always aligned with the target origin.
      </para>
      <para>
	The <command>enclose-portion</command> option allows the user to generate a sub-grid by
	specifying the distances from the grid origin to the sub-grid’s left, right, top, and
	bottom boundaries.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_sh_3">
      <title>Cell Size</title>
      <para>
	The dimensions of a grid cell are input as floating-point values that represent the
	distances between the centers of adjacent cells. <command>cell-size</command> also
	expresses the projected area of influence associated with a shotline or burst ray.
	Therefore, <command>cell-size</command> must be specified even when a grid will not
	be generated, such as with discrete shot or discrete burst point selection (see
	<link linkend="burst_sh_5">Input Discrete Shots</link> and
	<link linkend="bursting_1_1">Input Discrete Burst Points</link>).
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_sh_4">
      <title>Dithering Shotlines</title>
      <para>
	When gridding, shotlines normally pass through the center of each cell, however, they
	may be also be dithered via the <command>dither-cells</command> command. If the user
	chooses the latter, 2 random numbers are selected for each cell that are used to offset
	the shotline in both parametric directions of the grid plane, but within the respective
	cell’s boundaries.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_sh_5">
      <title>Input Discrete Shots</title>
      <para>
	If the user wants to fire at a known point on the target, he or she may wish to describe
	the shotline location in target coordinates. When coupled with the attack direction, each
	3-dimensional coordinate uniquely specifies a shotline.  The <command>input-3d-shot</command>
	command allows the user to type in a single shot location as an X, Y, and Z coordinate that
	is run when the <command>execute</command> command is given, but remember that no queueing
	of shots occurs in this mode; the last set of coordinates entered will be used.  For inputing
	multiple shots, <command>read-3d-shot-file</command> can be used to loop through every set
	of target coordinates in the named file after the <command>execute</command> command is run.
	The file should contain three floating-point numbers on each line separated by white space
	(blanks or tabs).
      </para>
      <para>
	Another way to describe a shot location is in the shotline coordinate system. Since the X’
	location of the	shot is irrelevant (the shotline is parallel to the X’ axis) a shot may be
	specified as a Y’ and Z’ coordinate. These coordinates can also be referred to as horizontal
	and vertical grid offsets.  The	<command>input-2d-shot</command> option allows the user to
	type in a single shot location as a Y’, and Z’ coordinate which will be run when the
	<command>execute</command> command is given, but like the 3d case no queueing of shots occurs
	in this mode and only the last set of grid offsets entered will be used.  To input multiple
	shots, the <command>read-2d-shot-file</command> can be used; <command>execute</command> will
	loop through every set of grid offsets in the named file. The file should contain three
	floating-point numbers on each line separated by white space (blanks or tabs).
      </para>
    </refsection>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_bursting_options">
    <title>Bursting Options</title>
    <para>
      Bursting is a technique for sampling a target’s geometry with the use of ray tracing. As
      opposed to shotlining involving parallel rays, bursting employs a distribution of rays
      that emanate from a single point. The burst program generates rays that approximate a uniform
      distribution over a user-specified solid angle (see
      <link linkend="bursting_2_2">Sampling Cone Half Angle</link>) and having a density (see
      <link linkend="busrting_2_4">Number of Sampling Rays</link>) that is also under control of
      the user. The user also has a choice between several mechanisms for setting up burst point
      locations depending on the particular threat he is attempting to emulate.
    </para>

    <refsection xml:id="bursting_1">
      <title>Method of Locating Burst Point</title>
      <para>
	Depending on threat type, burst points may be located using two basic techniques. The
	first technique is simply to input the burst point coordinates. This method can be used
	to compare vulnerability analysis results with empirical results from the firing range
	or combat field. The second technique available to the user is to burst along a shotline.
	This option is used more for predicting the burst point location based on target geometry,
	given certain parameters that describe the target/threat interactions.
      </para>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_1_1">
	<title>Input Discrete Burst Points</title>
	<para>
	  The input of explicit burst point coordinates can be accomplished either by typing them
	  in one at a time or by reading a file of target X, Y, and Z coordinates.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The <command>burst-coordinates</command> command allows the user to type in a single
	  burst point location as an X, Y, and Z coordinate. When the <command>execute</command>
	  command is given, that one burst point will be run. No queueing of burst points occurs
	  in this mode, the last set of coordinates entered will be used.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The <command>read-burst-file</command> command allows the user to specify a number of
	  burst points from a file; this option will, after submission of an execute directive,
	  loop through every set of target coordinates in the named file. The file should contain
	  three numbers on each line separated by white space (blanks or tabs).
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_1_2">
	<title>Burst on Contact</title>
	<para>
	  The <command>shotline-burst</command> command can be given a yes or no argument to either
	  enable or disable this method of generating burst points. When a yes argument is given,
	  a second yes or no argument is also required (see <link linkend="bursting_1_2_1">Burst on Armor</link>).
	  Bursting along a shotline can be done different ways depending on the combination of
	  several options. The location of the burst point is based on the triggering mechanism that
	  is selected with the burst distance parameter.
	</para>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_1_2_1">
	  <title>Burst on Armor</title>
	  <para>
	    If the <command>burst-distance</command> paramter is set to a negative or zero value, then
	    interior burst points will be generated (see <link linkend="bursting_2_1">Burst Distance</link>).
	    This method of bursting requires the input of burst armor idents and, by default, burst
	    air idents are also required. If the user does not want to require that certain air be
	    present to trigger a burst point, the shotline-burst command has a second argument. When this
	    second argument is set to no, bursting will occur as long as burst armor is followed by any
	    air or void (empty space), and the burst air file is not required. For more information see
	    <link linkend="bursting_io_1_2_1">Burst Armor and Burst Air Ident Files</link>.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_1_2_2">
	  <title>Ground Plane Bursting</title>
	  <para>
	    Ground plane bursting is a vehicle for evaluating the effect of fragmenting warheads
	    on light-armored vehicles when they strike the ground in close proximity to the target.
	    The <command>ground-plane</command> command is only relevant when bursting along a
	    shotline is selected. The ground is modeled as a rectangle lying in a plane parallel to
	    the target X-Y plane with edges parallel to the X and Y axes. The grid will be enlarged
	    to include the ground plane; it is important for efficiency to limit the size of the
	    ground plane to match the range of the fragments that may be generated by the particular
	    threat being modeled. When enabling this option, the <command>ground-plane</command>
	    command is given a yes argument followed by the height of the target above the ground,
	    and the distances that the ground rectangle extends out positive X, negative X, positive
	    Y, and negative Y axes.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

      </refsection>

    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="bursting_2">
      <title>Bursting Parameters</title>
      <para>
	The following parameters influence both the triggering mechanism for burst points, as well
	as the characteristics of the cone of rays generated from each point.
      </para>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_2_1">
	<title>Burst Distance</title>
	<para>
	  The <command>burst-distance</command> parameter is modeled after the BDIST parameter
	  used by the Air Force’s PGEN code. The role of this parameter is overloaded, however it
	  was retained to aid PGEN users in transitioning to the <command>burst</command> program.
	  If it is zero or negative, then interior bursting is enabled, otherwise, if it is greater
	  than zero, exterior bursting will occur, subject to certain conditions (see below).
	  The magnitude of this parameter is used to offset the burst point location along the
	  shotline relative to the geometry that triggered the burst.
	</para>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_2_1_1">
	  <title>Interior Bursting</title>
	  <para>
	    Burst armor refers to a component whose ident code is found in the list input by
	    the <command>burst-armor-file</command> command. Similarly, burst air refers to a
	    component whose ident code is found in the list input by the
	    <command>burst-air-file</command> directive. If interior bursting is enabled and
	    a burst armor component is encountered along a shotline that is immediately followed
	    by burst air, then a burst point will be located the absolute value of burst distance
	    beyond the exit of the shotline from the component. This means that if burst distance
	    is zero, the burst point will lie at the burst armor/air interface, and if it’s
	    -5.5, the burst point will lie 5.5 units inside the air compartment from the back
	    surface of the armor.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_2_1_2">
	  <title>Exterior Bursting</title>
	  <para>
	    If burst distance is greater than zero, the first component encountered along the
	    shotline will trigger a burst point, regardless of its ident code, that will be
	    located burst distance in front of the shotline entry point. This technique simulates
	    the behavior of a fragmenting munition with a standoff fuzing such that detonation
	    is triggered before the collision of the warhead with the target. The burst distance
	    is set to imitate the built in standoff of the warhead. When employing exterior
	    bursting methods, burst armor and burst air are not used.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_2_2">
	<title>Sampling Cone Half Angle</title>
	<para>
	  To limit the solid angle within which burst rays will be generated, the user may
	  specify a cone half angle. This angle represents the degrees (in floating point) from
	  the axis of the cone to its limiting surface. The default value for the cone half
	  angle is 45 degrees.
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_2_3">
	<title>Deflected Sampling Cone</title>
	<para>
	  The spall cone axis is, by default, aligned with the shotline. In reality, the center
	  of mass of the spall cloud would be between the shotline direction and the exit
	  normal of the shotline from the spalling component. By aligning the spall cone axis
	  with a vector halfway between the shotline and the exit normal, a narrower cone half
	  angle can be used and still sample within the solid angle of interest. This technique
	  can therefore be used to cut down on the number of rays calculated without lowering
	  the sampling density. The <command>deflect-spall-cone</command> command takes a yes
	  or no argument about whether or not to divert the cone axis.
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_2_4">
	<title>Number of Sampling Rays</title>
	<para>
	  The sampling ray density within the spall cone is controlled by specifying the maximum
	  number of rays desired with the <command>max-spall-rays</command> command. Due to the
	  uniform distribution algorithm employed, the number of rays calculated will be slightly
	  less.
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_2_5">
	<title>Maximum Barriers</title>
	<para>
	  For munitions known to have limited penetration capability, the user may set a limit
	  on the number of burst ray intersections reported with the
	  <command>max-barriers</command> command. The effect of setting this parameter is to
	  reduce the size of the burst point library (see
	  <link linkend="burst_of_1">Burst Point Library</link>) by limiting the number of
	  components that will be reported per burst ray. By default, up to 100 components
	  are reported, as it is not expected that this number will be reached under
	  normal circumstances.
	</para>
      </refsection>

    </refsection>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_input_file_options">
    <title>Input File Options</title>

     <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_1">
      <title>Target-Related Input Files</title>
      <para>
	This group of commands is for specification of target-specific input files.
      </para>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_1_1">
	<title>Target Data Base File</title>
	<para>
	  The input of the target’s BRL-CAD .g file is accomplished with the <command>target-file</command>
	  command. Note that only one data base may be read in during a given session. If the user wishes
	  to change the target once the execute command has been given, they must exit the burst program
	  and start a new session.
	</para>
	<para>
	  After specifying the BRL-CAD .g file, the user must list all of the objects in the .g
	  hierarchy that they wish to include in the analysis with the <command>target-objects</command>
	  command. The objects must be listed as arguments to one <command>target-objects</command>
	  command with spaces or tabs as separators. Note that only one list of objects may be loaded
	  per session, however, they do not get loaded until the <command>execute</command> command is
	  given.
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_1_2">
	<title>Ident List Input Files</title>
	<para>
	  Idents refer to the region ident code from the BRL-CAD .g file. Lists of idents may be specified
	  singly or as ranges. Individual idents must appear as one per line, but ranges are specified
	  by two numbers on a line that are separated by one or more of the following characters:
	  comma, hyphen, colon, semicolon, space, or tab. For example:
	  <literallayout class="monospaced">
600-999
1011
4002-4050
8000
9001
9004
9005
	  </literallayout>
	</para>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_io_1_2_1">
	  <title>Burst-Armor and Burst-Air Ident Files</title>
	  <para>
	    When interior burst points are to be generated along a shotline (see
	    <link linkend="bursting_2_1_1">Interior Bursting</link>) a file of burst armor
	    idents must be specified with the <command>burst-armor-file</command> command. Additionally
	    a burst air idents file must be specified with the <command>burst-air-file</command> command.
	    If a shotline intersects a component whose ident has been input as a burst armor and it is
	    immediately followed by burst air a burst point will be triggered.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="bursting_io_1_2_2">
	  <title>Critical Component Idents</title>
	  <para>
	    Whether interior or exterior bursting is being employed, information about components
	    hit by burst rays will only be output for rays that hit critical components. The file name
	    containing a list of critical component idents must therefore be specified by the
	    <command>critical-comp-file</command> command if burst points are to be generated.
	  </para>
	</refsection>

      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_1_3">
	<title>Color Mapping Input Files</title>
	<para>
	  The <command>color-file</command> command allows users to assign colors to component
	  idents for graphics options, in particular, the <command>image-file</command> and
	  <command>plot-file</command> commands. The format of this file is 5 numbers per line
	  separated by blanks or tabs. The first number is the low end of an ident range and the
	  second number is the high end of the range (both numbers are inclusive). This range is
	  mapped to the color specified by the last 3 numbers on the line that are red, green,
	  and blue components of the color (values for these components must be between 0 and
	  255 inclusive).  For example:
	   <literallayout class="monospaced">
4001 4003   255 255 0     # Fuel
4050 4050   255 255 0     # Fuel
8000 8001   255 100 255   # Ammo
100 165     150 255 100   # Hull armor
610 619     220 150 100   # Commander
720 729     220 150 100   # Gunner
830 839     220 150 100   # Loader
940 949     220 150 100   # Driver
	  </literallayout>
	</para>
      </refsection>

    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_2">
      <title>Project-Related Input Files</title>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_2_1">
	<title>Reading Session Files</title>
	<para>
	  The <command>read-input-file</command> command reads an input file of commands. These
	  files can be generated manually by using a text editor or saved from a session file
	  with the <command>write-input-file</command> command.  See
	  <link linkend="burst_commands">Command Input</link> for the format of this file.
	</para>
      </refsection>

      <refsection xml:id="bursting_io_2_2">
	<title>Shotline and Burst Point Input Files</title>
	<para>
	  For an explanation of commands for reading in files of shotline or burst point coordinates,
	  see <link linkend="burst_sh_5">Input Discrete Shots</link> and
	  <link linkend="bursting_1_1">Input Discrete Burst Points</link>.
	</para>
      </refsection>

    </refsection>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="burst_output_file_options">
    <title>Output File Options</title>
    <para>
      The following commands will turn on optional output. By default, no output is produced
      except error logging (see <link linkend="burst_of_7">Error Log</link>), unless an output
      file is specified with the appropriate command. Any combination of output options may be
      specified for a particular run. Note that specifying an output file will cause an existing
      file with that name to be truncated to zero length. Therefore, only one such command should
      be entered per session for a particular file name. Multiple runs during a session will append
      to the same files if intervening commands to change the output file name are not given,
      except for the graphics files as explained below. Note that there is no way to append to a
      file created by a previous session of the burst program, but these files may be concatenated
      after the fact.
    </para>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_1">
      <title>Burst Point Library File</title>
      <para>
	The <command>burst-file</command> command will open the named file for creating a burst
	point library. If the file exists, it will be truncated by this command.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_2">
      <title>Shotline File</title>
      <para>
	The <command>shotline-file</command> command will open the named file for creating a
	shotline file. If the file exists, it will be truncated by this command.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_3">
      <title>Plot File</title>
      <para>
	The <command>plot-file</command> command generates a plot file, using BRL-CAD extensions
	to the standard format. This option is useful for examining the shotline and burst ray
	information graphically as a three-dimensional vector plot. Due to constraints inherent
	in the plot format, these plots must be displayed as a post-process step by using a
	BRL-CAD plotting utility such as <command>pl-fb</command>. Because some of these display
	programs do not support multiple plots per file, the file name should be changed between
	runs. The following table describes the color mapping associated with these plots:

      <table>
	<title>Color Key for Plots</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Color</entry>
	      <entry>R</entry>
	      <entry>G</entry>
	      <entry>B</entry>
	      <entry>Representation</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>yellow</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>grid cell centers</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>red</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>burst cone</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>blue</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>default component intersection</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>lt blue</entry>
	      <entry>100</entry>
	      <entry>100</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>default outside air intersection</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>lt green</entry>
	      <entry>100</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>100</entry>
	      <entry>default inside air intersection</entry>
	    </row>

	    <row>
	      <entry>purple</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>0</entry>
	      <entry>255</entry>
	      <entry>default critical component intersection</entry>
	    </row>

	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>

      <para>
	If the user has specified a color mapping file with the <command>color-file</command> command,
	then those colors will be used rather than the above colors for all shotline/ray intersections.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_4">
      <title>Frame Buffer Image</title>
      <para>
	The <command>image-file</command> command will generate a color image that provides the
	user with immediate feedback about a run. The grid is displayed graphically and each cell
	location is dynamically color coded to show its current status. The following table describes
	the color mapping associated with the grid:

	<table>
	  <title>Color Key for Frame Buffer Image</title>
	  <tgroup cols="5">
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Color</entry>
		<entry>R</entry>
		<entry>G</entry>
		<entry>B</entry>
		<entry>Representation</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>red</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>axis of grid</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>black</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>grid cell boundaries</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>blue</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>outside of grid</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>lt grey</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>shot missed target</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>white</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>shot hit target</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>lt green</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>burst occurred but hit no critical components</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>pink</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>200</entry>
		<entry>burst occurred and hit some critical components</entry>
	      </row>

	      <row>
		<entry>purple</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>255</entry>
		<entry>a ground burst occurred</entry>
	      </row>

	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</table>
      </para>
      <para>
	In addition to the above cell colors, hits on critical components by burst rays are
	depicted as a colored pixel projected into grid space from the intersection point
	where the ray enters the component. Colors for the components are mapped from ident
	numbers according to the table specified by the user with the <command>color-file</command>
	command and shaded using a lighting model illuminated from the viewing direction.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_5">
      <title>Grid File</title>
      <para>
	The <command>grid-file</command> command will store each shotline coordinate generated
	during the run as grid offsets. These files can later be read in to replicate a previous
	run’s grid or discrete shots by using the <command>read-2d-shot-file</command> command.
	This capability is especially useful when dithered shotlines have been used and it is
	desired that the same shotlines be used in another run. Note that the shotline intersection
	information is not saved, just the grid offsets for each shotline.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_6">
      <title>Script File</title>
      <para>
	During a session, all commands are saved in a temporary file. The
	<command>write-input-file</command> command will create a snapshot of this session file,
	that can later be used to recreate the current session up to the point when the file was
	written. The session or input files can later be used in one of two ways: either read in
	with the <command>read-input-file</command> command, or supplied on the standard input of
	the <command>burst</command> program. Note that the <command>write-input-file</command>
	and <command>read-input-file</command> commands will not be included in the input files,
	but the commands read in by the latter will.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_7">
      <title>Error Log</title>
      <para>
	The <command>error-file</command> command is useful to save errors in a log file and prevent
	copious ray tracer diagnostics from scrolling by on the screen. This option is especially
	useful if using the batch mode of execution so that the terminal is not tied up by program
	output. If no error log is specified, diagnostic messages will appear in the scrolling window
	or, if in batch mode, on the <command>burst</command> program’s standard error output.
      </para>
    </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="burst_of_8">
      <title>Histogram File</title>
      <para>
	The <command>histogram-file</command> command generates a frequency histogram to the named
	file. The file format is simply one number per line; each number is a count of critical
	components hit by an individual burst ray. This file can easily be post-processed to display
	a histogram, for instance, how many rays hit zero, one, two, three, etc. components.
      </para>
    </refsection>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id='see_also'>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>burst_point_library</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>burst_shotline_files</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum></citerefentry>
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title>
  <para>BRL-CAD Team</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="copyright"><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
  <para>This software is Copyright (c) 1984-2022 United States Government as
  represented by the U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
  <para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
  mail to <email>devs@brlcad.org</email></para>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
