<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->

<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="anim_cascade1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>ANIM_CASCADE</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv xml:id="name">
    <refname>anim_cascade</refname>
    <refpurpose>evaluates movement of an object relative to a moving frame of reference</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>anim_cascade</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-s</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-o(<replaceable>f</replaceable>|<replaceable>r</replaceable>|<replaceable>a</replaceable>)</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-(<replaceable>f</replaceable>|<replaceable>r</replaceable>|<replaceable>a</replaceable>)(<replaceable>c</replaceable>|<replaceable>y</replaceable>) # # #</arg>
      <arg choice="plain" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>input.table</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="plain" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>output.table</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection xml:id="description"><info><title>DESCRIPTION</title></info>
    
    <para>
      <emphasis remap="I">Anim_cascade</emphasis> is designed to enable the user 
      to control the movement of objects relative to other objects. In the normal 
      mode of operation, the user supplies the position and orientation of a 
      (possibly moving) frame of reference and the position
      and orientation of an object relative to the frame of reference,
      and <command>anim_cascade</command> produces the absolute position and orientation 
      of the object at each point in time. All orientations are specified as yaw, 
      pitch, and roll. The columns of the input table are:
    </para>
    
    <para>time fx fy fz fyaw fpitch froll rx ry rz ryaw rpitch rroll</para>
    
    <para>and the columns of the output table are:</para>
    
    <para>time ax ay az ayaw apitch aroll</para>
    
    <para>
      Here "f" refers to the frame of reference, "r" refers to the position
      and orientation of the object relative to the frame, and "a"
      refers to the absolute position and orientation of the object.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="options"><info><title>OPTIONS</title></info>
    
    <variablelist remap="TP">
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-or</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Output the relative position and orientation. If this option is specified,
	    <command>anim_cascade</command> will expect the absolute position and 
	    orientation of the frame of reference and the object as input,
	    and will produce the position and orientation or the object relative to
	    the frame as output. The input columns should be:
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>time fx fy fz fyaw fpitch froll ax ay az ayaw apitch aroll</para>
	  
	  <para>and the output columns will be:</para>
	  
	  <para>time rx ry rz ryaw rpitch rroll</para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-of</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Output the frame of reference. If this option is specified,
	    <command>anim_cascade</command> will expect the absolute and relative 
	    positions and orientations of the object as input,
	    and will produce the corresponding frame of reference as output.
	    The input columns should be:
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>time ax ay az ayaw apitch aroll rx ry rz ryaw rpitch rroll</para>
	  
	  <para>and the output columns will be:</para>
	  
	  <para>time fx fy fz fyaw fpitch froll</para>
	  
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-fc # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant position for the frame of reference. The
	    columns fx, fy, and fz should be omitted from the input table, and the
	    command-line arguments will be used instead. This has no effect if used
	    in conjunction with <option>-of</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-fy # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant orientation for the frame of reference. The
	    columns fyaw, fpitch, and froll should be omitted from the input table,
	    and the command-line arguments will be used instead.
	    This has no effect if used in conjunction with <option>-of</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-rc # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant position of the object relative to the frame
	    of reference. The columns rx, ry, and rz should be omitted from the input 
	    table, and the command-line arguments will be used instead.
	    This has no effect if used in conjunction with <option>-or</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-ry # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant orientation of the object relative to the
	    frame of reference. The columns ryaw,  rpitch, and rroll should be 
	    omitted from the input table, and the command-line arguments will be 
	    used instead. This has no effect if used in conjunction with
	    <option>-or</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-ac # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant absolute position for the object. The
	    columns ax, ay, and az should be omitted from the input table, and the
	    command-line arguments will be used instead. This has no effect unless used
	    in conjunction with <option>-or</option> or <option>-of</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-ay # # #</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specify a constant absolute orientation for the object. The
	    columns ayaw, apitch, and aroll should be omitted from the input table,
	    and the command-line arguments will be used instead.
	    This has no effect unless used in conjunction with
	    <option>-or</option> or <option>-of</option>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-s</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Suppress time column. No time column is read or written.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note: When all of the input columns are specified with command-line arguments,
	    then standard input is not read and
	    only one line of output is produced. The time value will be set to zero,
	    unless it is suppressed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsection>
  
  <refsection xml:id="examples"><info><title>EXAMPLES</title></info>
    
    <example><info><title>Circular pan around a moving vehicle</title></info>
      
      <para>
	Suppose that you want the virtual camera to pan in a circle around a
	moving vehicle, always staying a fixed distance from the vehicle.
	There should already exist an animation table with the time, position,
	and orientation of the vehicle in each frame. This will be the moving
	frame of reference. Next, you should create an animation table which
	describes how the camera would need to move if the vehicle stood still
	at the origin. The columns of the second animation table should be
	appended to the columns of the first table (using
	<emphasis remap="I">paste</emphasis>, for example), to create the
	input table. <emphasis remap="I">Anim_cascade</emphasis>
	will produce an absolute animation table for the camera, suitable to 
	use as input to <emphasis remap="I">anim_script</emphasis>:
      </para>
      <para>
      <userinput>anim_cascade &lt; input.table | anim_script -v500 &gt; view.script</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><info><title>Determine time of place crossing</title></info>
      
      <para>
	Suppose that you have an animation path for an object and you want to
	know when it crosses a given oblique plane. You can use the
	<option>-or</option> option to find out what the position of the object 
	is relative to the frame of reference of the plane. Suppose that the plane 
	is defined by the equation:
      </para>
      
      <para>x + z = 0</para>

      <para>
	In a frame of reference located at the origin with a pitch of 45
	degrees, the x-axis is perpendicular to the given plane.
	To convert the absolute animation path into this frame of reference, the command
	would be:
      </para>
      <para>
      <userinput>anim_cascade -or -fc 0 0 0 -fy 0 45 0 &lt; absolute.table &gt;; \ relative.table</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>
	Wherever the x coordinate in the output table is positive, the object
	lies above the plane.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><info><title>Camera positioning relative to objects</title></info>
      
      <para>
	Suppose that one object is situated at the point (1,2,3) with a yaw,
	pitch, and roll of (45, 25, 10). Suppose further that you want to
	position a camera so that to the camera, the first object seems to be 10
	units straight ahead, facing to the right. You could find the required
	position and orientation of the camera with the following command:
      </para>
      <para>
	<userinput>anim_cascade -s -of -ac 1 2 3 -ay 45 25 10 -rc 10 0 0 -ry -90 0 0</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>
  </refsection>
 
  <info>
    <author>
      <personname>Carl J. Nuzman</personname>
      <contrib></contrib>
    </author>
  </info>
  
  <refsection xml:id="copyright"><info><title>COPYRIGHT</title></info>
    
    <para>
      This software is Copyright (c) 1993-2011 by the United States Government
      as represented by the U.S. Army Research Laboratory.  All rights reserved.
    </para> 
  </refsection>
  
  <refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><info><title>BUG REPORTS</title></info>
    
    <para>
      Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
      mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.
    </para>
</refsection>
</refentry>
