<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="gr">

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>GR/DG</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv xml:id="name">
   <refname>gr</refname>
   <refname>dg</refname>
   <refpurpose>
        Add or remove primitives or primitive parents from a group using a GUI selection box.  dg exits grouper mode.
   </refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
  <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
    <command>gr</command>
       <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>GroupName</replaceable></arg>
       <group choice="req" rep="norepeat">
	 <arg choice="plain" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>+</replaceable></arg>
	 <arg choice="plain" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-</replaceable></arg>
       </group>
       <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>ListLimit</replaceable></arg>
       <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-p</replaceable></arg>
     </cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection xml:id="description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
 <para>Allows primitives or primitive parents to be added or removed from a
 group by selecting them on the MGED display using a selection box. Objects
 are identified by the location of their vertices on the display. For example,
 a portion of a object may be within the selection box but if none of its vertices
 are then it is not considered within the section box. Because of this, objects
 can only be selected if they are displayed in wireframe. Drawing a selection box
 (left to right), objects completely in the box are selected. Drawing the selection
 box (right to left), objects completely and partly in the box are selected. To
 start grouper use the command 'gr' or 'grouper'. Press and hold the center mouse
 button then drag the mouse to create the selection box. If there are a large number
 of vertices on the display, there will be a delay before the selected objects are
 highlighted and control of MGED is returned to the user. To exit grouper mode, hold
 down the 'ctrl' key and single-click the center mouse button. You can also exit
 grouper mode with the 'dg' or 'done_grouper' commands. Objects in the group, while
 in grouper mode, will be displayed (i.e. highlighted) in yellow wireframe. When
 entering grouper mode, if the chosen group already contains objects, these
 existing objects will be immediately displayed in yellow wireframe. As objects
 are added to the group, they will also be highlighted in yellow. When you exit
 grouper mode, the yellow highlights will be removed.</para>
 <para>Caveats: This command will not function as expected if a selected
 object has matrices applied. The xpush command can resolve this
 limitation.</para>
</refsection>

 <refsection xml:id="options"><title>OPTIONS</title>
  <variablelist remap="TP">
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>GroupName</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  The name of the group to add/remove primitives or primitive parents.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>+</option></term>
      <term><option>-</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Indicates if to add or remove from group.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>ListLimit</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  As primitives/parents are selected using a selection box, the
	  names of the selected objects can be listed. This option controls
	  the number of entries which will be listed. By default this value
	  is zero. All selected objects will be listed, assuming the
	  'ListLimit' is high enough, even if they are not added to the
	  group. This will happen if some of the selected objects are already
	  in the group.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><option>-p</option></term>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Places the parent of the selected primitives in the group instead of
	  the primitives. With the '-p' option, if the primitive does not have a
	  parent (i.e. is in the root) it will be ignored.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title><para>BRL-CAD Team</para></refsection>

<refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>

  <para>
    Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
    mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;, or via the "cadbug.sh" script.
  </para>
</refsection>
</refentry>
