<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="rtarea1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>RTAREA</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv xml:id="name">
    <refname>rtarea</refname>
    <refpurpose>Calculate exposed, presented and centers of surface areas (MGED Command)</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>rtarea</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat"><replaceable>options</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection xml:id="description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

    <para>
      For displayed objects, the <emphasis remap="I">rtarea</emphasis> command calculates
      the exposed, presented and centers of surface areas. The summary output includes
      details for individual regions, assemblies (combinations that contain regions),
      and summarized totals. By default current display azimuth and elevation are used
      for computations. Summary units are current MGED editing units.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <emphasis remap="B">exposed </emphasis> area corresponds to what a human observer
      would see looking at the object(s) in question, if all the objects were non-transparent.
      For example, say rays were cast towards two cubes, each one of which is a region, one in
      front of the other, grouped into an assembly, with the ray direction pointed into the page:
      <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|                |
|                |
|        |--------------| Front Cube
|        |       |      |
|        |       |      |
|--------|-------|      |
	 |              |
	 |              |
	 |--------------|
      </screen>

      The exposed area of the Front Cube corresponds to the total area of the sheet, since it is not
      occluded by any other object:
       <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|                |
|                |
|        |--------------| Front Cube
|        |**************|
|        |**************|
|--------|**************|
	 |**************|
	 |**************|
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


      The Rear Cube, on the other hand, IS occluded by the Front Cube and would thus report only a fraction
      of its area as exposed:
       <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|****************|
|****************|
|********|--------------| Front Cube
|********|       |      |
|********|       |      |
|--------|-------|      |
	 |              |
	 |              |
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


      An object that combines both of these sheets would thus report as its exposed area the
      sum of the exposed areas of the individual sheets:
      <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|****************|
|****************|
|****************|------| Front Cube
|***********************|
|***********************|
|--------|**************|
	 |**************|
	 |**************|
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


   </para>
   <para>
      <emphasis remap="B">Presented</emphasis> area, unlike exposed area, does not take
      occlusion into account. It is the equivalent of taking each object and considering
      it in isolation. So for the previous case of two sheets of metal, the Front Cube
      would report the same area:

       <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|                |
|                |
|        |--------------| Front Cube
|        |**************|
|        |**************|
|--------|**************|
	 |**************|
	 |**************|
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


      The Rear Cube, on the other hand, ALSO reports its full area:
      <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|****************|
|****************|
|****************-------| Front Cube
|****************|      |
|****************|      |
|--------|-------|      |
	 |              |
	 |              |
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


      When reporting the presented area of the group, there is a subtle point - rtarea
      does not count area covered by multiple regions multiple times when totaling the
      presented area. So for the group containing both cubes, the presented area is NOT
      the cumulative area of both regions' presented areas but the area of the union of
      those two areas. In this case, that works out to be the same as the exposed area.
       <screen>
|----------------| Rear Cube
|****************|
|****************|
|****************|------| Front Cube
|***********************|
|***********************|
|--------|**************|
	 |**************|
	 |**************|
	 |--------------|
      </screen>


    </para>

    <para>
      It should be noted that rtarea only counts surfaces with a surface normal that
      has a component looking back in the direction of the ray.  So, for example, a
      cube with only one face looking "back toward" the ray will not report area from
      other faces as "presented", since their surface normals will indicate they are
      not surfaces being presented to the ray.
    </para>

    <para>
      WARNING: <emphasis remap="I">Rtarea</emphasis> may not correctly report area or
      center when instancing is done at the group level. Using <command>xpush</command>
      can be a workaround for this problem.
    </para>

</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="options"><title>OPTIONS</title>

    <variablelist remap="TP">
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-s#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Specifies the number of rays to fire in the X and Y directions on a
	    square grid. The default size is 512 pixels.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-a#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Selects auto-sizing, and gives the view azimuth in degrees. Used with
	    -e option. The default is the current display azimuth.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-e#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Selects auto-sizing, and gives the view elevation in degrees. Used with
	    -a option. The default is the current display elevation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-g#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Is used to set the grid cell width, in millimeters. Ordinarily, the cell
	    width is computed by dividing the view size by the number of pixels of
	    width, so this option need not be used. To obtain exactly 1 inch ray
	    spacing, specify -g25.4.  If the grid cell width is specified and the grid
	    cell height is not specified, the grid cell height defaults to be the same
	    as the width.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-G#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Sets the grid cell height, in millimeters.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-J#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The "jitter" flag is a bit vector. If one (-J1), it randomizes the
	    point from which each ray is fired by +/- one half of the pixel size.
	    If two (-J2), it shifts the origin of the output frame once for each frame.
	    The shift is along a circular path in the plane of the frame, with a period
	    of ten seconds, and a radius of +/- 1/4 pixel width. If three (-J3), it
	    performs both operations.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-U#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Sets the "use_air" value. The default is 1, meaning "air" solids (i.e. regions
	    with a non-zero aircode attribute value) will be retained. If this value is zero,
	    "air" solids in the model will be ignored.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-c "set cc=1"</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Compute and report area centers. The default is off.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-X#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Turns on the rt(1) program debugging flags. See raytrace.h for the meaning of
	    these bits.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
	<term><option>-x#</option></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Sets the librt(3) debug flags to the given hexadecimal bit vector. See raytrace.h
	    for the bit definitions.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="examples"><title>EXAMPLES</title>
    <example><title>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas</title>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>rtarea</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas of the displayed
       objects using current azimuth, elevation and size. Results are reported
       in current editing units.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><title>Calculate exposed, presented and centers of surface areas</title>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>rtarea -c "set cc=1"</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Calculate exposed, presented and centers of surface areas of the
       displayed objects using current azimuth, elevation and size. Results are
       reported in current editing units.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><title>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas (results in inches)</title>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>units in</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Set current editing units to inches.
      </para>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>rtarea</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas of the displayed
       objects using current azimuth, elevation and size. Results reported
       in inches.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><title>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas (az=35, el=25, auto-size)</title>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>rtarea -a35 -e25</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas of the displayed
       objects using azimuth 35, elevation 25 and size auto-set for best fit.
       Results reported in current editing units.
      </para>
    </example>
    <example><title>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas (1x1 inch grid cells)</title>
      <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>rtarea -g25.4</userinput>
      </para>
      <para>Calculate exposed and presented surface areas of the displayed
       objects using current azimuth, elevation and size. The grid cell width
       and height is 25.4 millimeters (i.e. 1 inch). Results reported in
       current editing units.
      </para>
    </example>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="copyright"><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
    <para>
      This software is Copyright (c) 1987-2014 United States Government as represented by the
      U.S. Army Research Laboratory.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
    <para>
      Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
      mail to &lt;bugs@brlcad.org&gt;.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title><para>BRL-CAD Team</para></refsection>
</refentry>
