<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->

<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
>
  <info><title><application>BRL-CAD</application> Tutorial Series: Volume III - Principles of Effective Modeling</title>
    
    <xi:include href="./tutorial_series_authors.xml" xpointer="Intro_MGED_Tutorial_Series_III_authors"/>

    <publishername>Army Research Laboratory</publishername>
    <biblioid class="pubsnumber">ARL-SR-119</biblioid>
    <pubdate>September 2003</pubdate>
    
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Approved for public release; distribution is unlimited</para>
      
      <para>The findings in this report are not to be construed as an
      official Department of the Army position unless so designated 
      by other authorized documents.</para>
      
      <para>Citation of manufacturer's or trade names does not constitute
      an official endorsement or approval of the use thereof.</para>
      
      <para>Destroy this report when it is no longer needed. Do not return
      it to the originator.</para>

      <para>Note that the name BRL-CAD and the BRL-CAD eagle logo are
      trademarks of the U.S. Army.</para>
    </legalnotice>      
    
    
  </info>

  <preface><info><title>Acknowledgements</title></info>
    

    <para>
      The authors would like to acknowledge Mr. John Anderson, Mr. Sean
      Morrison, Mr. Keith Applin, Mr. Charles Kennedy, Ms. TraNese Christy, and
      Ms. Wendy Winner for reviewing this document at various stages in its
      development and for providing many helpful suggestions for improving its
      content and presentation.
    </para>
    <para>
      In addition, the following individuals and organizations are thanked for
      contributing various tables and figures throughout the report. They
      include Ms. Wendy Winner, Mr. Michael Gillich, Dr. Paul Tanenbaum, the
      Aberdeen office of the Science Applications International Corporation
      (SAIC), and the SURVICE Engineering Company.
    </para>
    <para>
      Finally, the authors would especially like to acknowledge Mr. Michael
      Muuss, the original architect of BRL-CAD, who passed away in the fall of
      2000. Without his vision, intellect, and diligence, this work would not
      have been possible. The BRL-CAD Tutorial Series is dedicated to his
      memory.
    </para>
  </preface>

  <chapter xml:id="volIIIintro"><info><title>Introduction</title></info>
    
    <para>
      Since 1979, the U.S. Army Research Laboratory (ARL) has been developing
      and distributing the U.S. Army Ballistic Research Laboratory -
      Computer-Aided Design (BRL-CAD) constructive solid geometry (CSG) modeling
      package for a wide range of military and industrial applications. The
      package includes a large collection of tools and utilities including an
      interactive geometry editor, raytracing and generic framebuffer libraries,
      network-distributed image-processing/signal-processing capabilities, and
      an embedded scripting language.
    </para>
    <para>
      As part of this effort, a multivolume tutorial series is under development
      to assist users with the many features of the BRL-CAD package. Volume I
      provides an overview of the package contents and installation (Butler and
      Edwards, 2002). Volume II addresses the basic features and functionality
      of the package's Multi-Device Geometry Editor (MGED) and offers a
      comprehensive list of the user commands available (Butler et al., 2001).
      These documents are available for download at
      http://ftp.arl.army.mil/brlcad/ (U.S. ARL, 2003).
    </para>
    <para>
      The purpose of Volume III is to discuss the components of the modeling
      process and suggest principles for maximizing the effectiveness of
      BRL-CAD's capabilities. Because of the large diversity in modeling
      projects, these principles have largely been kept to a general nature so
      that they have the widest applicability possible. In addition, several
      appendices have been included to offer detailed discussions on several
      BRL-CAD tools and features, including the pipe primitive (Appendix A), the
      projection shader (Appendix B), the extruded bitmap primitive (Appendix
      C), the .mgedrc file (Appendix D), the Build Pattern tool (Appendix E),
      and the build_region command (Appendix F).
    </para>
    <para>
      Future volumes in the tutorial series are planned to discuss geometry
      format conversion, advanced modeling features, and programming options.
    </para>
  </chapter> 

  <chapter xml:id="volIIImodelprocess"><info><title>The Model Process</title></info>
    
    <section><info><title>The Importance of the Model Mission</title></info>
      
      <para>
	The key to knowing how to build successful, effective models in BRL-CAD is
	to know why you are building them. Thus, before any measurements are
	taken, before any structures are laid out, and before any geometry is
	built, the modeler should, if possible, meet with program sponsors,
	participants, and/or end users to gain a clear understanding of the
	model's intended purpose--that is, its mission.
      </para>
      <para>
	Whether a model is intended for ballistic analyses, radar studies, or
	something else, the model's mission should be the basis for determining
	how all parts of the modeling process should be conducted. This includes
	the level of detail that the modeler should achieve, the tree structure
	the model should have, the amount of modeling time that should be
	allotted, the types of validation and verification the model should have,
	and even the way documentation should be created and logged. This point
	may seem obvious, but failure to acknowledge the mission can result in
	wasted time and resources and, ultimately, an ineffective model.
      </para>
      <para>
	For example, if one is creating a geometric target description of a combat
	vehicle to simulate a ballistic penetration event, accurately modeled
	material thicknesses and densities of outside armor are crucial in
	analyzing penetration damage. In addition, it is usually important to
	include internal components such as fuel and electrical lines, ammunition,
	and even crew members, which can greatly affect the vehicle's
	functionality if they are impacted by a projectile (see Figure 1).
      </para>
      <para>
	Radar signature studies, on the other hand, often call for a different
	type of model. For the most part, the vehicle's outer shell--or "skin"--is
	what is important, and the previously mentioned armor thicknesses and
	internal components are usually unnecessary (see Figure 2).
      </para>

      <figure><info><title>Ballistic penetration model with transparent exterior.</title></info>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig01.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure><info><title>External detail commonly used in radar signature models.</title></info>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig02.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>
	It is also important to note that some models will need to serve multiple
	missions. If the modeler suspects that this will be the case with a model,
	it should be built to the highest level of detail that any of the intended
	users requires (and, of course, that time/resources permit).
      </para>

    </section>

    <section><info><title>M-O-D-E-L: A Five-Step Approach to Creating Effective Models</title></info>
      
      
      <para>
	After one has explicitly and unequivocally established the "why" of a
	model, the "how" of a model can be addressed. Unfortunately, there is no
	single, universally accepted method to creating models in BRL-CAD. In
	fact, professional modelers are known to employ many unique techniques to
	accomplish equivalent results. Nonetheless, there are several basic steps
	or procedures that are commonly used by most modelers to create accurate,
	realistic, and useful geometric representations in a timely and efficient
	manner. These steps could be described in a variety of ways, but for
	convenience, they can be generalized into the following five categories
	and represented by the acronym M-O-D-E-L:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    M-easuring (or collecting/converting) data,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    O-rganizing the structure,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    D-eveloping (or building) geometry,
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    E-valuating (or checking) geometry for correctness, and
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    L-ogging (or creating) documentation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
	The remaining sections of this document address each of these steps in
	turn.
      </para>

      <para>
	As shown in Figure 3, the modeling process can be thought of as a wagon
	wheel with five spokes. Each spoke extends out from the inner hub--the
	model's mission--and is equally important in giving the wheel its strength
	and functionality. Also, although it is common to consider the steps in
	the order in which they are listed (i.e., M then O then D then E then L),
	the modeling process is dynamic, and it is not unusual for a particular
	phase to occur in a different order, to repeat itself, or to be skipped
	altogether as a project develops.
      </para>

      <figure><info><title>M-O-D-E-L: the five-stage modeling process.</title></info>
	
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig03.png" format="PNG"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      
      <para>
	For example, the organization phase is often the first step in large or
	complex modeling projects because it helps the modeler establish a tree
	structure that will guide him in collecting/measuring the right (or right
	amount of) data. Also, the modeler often detects missing or inaccurate
	data in the geometry development phase, which requires a return to the
	measurement phase. Finally, in cases involving the conversion of geometry
	from another source, the measurement and development phases might be
	nonapplicable, and a modeler might skip directly to the evaluation phase.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="volIIImeasuringdata"><info><title>Measuring data</title></info>
    
    
    <para>
      Unless a modeler is creating a conceptually new geometry, he must work
      from a variety of information sources to build a model. In some cases,
      blueprints or mechanical drawings exist. In others, a trip to the field is
      required to physically measure objects and orientations. In still others,
      geometry exists in another CAD format and needs to be converted to BRL-CAD
      format. As shown in Table 1, each type of measurement source has its own
      set of advantages and disadvantages, depending on the modeler's and/or
      user's point of view.
    </para>

    <table><info><title>Various modeling data sources.</title></info>
      
      <tgroup cols="3" align="center">
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      Data Sources
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Advantages
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Disadvantages
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      <para>
		Blueprints/schematics/mechanical drawings/photographs
	      </para>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig30.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can save time/resources by providing precise measurements with minimal data collection 
	      effort.  Can also suggest ways to structure the model (e.g., by providing wiring diagrams, 
	      subsystem schematics, etc.).
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can sometimes be difficult to read.  Do not always show all needed measurements or views.  
	      Are not always consistent with the actual objects they represent (e.g., design changes 
	      sometimes occur during development or manufacturing).
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      <para>
		Measurable objects
	      </para>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig21.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can arguably provide the best source of verifiable information by providing hands-on 
	      access to the actual objects being modeled.
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can be resource and labor intensive and can be limited by the objects’ availability, 
	      accessibility, and measurability, resulting in missed measurements.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>
	      <para>
		Converted geometry
	      </para>
	      <para>
		<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig22.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
	      </para>
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can offer significant savings in data collection and/or measurement efforts.
	    </entry>
	    <entry>
	      Can have missing data, unfamiliar naming schemes, and alternate/dissimilar geometry 
	      formats (e.g., feature-based objects, splines, etc.).  Can also be unsuitable for a 
	      given application because the original model was developed for a different purpose.
	    </entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      Regardless of the type information source used, there are several simple
      keys to obtaining data. These keys often require a little extra time and
      effort in the early stages of the modeling process, but they can save
      significantly more time and effort later on (especially if multiple
      modelers are involved in the project). Several of these keys are
      identified as follows:
    </para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Leverage all sources available:</emphasis> Although one of the previously
	    mentioned sources may be the primary one from which a modeler will work,
	    all available photographs, drawings, converted geometry, etc., should be
	    used together to spot-check and verify the information given. Sometimes
	    schematics are mislabeled, mistakes are made while measuring, or geometry
	    from other CAD packages does not convert properly. The only way to catch
	    some of these errors is to compare them against another source.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Get information while it is available:</emphasis> With the many data points
	    involved in building complex geometry, it is not uncommon to find during
	    geometry development that not all required information was obtained during
	    the data measurement/collection phase. Important components and/or
	    dimensions can be overlooked, and it may be inconvenient or impossible
	    (e.g., with a combat vehicle) to recollect, remeasure, or reconvert what
	    is missing. Thus, a modeler should be as thorough as possible when
	    obtaining data. Even if it is not clear whether a piece of geometry or
	    measurement will be required, it can always be discarded later if not
	    needed. Also, in the spirit of the carpenter's maxim, it is a good idea to
	    "measure twice and cut once" and double-check measured or converted
	    geometry before it is placed in a model.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Get total lengths and total views:</emphasis> Modelers sometimes take relative
	    measurements of objects across a face without measuring the entire
	    length/width of the face. Unfortunately, at the end, the measurements do
	    not always add up. It is much easier to "back out" missed or inaccurate
	    measurements given total lengths/widths. Likewise, when photographing
	    portions of a bigger object (e.g., a radiator on a truck), it is a good
	    idea to also capture several "bird's eye" views of encompassing objects
	    (e.g., the engine compartment or the entire truck) to help establish
	    overall reference points.
	  </para>
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      For a series of uniformly spaced objects, it is good practice to      
	      measure the total length of the series and divide by the number of    
	      objects. This helps spread out any inaccuracies along the span and    
	      prevents them from accumulating at the last object. For example, in a 
	      row of 20 bolts at 50-mm intervals, a measurement error of just 2 mm  
	      between bolts could result in the last bolt being nearly 40 mm out of 
	      position.                                                             
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Record measurements as clearly and consistently as possible:</emphasis> It is
	    interesting how a "scribble" that is perfectly understandable to the
	    measurement-taker who is still in front of the object can become
	    indecipherable when it is later viewed back in the office (when the object
	    is no longer accessible). Furthermore, despite the best laid plans,
	    projects and personnel can change in midstream, and the person(s) taking
	    measurements may wind up having little or no connection to the person(s)
	    actually interpreting those measurements and building the model.
	    Therefore, all drawings and notations should be sufficiently clear and
	    consistent so that someone unfamiliar with the object could understand and
	    work with the recorded measurements. A few recommendations are given as
	    follows:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Include meaningful titles on drawings:</emphasis> Detailed drawings and data can
		  be of little value if it is unclear what the overall geometry/view is and
		  how the designated piece ties into the completed model.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>In general, orient drawings in orthogonal views:</emphasis> This practice
		  eliminates potential problems associated with perspective and makes
		  drawings easier to read and use. If other angles are desired (and it is
		  not a bad idea to include at least one off-angle view with a few
		  measurements to help confirm reference points), be sure to include
		  azimuth/elevation and information about the orientation relative to the
		  eye point and to the actual vehicle coordinate system. In addition, note
		  any atypical configurations and orientations (e.g., a tank turret rotated
		  in an unusual fashion to allow access to certain components).
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Include offsets from other objects:</emphasis> Although these measurements may not
		  actually be primary data (i.e., required inputs for MGED commands), they
		  may help the modeler resolve problems or derive other measurements needed
		  later. For example, when modeling a field of objects on a flat surface
		  (e.g., gauges and buttons on an instrument panel), it is good practice not
		  only to collect the distances of the objects from, say, the edges of the
		  panel but also the distances relative to other objects. This information
		  can be valuable when trying to troubleshoot overlaps or other problems
		  encountered during the evaluation phase.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Clearly record small details and symbols:</emphasis> When recording measurements,
		  it is important to remember that even small details (such as arrows,
		  edges, centers, thicknesses, numbers, and units) can lead to possible
		  confusion. Arrows too long or too short can be mistaken for pointing to a
		  shape's edge instead of its center, hastily written numbers can be
		  mistaken for other numbers (e.g., "1" vs. "7"), unidentified inner
		  diameters can be confused with outer diameters, unidentified units can be
		  assumed to be other units, etc. The table below lists some standard symbols and
		  abbreviations that are commonly used when recording measurements.
		</para>
		<figure><info><title>Commonly used measurement symbols and abbreviations.</title></info>
		  
		    <mediaobject>
	               <imageobject>
			   <imagedata fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_table_image_1.png" format="PNG"/>
		       </imageobject>
		       <caption align="left">
			  <para>[a] Intersection and union symbols presented here
			  should not be confused with the intersection (+) and union (u) symbols used
			  to represent and execute Boolean operations in BRL-CAD.</para>
		       </caption>
		    </mediaobject>
		  </figure>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </chapter>
 
  <chapter xml:id="volIIIorganizing"><info><title>Organizing the Structure</title></info>
    
     <para>
       Taking the time to map out a tree structure of an object before building
       it is another important step in the modeling process, especially if the
       object being constructed is elaborate, if modeling time and resources are
       limited, if the work is being performed as a team, or if the model will be
       passed on to someone else later.
     </para>
     <para>
       If we consider the construction of a house, we know that builders do not
       actually build houses; they build pieces of a house until the completed
       structure emerges. Furthermore, these pieces are not usually built in a
       random order. Rather, a good builder (often as part of a team of
       carpenters, masons, electricians, plumbers, etc.) follows blueprints or
       drawings that group the pieces into categories based on their
       functionality (e.g., framing, wiring, plumbing, etc.) or location (e.g.,
       basement, bedroom no. 1, kitchen, etc.).
     </para>
     <para>
       The modeling process can be thought of in much the same way. Before
       anything is built, a modeler should take on the role of an architect and
       lay out a logical way to break down a potentially complicated object into
       smaller, more manageable pieces. Also, this step can often reveal a
       logical building order (e.g., the drywall does not get installed until the
       wiring inside the walls has been run) as well as identify important
       interconnectivities among parts.
     </para>
     <para>
       The following list provides some tips to achieve good model structuring:
     </para>
     
     <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use a top-down approach:</emphasis>  It is a good idea to design the structure
	    using a top-down approach, beginning with the largest, most encompassing,
	    or most functionally significant parts/systems and working down from
	    there. Once again, the model's mission is all-important here. If an
	    armored tank is being modeled for a ballistic analysis, the model should
	    probably be structured so that all the pieces connected to the turret are
	    grouped together and, therefore, can move together when the turret is
	    rotated.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Take advantage of established organizational conventions:</emphasis> It is wise to
	    follow any traditional or widely used conventions that might be available
	    in, say, an owner's or operator's manual. If a mechanic or user would
	    normally expect a particular component to be part of a suspension system,
	    then it is wise for the modeler to structure his model accordingly unless
	    there is a good reason to do otherwise.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use good naming practices:</emphasis> Closely associated with the idea of using
	    good organizational conventions to structure geometry is the idea of using
	    good naming conventions to name geometry. Although naming may appear to be
	    a trivial matter, the fact is that it is not always easy to establish
	    titles and schemes that are intuitive, robust, and useful in helping the
	    end user know where he is in a potentially complex model.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    There are few limitations to how files and objects can be named in BRL-CAD
	    (other than that each file/object name must be unique). However, new
	    modelers soon find that random or haphazard naming schemes lead to
	    inefficiency and frustration. Thus, the following general recommendations
	    are provided to help modelers efficiently organize and track what they
	    build.
	    
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  Develop logical schemes, stick to them, and document them: If logical
		  or obvious titling schemes (such as a manufacturer's part names or
		  numbers) are already in place, the user should take advantage of them,
		  especially at the highest assembly levels of "complete" or aggregated
		  objects and especially when multiple modelers are involved. This practice
		  helps establish a logical structure (e.g., all engine parts have a prefix
		  of, say, eng), and many users may already know these names.
		</para>
		<para>
		  Table 3 provides examples of a number of other logical naming conventions
		  traditionally used in BRL-CAD. These conventions include (1) an initial
		  nametag to designate shape/object type or function (i.e., sph for sphere,
		  ant for antenna, and frf for front face); (2) a suffix (or prefix) to
		  designate MGED object type (i.e., .s for primitive shapes [formerly
		  referred to as "solids"], .r for regions, .c for shape combinations, and
		  .a or .g for assembly combinations); and (3) some sort of sequential
		  numbering scheme (i.e., 1, 2, 3, etc.). For more information on BRL-CAD
		  shapes and modeling levels, see Section 5, as well as Lesson 5 and
		  Appendix C of BRL-CAD Tutorial Volume II (Butler et al., 2001).
		</para>
		<table><info><title>Examples of naming conventions.</title></info>
		  
		  <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
		    <tbody>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  Name
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Rationale
			</entry>
		      </row>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  <literallayout class="monospaced">
sph.s1,
sph.r1,
sph.c1
			  </literallayout>
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Associates the name with primitive shape type (sphere), order of creation (1), 
			  and MGED object type (shape [.s], region [.r], or combination [.c]).  Often used 
			  for training or testing BRL-CAD functionality but not recommended for large, 
			  complex models<footnote><para>Sometimes the primitive shape tags are used to name 
			  temporary objects that the modeler knows will be replaced or discarded.  In this case, 
			  a more intuitive, functional name, such as “temp,” is recommended.</para></footnote>
			</entry>
		      </row>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  <literallayout class="monospaced">
ant.s1,
ant.r1, 
ant.c1
			  </literallayout>
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Associates the name with type of function (antenna), order of creation (1), and MGED 
			  object type (shape [.s], region [.r], or shape combination [.c]).  
			</entry>
		      </row>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  <literallayout class="monospaced">
frf.s1-1,
frf.s1+1,
frf.s1
			  </literallayout>
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Associates the name with function (front face), MGED object type and order of 
			  creation (.s1), and type of Boolean operation performed (subtraction [−] and 
			  intersection [+]).<footnote><para>Note that we have chosen not to associate a 
			  suffix for objects that are unioned.  In this naming convention, objects without 
			  a Boolean operation suffix are understood to be unioned.</para></footnote>  
			  This is the notation currently used with the Build Pattern tool.
			</entry>
		      </row>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  <literallayout class="monospaced">
front_face.a, 
right_antenna.a, 
left_roadwheel.a
			  </literallayout>
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Gives the assembly combination levels (.a) more descriptive titles to better
			  designate overall model composition and/or functionality for the end user.
			</entry>
		      </row>
		      <row>
			<entry>
			  <literallayout class="monospaced">
Driver  Main_Gun 
M1A1
			  </literallayout>
			</entry>
			<entry>
			  Gives top-level assemblies human-readable descriptions of overall composition 
			  and/or functionality.  Uses initial capitalization to show higher tree level 
			  and disregards traditional MGED suffix.
			</entry>
		      </row>
		    </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</table>

		<para>
		  Note that the suffix at the end of names is particularly useful for
		  searching for similar items in large tree structures and for using MGED
		  automation features such as the Build Pattern tool and the build_region
		  command (see Appendices E and F).
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Keep names short:</emphasis> Prior to BRL-CAD  release 6.0, all BRL-CAD names were
		  limited to 16 characters. In some respects, this "limitation" was useful,
		  compelling new modelers to resist the common urge to name primitives with
		  as much detail as possible. Although the length restriction no longer
		  applies, it is still a good idea, especially in large models (and with
		  frequently used objects), to keep names of objects as short as possible so
		  as to reduce the amount of typing the modeler must do and, thus, reduce
		  the possibility for input errors. In addition, some vulnerability analysis
		  codes do not support names longer than 16 characters.
		</para>
		<para>
		  As shown in Table 3, an exception to the practice of keeping names short
		  includes the names at the assembly combination level and above, where
		  fewer names are used and more descriptive titles can be helpful in
		  designating overall model composition and structure for the end user.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Establish "reserve" names:</emphasis> In projects that involve multiple modelers
		  developing different pieces of the same geometry, it is helpful in some
		  cases to reserve particular name designations to avoid possible confusion.
		  For example, a team of modelers developing an armored vehicle might choose
		  to reserve the letter "h" to denote the "nametag" for only those
		  components associated with the hull (e.g., "h.s1," "h.s2," etc.). This
		  would mean that those modelers building, say, headlight assemblies would
		  have to choose another designation (e.g., "hlght.s1," "hlght.s2," etc.).
		  This standardization can also be helpful in establishing common
		  terminology for later projects with the same or similar components.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  <emphasis>Avoid using certain letters and symbols:</emphasis> To avoid potential problems
		  associated with common UNIX notation, searching schemes, and certain
		  survivability, lethality, and vulnerability (SLV) analysis codes, the
		  following recommendations (or, in some cases, requirements) are made
		  regarding the use of keyboard characters in BRL-CAD names:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Use lowercase Arabic letters (except for the previously mentioned
		      initial capitalization used for top-level assemblies).
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Use numerals without internal commas (e.g., "5000" not "5,000").
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Avoid using numerals to begin a name.
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Do not use a space between words; use an underline or capitalize the
		      first character of each word (i.e., Hungarian notation).
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Avoid using special characters. Restrict the use of "+" and """
		      symbols to the suffix of primitive shape combinations, and do not  use the
		      "/".
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Restrict the use of the period to the suffix of MGED object types.
		      Avoid using other punctuation (e.g., "?," "!," etc.).
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem>
		    <para>
		      Avoid using the lowercase letter "l" by itself (to avoid possible
		      confusion with the number "1").
		    </para>
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Include the right amount of detail: The structure should only be as
	    deep as needed for the application. Obviously, every part, no matter how
	    complex, could in theory be reduced down to the atomic or even subatomic
	    level, but how cost efficient and useful would this be? More is not
	    necessarily better. The modeler should use common sense and consult with
	    the end user(s) when deciding how far to break down components and
	    systems. Insufficient detail can diminish the model's usefulness and
	    reduce user confidence, and yet too much detail can unnecessarily drain
	    time and resources, slow down processing time of application codes, and
	    frustrate users who have to wade through many parts that they do not need
	    to get to what they do need.
	  </para>
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      Note that it is not unusual for a modeler to select relatively        
	      arbitrary names when shapes and parts are first made and then go back 
	      and rename them as the model develops. There are two commands to      
	      rename database objects.
	    </para>
	    <para>                                                                           
	      To rename only the database object, type the following:               
	      <literallayout class="monospaced">
mv  oldname newname                          
	      </literallayout>
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      Note that this command changes only the name of a particular object   
	      and not any references to the object that may occur in combinations   
	      throughout the database.                                              
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      To change an object's name and all references to that object, the     
	      mvall (move all) command can be used as follows:                      
	      <literallayout class="monospaced">
mvall oldname newname                       
	      </literallayout>
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Use location- and function-based groupings: Components should be
	    grouped based on simple, logical categories such as location and/or
	    functionality. For example, the structure of the simple radio that was
	    built in Lesson 16 of Volume II of the BRL-CAD Tutorial Series (Butler et
	    al., 2001) could be set up in several ways. Figure 4 shows a structure
	    based on location, and Figure 5 shows a structure based on functionality.
	  </para>
	  <figure><info><title>Location-based structure of the radio in Volume II.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig04.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Function-based structure of the radio in Volume II.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig05.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <para>
	    The structuring phase, of course, gets trickier and more subjective as the
	    model gets more complex. Regardless of whether the structure is based on
	    location, function, or something else, it is not always clear which parts
	    belong to which structures. In fact, some parts are clearly designed to
	    interface between parts or systems, and so the modeler must choose where
	    he should place them in the tree structure. A consistent treatment of
	    these parts within the model is an important part of the user's ability to
	    understand and use the model.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    It is also important to remember that the tree structure in MGED is
	    independent of the geometry created. The structure is simply a tool to
	    help the user organize and work with the database. Accordingly, the tree
	    structure can be manipulated to suit whatever needs the user(s) may have.
	    Consider the example of a model of a room containing a table and a cup on
	    top of the table. If one wanted to relocate the table (along with the cup)
	    next to a wall, one could create a temporary combination containing the
	    table and the cup. This combination could then be used to move the two
	    objects together to their new location. After the objects are in position,
	    the temporary combination could be "pushed" (see discussion of the push
	    command in Section 5) and then deleted using the kill command (see
	    Appendix A of Volume II [Butler et al., 2001]).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

  </chapter>

  <chapter xml:id="volIIIdevgeometry"><info><title>Developing Geometry</title></info>
    
    <para>
      In the end, the heart of the modeling process is the actual construction
      of the geometry. All the best measurement, organization, evaluation, and
      documentation would be ineffective unless the geometric shapes that make
      up a model are built and built correctly.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Basically, there are two steps to geometry development: (1) <emphasis>creating
      geometry</emphasis>, and (2) <emphasis>positioning geometry</emphasis>. Of course, as with all the other
      phases in the modeling process, there are different schools of thought as
      to how these steps should be accomplished, and each method has its own set
      of advantages and disadvantages.
    </para>

    <para>
      Factors that need to be considered when deciding which methods to use
      include the convenience of building location and manner (e.g., building
      geometry at the origin or in an order that leverages previously defined
      measurements or mathematical calculations); the number of object
      replications that will be needed in the model; the ease of editing one or
      more of the replications; storage space; prep/rendering time; etc.
    </para>

    <para>
      The following are some general tips regarding the efficient development of
      geometry in BRL-CAD:
    </para>

     <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Build the main structure first:</emphasis> As mentioned previously,  it is a good
	    idea to start building with the "main" object of a model. This could be
	    the largest piece, the piece most central to the rest of the model, or a
	    piece whose location represents a prominent corner or point. Much like on
	    the assembly line of an automobile manufacturer, building the main frame
	    first provides an overall model coordinate system for the rest of the
	    smaller, secondary parts to reference. Also, for projects in which
	    multiple modelers work on separate pieces simultaneously, starting with
	    the main structure allows other pieces to be built in place or put in
	    position immediately upon completion. This practice is more efficient in
	    that it eliminates having extra parts floating around waiting to be
	    positioned, and it provides a better picture of model completion
	    throughout the project.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Know the four modeling levels and their differences:</emphasis> As shown in Table
	    4 (and discussed in Volume II [Butler et al., 2001]), all models built in
	    BRL-CAD are built within the confines of its four modeling levels: (1) the
	    primitive level, (2) the combination level, (3) the region level, and (4)
	    the assembly level. Knowing the characteristics of these modeling levels
	    is one of the first keys to developing effective geometry.
	  </para>

	  <table><info><title>The four modeling levels in BRL-CAD</title></info>
	    
	    <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Modeling Level
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Description
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Primitive level (.s)
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    This level is where one performs three-dimensional (3-D) CAD “sculpting,” working with 
		    the primitive shapes to represent the target geometry in coordinate space.  Objects at this 
		    level are not recognized as having volume or material properties.
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Combination level (.c)
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    This level is an optional intermediate level between primitives and regions or regions 
		    and assemblies.  It allows Booleaned objects to be subtracted and intersected.  All 
		    nonprimitive objects are stored as combinations.
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Region level (.r)
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    This level is the lowest level at which geometry occupies 3-D space and can have material 
		    properties. It is where one assembles primitives and defines positive volume using Boolean 
		    logic.  A region must be composed of one material, should be interconnected, and should 
		    perform the same function.  
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Assembly level (.a or .g)
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    This is the level at which subparts are organized into parts and parts are organized 
		    into assemblies.  This is also where meaningful names and appropriate hierarchical structure 
		    are applied.
		  </entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Know the major primitives and their constraints:</emphasis> Another key to good
	    model building is to understand the required inputs, editing options,
	    geometric characteristics, and relative advantages/disadvantages of the
	    package's basic "building blocks"--the primitive shapes. Although the
	    package currently has more than 20 primary primitives (as well as another
	    dozen developmental/special-use primitives), only a few of these
	    primitives are used on a regular basis (see Table 5). That is not to say,
	    of course, that less common shapes could not be used, but with some
	    experience, users can begin to "see geometry" in a relatively small set of
	    primitives and understand the data needed to produce accurate models.
	  </para>

	  <table><info><title>The major BRL-CAD primitives and parameters.</title></info>
	    
	    <tgroup cols="2" align="center">
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Primitive Shape/BRL-CAD Abbreviation
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Input Parameters/Definitions<footnote><para>To maximize database efficiency, some shape 
		    types are stored as other types (e.g., all arbs are stored as arb8's), but this behavior
		    is invisible to the user.</para></footnote>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig24.png" format="PNG"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			      Arbitrary convex polyhedron, 8 pts (arb8)
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  8 vertices, 6 faces, and 12 edges
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Each face must be a plane.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Illegal variations include the following: 
			</para>
			<para>
			  <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig23.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig25.png" format="PNG"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			      Arbitrary convex polyhedron, 6 pts (arb6)
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  6 vertices, 5 faces, and 9 edges.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Stored as an arb8, where point 8 is coincident with point 5 and point 7 is      
			  coincident with point 6
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig26.png" format="PNG"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			      Sphere (sph) 
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Vertex, V.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Radii, A, B, C.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Stored as an ellipsoid (ell).  
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			   Vectors A, B, and C are mutually perpendicular.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig27.png" format="PNG"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			     Right circular cylinder (rcc) 
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>		    
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Vertex, V.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Radii, A, B, C, D.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Height vector, H (base-to-top distance).
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Stored as a truncated general cone (tgc).
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Vectors A and B have equal lengths, C and D have equal lengths, and all vectors are   
			  perpendicular to H.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig28.png" format="PNG"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			      Torus (tor)
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>		    
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Vertex, V (center of hole).
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Normal direction for the plane of the ring.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Radius 1 (radius from V to center of tube).
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Radius 2 (radius of tube).
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    <para>
		      <informalfigure>
			<mediaobject>
			  <imageobject>
			    <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig29.png"/>
			  </imageobject>
			  <caption>
			    <para>
			      Pipe (pipe)
			    </para>
			  </caption>
			</mediaobject>
		      </informalfigure>
		    </para>		    
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist mark="dash">
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Outer diameter (OD). 
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Inner diameter (ID). 
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Bend radius (equivalent to an r1 value of a torus). 
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Each point contains X, Y, Z coordinates, OD, ID, and bend radius data.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Is effectively a subregion combination of cylinders and bounded tori whose path is    
			  defined by a series of coordinates.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table>

	  <note>
	    <para>
	      For a list of all the primary primitives and their shapes, see        
	      Appendix C of BRL-CAD Tutorial Volume II (Butler et al., 2001) or     
	      consult http://ftp.arl.army.mil/brlcad/ (U.S. ARL, 2003). For       
	      detailed guidance on using the pipe and the extruded bitmap (ebm)     
	      primitives, see Appendices A and C of this volume.
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use the best command to build primitives:</emphasis> In addition to understanding
	    the package's basic building blocks and modeling levels, it is important
	    to understand the behavior and advantages/disadvantages of its basic
	    building "tools" (see Table 6). Using the right building command at the
	    right time can maximize modeling efficiency by, in some cases, taking
	    advantage of data from previously built geometry and saving measurement
	    and/or input time.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Build objects in the most convenient location: Although coordinate
	    systems vary according to the type of situation (e.g., converted geometry
	    or group modeling, where a particular orientation has been established),
	    BRL-CAD models are generally centered at the origin (x y z = 0 0 0), where
	    the +X axis is front, the +Y axis is left, and the +Z axis is up.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    For objects that are symmetrical in nature, this practice can take
	    advantage of BRL-CAD's mirroring operations and can provide simpler
	    reference numbers for objects that are more complex in composition and/or
	    orientation. In some cases, however, the modeler will find it makes more
	    sense to build objects in place in the model. These include cases in which
	    previously created objects offer convenient reference numbers for the
	    object's location/orientation and cases in which tangencies and other
	    necessary calculations would be more difficult to derive with the object
	    at the origin.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Note that there are traditional coordinate system conventions that some
	    organizations use for their target descriptions (Ellis, 1992; Robertson et
	    al., 1996; Winner et al., 2002). For a turreted vehicle, the origin is
	    traditionally located at the intersection of the axis of the turret
	    rotation and the ground surface. The +X axis points to the front of the
	    vehicle, the +Y axis points toward the vehicle's left, and the +Z points
	    up (see Figure 6). For a nonturreted vehicle, the axes are the same, but
	    there is no axis of rotation to provide a definitive reference point. So,
	    the origin is located at the intersection of the ground surface and a
	    convenient point along the left-right, mid-plane of the vehicle (see
	    Figure 7). For fixed-wing and rotary-wing aircraft, the axes are the same,
	    but the origin is located on the front nose of the airframe (see Figures 8
	    and 9).
	  </para>
	  
	  <table><info><title>Various ways to build primitives.</title></info>
	    
	    <tgroup cols="4" align="center">
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    MGED Command
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Behavior
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Advantages/Disadvantages
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Method of Input
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    create
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a “generic” primitive shape based on the user’s screen size and center.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates shape without having to input parameter/location values; primitive usually 
		    requires further editing; puts user into edit mode. 
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Graphical user interface (GUI)
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    make
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a “generic” primitive shape based on the user’s screen size and center.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates shape without having to input parameter/location values; primitive 
		    requires further editing.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    in
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a new primitive shape according to user-input parameter values and location.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Allows user to create a shape in a specific size and location without having to further edit it.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    inside
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a primitive shape by referencing a previously created shape and applying user-defined 
		    positive/negative thicknesses to faces (e.g., making an interior wall).
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Allows user to create a shape based on a specified primitive by applying wall thicknesses 
		    without having to further edit it.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    cp
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a duplicate of a previously defined object.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Copies the parameters of an object to a new object of the same type.  Takes advantage of 
		    previously defined measurements and locations.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    cpi (copy index)
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Originally created to model wiring or piping runs; creates a duplicate cylinder whose 
		    base vertex is coincident with the top of the original cylinder.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Can only be used with cylinders; takes advantage of previously defined measurements 
		    and locations; puts user into edit mode automatically.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    mirror
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a duplicate primitive shape, region, or assembly and locates it across 
		    the x axis, y axis, z axis, or an arbitrary axis specified by a point and a direction.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Takes advantage of previously defined measurements and locations; can mirror across 
		    only one axis at a time but across any point along that axis.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    pattern
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Creates a rectangular, spherical, or cylindrical pattern of primitive shapes, regions, 
		    or assemblies by referencing a previously created object and applying user-defined offsets 
		    and parameters.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Takes advantage of previously defined measurements and locations; requires extra 
		    positioning measurements.
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    GUI or command line
		  </entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table>
	  
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      Note the in and inside commands are often the best ways to create a   
	      primitive in the right size/location if the modeler knows the         
	      parameters. Also, using the cp and mirror commands to create          
	      primitives can often save time by taking advantage of previously      
	      established measurements/positioning.
	    </para>
	  </note>


	  <figure><info><title>Coordinate axes of a turreted ground vehicle.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig06.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Coordinate axes of a nonturreted ground vehicle.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig07.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Coordinate axes of a fixed-wing aircraft.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig08.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Coordinate axes of a rotary-wing aircraft.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig09.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Build multiple occurrences of objects in the most advantageous manner:</emphasis>
	    Sometimes a modeler will have to make several occurrences of an object.
	    For example, imagine modeling a box of new, identical pencils. Wouldn't it
	    be convenient to take advantage of the similarities involved? There are
	    two basic techniques for constructing such collections. The first involves
	    actually replicating geometry; the second involves referencing shared
	    geometry.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Regardless of the technique used, the modeler typically starts by creating
	    a prototype of the object. In the first technique (illustrated in Figure
	    10), the modeler creates complete copies of the object to be replicated.
	    Each copy is then positioned within the model. In the second technique
	    (illustrated in Figure 11), a "reference" combination that contains only
	    the prototype is created. This combination is then positioned within the
	    model.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    As shown in Table 7, there are tradeoffs to be considered when using each
	    of these approaches. Construction effort is one of them. If the prototype
	    consists of many objects or layers of structure, replication could be a
	    tedious task. In the box of pencils, for example, all of the structure of
	    the pencil would have to be duplicated, including the wood, eraser,
	    barrel, and lead. On the other hand, if the referencing approach is used,
	    then a relatively minor amount of work is needed to create the multiple
	    occurrences.
	  </para>

	  <figure><info><title>Building multiple occurrences through replication.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig10.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>

	  <figure><info><title>Building multiple occurrences through referencing.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig11.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  
	  <table><info><title>Advantages and disadvantages of replication vs. referencing.</title></info>
	    
	    <tgroup cols="3" align="center">
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Duplication Method
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Advantages
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    Disadvantages
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		   Replication 
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  No matrices.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Faster prep time for raytracing.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  More effort to construct.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Loss of update relationship between occurrences.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>
		    Referencing
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Easier to create.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Changes to prototype propagate to all occurrences.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Uses less disk space when creating many occurrences of complex objects.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		  <entry>
		    <itemizedlist>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Does not provide a unique object, which is required by some analysis codes.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		      <listitem>
			<para>
			  Prototype parameters do not reflect location and orientation of an individual reference.
			</para>
		      </listitem>
		    </itemizedlist>
		  </entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table>

	  <para>
	    Also, if the modeler wants to make a change to all of the objects (e.g.,
	    sharpening the point of the pencil), then the referencing approach has
	    definite advantages. The prototype object is edited to incorporate the
	    change, and all occurrences automatically reflect that change. However, if
	    only one object is to be modified, then a copy of the prototype must be
	    made, and the reference for that item must now refer to the copy. Not
	    surprisingly, when this type of operation is to be performed often, the
	    replication approach has definite advantages over the referencing
	    approach.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    Referencing also has the advantage that it can reduce the amount of disk
	    space needed to store multiple copies of complex objects. The extra space
	    needed to store each new occurrence on disk consists of the transformation
	    matrix and the name of the object and reference combination. This can be
	    significantly smaller than the replication of all the geometry that makes
	    up the prototype.
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    It should be noted, however, that because some analysis codes require a
	    unique identifier for each object in the database, some agencies require
	    that all occurrences be replicated to the primitive level without
	    matrices.
	  </para>
	  
	  <para>
	    There are several other tools that can make the duplication process
	    easier--namely, the Build Pattern tool and the keep and dbconcat commands.
	    The Build Pattern tool, which is discussed in Appendix E, can help the
	    modeler automatically generate multiple copies of geometry in rectangular,
	    spherical, or cylindrical patterns. The keep  command can be used to save
	    portions of geometry, and the dbconcat command can be used to concatenate
	    (add) them to other geometries or reinsert them into the existing database
	    as copies.
	  </para>

	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use the  push command to eliminate matrices from replicated geometry:</emphasis>
	    When the replication technique has been used to copy a particular piece of
	    geometry, the <command>push</command> command is frequently used to walk the geometry tree
	    from a specified top to the primitive level and collect the matrix
	    transformations (i.e., any translations, rotations, or scales applied to
	    the new assembly using matrix edits). The push command applies the matrix
	    transformation to the parameters of the primitives, eliminating the need
	    for storing the matrices. One disadvantage of this operation is that any
	    local coordinate system used in constructing objects is lost.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use the best method for exporting and importing pieces of a database:</emphasis>
	    Sometimes a modeler will want to save a portion of a model to be added to
	    another database, to be reinserted into the original database as a copy,
	    to be saved for future use, or to be edited as a new database (e.g., using
	    a crew member or engine from one database in a different database). There
	    are two commonly used methods to export and import geometry in BRL-CAD:
	    (1) using the keep and dbconcat commands from the command line, or
	    (2) using the export and import commands from the GUI.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    For the first method, the keep command exports data either creating a new
	    database file or appending objects to an existing database. The form of
	    the command is as follows:
	    <literallayout class="normal">
mged&gt;  keep filename.g object(s)
	    </literallayout>
	    The <command>dbconcat</command> command adds the contents of an existing database file to the
	    database currently open. The user may import the database as is or choose
	    to rename each element of the geometry by specifying a prefix. The user
	    may alternatively use the -s or -p option to add a computer-generated
	    suffix (-s) or prefix (-p). The form of the command is as follows:
	    <literallayout class="normal">
mged&gt;  dbconcat [-s, -p] filename.g [prefix]
	    </literallayout>
	    As mentioned previously, every BRL-CAD object must have a unique name;
	    however, when combining geometry from more than one database, there may be
	    duplicate names (especially if a modeler uses standard naming conventions
	    in all of his models). If there are name collisions, the package will
	    automatically add computer-generated prefixes to the duplicate items in
	    the concatenated geometry. The default prefix names are of the form A_,
	    B_, C_, etc. Note that these prefixes will not be added to the member
	    names in existing combinations in the database. This allows the user to
	    edit or remove this geometry independently of existing data, preventing
	    unintentional overwriting of the existing database items.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Another way to move data  to and from separate databases is by using the
	    export and import commands in MGED's GUI. Located under the File menu,
	    these commands allow the user to choose either ASCII or binary objects.
	    They perform the same functions as their command-line counterparts. (When
	    exporting, if no objects are selected, the default objects will be any
	    that are currently displayed in the graphics window.)
	  </para>

	  <para>
	    It is good modeling practice to check for duplicate names before inserting
	    new geometry into your database. To check for duplicates, use the dup
	    command from the command line. This command compares external database
	    file object names with current database file object names and reports
	    duplicate names. The form of the dup command is as follows:
	    <literallayout class="normal">
mged&gt;  dbconcat [-s, -p] filename.g [prefix]
	    </literallayout>
	    Note that there is currently no GUI equivalent to the dup command.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Keep bounding primitives as small and compact as possible:</emphasis> Although it
	    is possible to use large primitives to achieve intersected or subtracted
	    shapes in BRL-CAD (e.g., using a large sphere to create the relatively
	    flat curve of a radar dish), using bounding or subtraction primitives that
	    extend significantly beyond the outer boundaries of the positive volume of
	    the region is generally not recommended because it slows down raytracing
	    applications and can make wireframe geometry more difficult to view,
	    especially in a complex database.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Imagine that a user wants half of a sphere for the target geometry (see
	    Figure 12). In some cases, the user might want to use a large primitive
	    that already exists in the database because it is in the proper
	    location/orientation or because it requires no edits. The user should
	    recognize, however, that whenever this object is rendered, any rays that
	    pass through the large bounding primitive will have to do the extra
	    calculation to determine whether or not the ray is in the positive volume
	    for that region (see Figure 13). Therefore, whenever possible, the use of
	    smaller, more compact bounding primitives is recommended (see Figure 14).
	  </para>
	  <figure><info><title>Target geometry.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig12.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Example of an Overly Large Bounding Primitive.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig13.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  <figure><info><title>Example of a compact bounding primitive.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig14.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>

	  <note>
	    <para>
	      The half space is a prime example of an overly large bounding         
	      primitive. Because its extent is infinite, it is always larger than   
	      needed. Therefore, whenever possible, the modeler should use an arb8  
	      or other primitive that can be dimensioned to meet the modeling       
	      needs.
	    </para>
	  </note>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Consider the possibility of articulations, animations, and
	    presentations:</emphasis> Sometimes models need to be able to simulate movement in
	    parts and personnel or to show unique views for presentation purposes.
	    Unfortunately, the modeler (or even the user) cannot always predict all
	    the possible uses at the outset of a project. Therefore, it is wise,
	    especially in organizations that use many different types of model
	    applications, to try to design and build models with the thought that they
	    may need to be articulated, animated, or presented in different
	    configurations at some point.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    For articulation and animation, this generally means that objects that
	    normally move together (e.g., components on a helicopter rotor, tank
	    turret, etc.) should be grouped together in assembly combinations (as
	    shown in Figure 15).

	    <figure><info><title>Example of grouping objects for articulation.</title></info>
	      
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig15.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	    </figure>
	    In the example shown in Figure 15, we would want to create a turret_asy
	    assembly with turret_armor, main_gun, and commanders_hatch in it.	    
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Also, as discussed in Lesson 16 of Volume II (Butler et al., 2001),
	    specialty models or assemblies can be made to simulate changes in model
	    configuration (e.g., personnel hatches opened/closed, crew compartments
	    occupied/unoccupied, fuel tanks full/half full/empty, etc.) or to show
	    views not normally seen (e.g., transparent skin or cross-sectional cutouts
	    to show internal components, similarly colored components to show
	    subsystem categorization, etc.). Specialty models usually involve copying
	    the original model or assembly, altering the copy to achieve the special
	    effect, and then substituting in the copy as needed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Understand and use Boolean operations properly:</emphasis> Because Boolean
	    operations play such a vital role in building geometry, it is important
	    that the modeler possesses a good understanding of them. As shown in Table
	    4, a combination is the BRL-CAD database record that stores Boolean
	    operations. It can take one of three forms:
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Primitive shape combination</emphasis>  - a combination that intersects,
		subtracts, or unions primitive shapes. This combination does not actually
		occupy 3-D space.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Region</emphasis> - the lowest-level combination that assigns material properties
		to geometry and occupies 3-D space. Because it is impossible for two or
		more objects to occupy the same physical space, it follows that one region
		cannot be unioned into or intersected with another region (e.g., a wheel
		cannot occupy the same space as the axle that connects to it). Conversely,
		subtraction is valid (e.g., subtracting a wall-mounted radio from the wall
		on which it hangs). For a reminder of how Boolean combinations work, see
		Figure 16.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Assembly combination</emphasis> - a type of combination that associates two or
		more regions or other combinations together.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <figure><info><title>Sample Boolean operations.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig16.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  
	  <para>
	    Combinations can be created with a variety of commands, depending on the
	    user's requirements. These commands include the following:
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>comb</emphasis> - creates a combination using Boolean expressions in GIFT
		<footnote><para>Geometric information for targets (GIFT) is the single-level operator 
		hierarchy format that is the traditional (and default)
		notation used in BRL-CAD.</para></footnote> format.
		Proceeding left to right, intersections (+) and subtractions (") are
		performed before unions (u). For example, the command
		<literallayout class="normal">
comb comb_name u a - b + c
		</literallayout>
		is evaluated as
		<literallayout class="normal">
((a - b) + c).
		</literallayout>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>c</emphasis> - creates a combination using parenthetically ordered Boolean
		expressions. Where no order is indicated, intersections are performed
		before subtractions or unions, and then subtractions and unions, which
		have equal precedence, are performed left to right.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  <emphasis>r</emphasis> - creates a region out of primitive shapes or assembly combinations
		  using Boolean expressions in GIFT format. Unless the user specifies
		  otherwise, default region ID, air code, line-of-sight density, and GIFT
		  material values are assigned.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      
	      <para>
		<emphasis>g</emphasis>creates a combination by automatically unioning all user-specified
		elements together. Thus, this command does not accept any sort of Boolean
		operators from the user.<footnote><para>The <command>g</command> command is derived from “group,” 
		the term sometimes used for <emphasis>assembly combination</emphasis>.</para></footnote>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>		  

	  <para>
	    In addition, there are several general recommended practices when dealing
	    with Boolean operations. They are as follows:
	  </para>
	  
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Start with a positive volume:</emphasis> The modeler must start with a positive
		volume before any subtraction or intersection operations are performed. If
		you are using GIFT notation, this means that you must start with a union
		operator. If you are using fully parenthesized standard notation, this
		means that you must specify an object before specifying a subtraction or
		intersection from it.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		<emphasis>Be mindful of the order of Boolean operations:</emphasis> The modeler should make
		sure unions, intersections, and subtractions are properly ordered in the
		region structure to achieve the desired effect. For example, imagine that
		a modeler wants to subtract a hole in a region named bolt.r. As shown in
		Figure 17, if that region consists of two unioned primitives--head.s and
		shaft.s--the subtraction in the region must follow the shaft primitive.
		Alternatively, if the hole is subtracted from the head, the subtraction
		will have no effect because head.s and hole.s do not share any volume.		  
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  
	  <figure><info><title>Properly (top) and improperly (bottom) ordered regions.</title></info>
	    
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig17.png" format="PNG"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </figure>
	  
	  <note>
	    <para>
	      Note that in BRL-CAD releases 6.0 and later, fully parenthesized      
	      Boolean expressions are available for the c command. This allows the  
	      user to designate operator precedence on the command line based on    
	      standard parenthetical notation as opposed to the order-of-occurrence 
	      and union-last methodology, which is the previously described         
	      functionality in BRL-CAD.
	    </para>
	  </note>
	  
	</listitem>
	
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Follow or develop standardized conventions for colorizing objects:</emphasis>
	    When displaying a complex model, it is sometimes difficult for the user to
	    visually differentiate one system, subsystem, or component from another.
	    Also, it is not always clear as to which components belong to which
	    systems/subsystems. Therefore, if possible, it is good practice to follow
	    a standardized RGB (red-green-blue) color scheme for commonly
	    modeled/analyzed systems (e.g., engine, suspension, communications, etc.).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Table 8 shows some RGB colors traditionally used in MGED (out of a
	    possible 17 million color combinations between black [0 0 0] and white
	    [255 255 255]) (Applin et al., 1988). Table 9 shows some commonly used
	    system-color assignments for various ground and air target descriptions
	    (as drawn in a graphics display window with a black background) (Robertson
	    et al., 1996; Winner et al., 2002).
	  </para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Take advantage of advanced/automation modeling tools:</emphasis> BRL-CAD offers
	    many tools that can help users perform advanced functions or automate
	    complex or tedious aspects of the geometry development process. Examples
	    of some these tools, which are discussed in Appendices A-F, include the
	    pipe primitive (which can automate the building of wiring or hydraulic
	    lines), the projection shader (which can paste words or images onto
	    geometry instead of having to build them), the extruded bitmap (which can
	    turn two-dimensional objects [e.g., a building floor plan] into 3-D
	    geometry [e.g., walls]), the .mgedrc file (which can create customized
	    shortcuts for many MGED operations), the Build Pattern tool (which can
	    automatically replicate objects in a specified pattern), and the
	    build_region command (which can automatically build regions by grouping
	    together similarly named objects).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <table xml:id="mgedcolors"><info><title>Traditionally used MGED colors.</title></info>
	
	<tgroup cols="2" align="center">
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Color
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		RGB Value
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Aquamarine
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		112 219 147
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium aquamarine
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 204 153
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Black
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 0 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Cadet blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		95 159 159
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Corn flower blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		66 66 111
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark slate blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		107 35 142
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Light blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		191 216 216
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Light steel blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		143 143 188
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 50 204
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium slate blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		127 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Midnight blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		47 47 79
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Navy blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		35 35 142
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Sky blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 153 204
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Slate blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 127 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Steel blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		35 107 142
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Coral
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 127 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Cyan
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 255 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Firebrick
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		142 35 35
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Gold
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		204 127 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Goldenrod
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		219 219 112
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium goldenrod
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		234 234 173
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 255 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		47 79 47
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark olive green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		79 79 47
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Forest green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		35 142 35
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Lime green	
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 204 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium forest green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		107 142 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium sea green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		66 111 66
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium spring green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		127 255 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Pale green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		143 188 143
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Sea green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		35 142 107
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Spring green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 255 127
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Yellow green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		153 204 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark slate gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		47 79 79
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dim gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		84 84 84
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Light gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		168 168 168
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Khaki
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		159 159 95
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Magenta
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Maroon
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		142 35 107
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Orange
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		204 50 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Orchid
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		219 112 219
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark orchid
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		153 50 204
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium orchid
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		147 112 219
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Pink
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		188 143 143
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Plum
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		234 173 234
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 0 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Indian red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		79 47 47
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium violet
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		219 112 147
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Orange red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 0 127
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Violet red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		204 50 153
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Salmon
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		111 66 66
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Sienna
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		142 107 35
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Tan
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		219 147 112
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Thistle
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		216 191 216
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Turquoise
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		173 234 234
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Dark turquoise
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		112 147 219
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Medium turquoise
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		112 219 219
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Violet
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		79 47 79
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Blue violet
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		159 95 159
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Wheat
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		216 216 191
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		White
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 255 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Yellow
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 255 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Green yellow
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		147 219 112
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <table xml:id="system-color-codes"><info><title>Commonly used system-color codes.</title></info>
	
	<tgroup cols="3" align="center">
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		System
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Color
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		RGB Value
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Crew/passenger
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Tan
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		200 150 100
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Exterior armor<footnote xml:id="armygreenrecommended"><para>Army green (RGB 42 98 48) is recommended for white backgrounds (e.g., printouts).</para></footnote>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		80 80 80
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Fuel system
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Yellow
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 255 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Armament (not ammunition)<footnoteref linkend="armygreenrecommended"/>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		80 80 80
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Propellant
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Magenta
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Projectiles
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 0 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Engine/propulsion<footnoteref linkend="armygreenrecommended"/>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Oil Lines/hoses
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Light brown
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		159 159 95
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Coolant lines/hoses
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 255 0
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Air lines/hoses
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 0 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Drivetrain
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Cyan
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		0 255 255
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Driver/flight controls<footnoteref linkend="armygreenrecommended"/>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Dark blue
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 0 175
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Suspension/rotor blades<footnoteref linkend="armygreenrecommended"/>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		80 80 80
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Tracks
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Dark brown
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		104 56 30
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Tires/roadwheel rubber<footnote><para>Black (RGB 0 0 0) is recommended for white backgrounds (e.g., printouts).</para></footnote>
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Gray
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		80 80 80
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Electrical
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Forest green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 145 20
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Hydraulics
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Pink
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		255 145 145
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Communications/mission equipment package
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Lime green
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		50 204 50
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Fire control
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Peach
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		234 100 30
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>
		Fire suppression
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		Dark red
	      </entry>
	      <entry>
		79 47 47
	      </entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <note><info><title>
	  A Final Word About Modeling Ease vs. Modeling Precision 
	</title></info>
	
        <para>                                                                   
	  Modelers can be tempted to use the "quickest" methods of creating and 
	  aligning objects (e.g., using mouse clicks to size objects and the    
	  shift/control grips and "eyeballing" to position them).               
	</para>
	<para>
	  However, using precision MGED tools (e.g., the analyze and extrude    
	  commands, the snap-to-grid feature, etc.), listing primitives, making 
	  temporary assemblies, etc., is often more efficient. In addition, as  
	  the user becomes more familiar with these tools and features, they    
	  become easier to use. For more information on these specific          
	  features, see the appropriate on-line help in MGED.  
	</para>
      </note>

  </chapter>

  <chapter><info><title>Evaluating Geometry</title></info>
    
    <para>
      Evaluating geometry for correctness is an important companion to building
      real-world models. In fact, without testing the validity of the geometry's
      positioning and composition, the modeling process has not actually been
      completed. Evaluation is performed at the following two times in the
      modeling process: (1) after individual objects are built and organized
      into regions and combinations, and (2) after the model is completely
      built. In both cases, the primary evaluation goal is to identify any
      errors in measurement, logic, or input that would make the model invalid
      or unrealistic.
    </para>
    <para>
      One common error that the evaluation process reveals is overlapping
      geometry. Overlaps are the physical violation that occurs when two or more
      objects (regions) occupy the same volume in space. While this condition is
      occasionally acceptable (e.g., when modeling air volumes), it creates
      inaccuracies when the geometry is later analyzed.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	Because all of the volume within a region is considered to be one     
	material, it is acceptable for primitives within a region to          
	"overlap" without error (e.g., spheres rounding cylinder ends).       
	However, it is good modeling practice to minimize this wherever       
	practical to simplify Boolean logic and keep primitives as compact as 
	possible.
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      Shotlining is the principal method of interrogation in BRL-CAD. Rays are
      fired through geometry to report information about material properties,
      thickness, orientation, etc., of objects encountered along each ray's path
      (see Figure 18).
    </para>

    <figure><info><title>Shotline through a tank.</title></info>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig18.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      There are several ways to evaluate BRL-CAD geometry. These include
      (1) rendering the image using rt, (2) checking for overlaps using rtcheck
      (or the lesser-known/used g_lint or MGED's overlap tool), and (3) checking
      for faulty material composition (e.g., densities) using rtweight.
    </para>
    <para>
      Generally, as soon as a region is completed, it is good practice to
      raytrace it using rt. This allows the user to visually verify that all
      Boolean logic is correct and that the geometry has no obvious problems. If
      there is anything questionable, it can then be examined more closely with
      a raytrace that highlights that particular area. Note that rendering is
      also a good way to compare geometry with drawings, sketches, photographs,
      or images from other CAD systems.
    </para>
    <para>
      As subcomponents are organized into assemblies and the complexity of the
      geometry increases, it is then a good practice to use rtcheck (or g_lint
      or the overlap tool) to help find any errors in the geometry and isolate
      any problems.
    </para>
    <para>
      The rtcheck feature  is a program run from the MGED command line or shell
      command line that fires a grid of rays through a list of objects in order
      to check for overlapping geometry. It reports a total count of the
      overlaps and a list of overlap pairs, a listing of the paths to the
      regions, the number of overlaps between each pair, and the maximum depth
      in millimeters. This is followed by a summary of the total number of
      overlaps, the number of unique overlapping region pairs, and a listing of
      all overlapping regions.
    </para>
    <para>
      When run from within MGED, overlaps are displayed in the graphics display
      as yellow lines (see Figure 19). These yellow lines are created as
      temporary database objects and are stored in a combination called
      OVERLAPSffff00 ("ffff00" is hexadecimal notation for yellow [255 255 0]).
      Note that these temporary objects cannot be edited or saved and last only
      as long as they are not erased from the MGED display or are not
      overwritten by another set of overlaps.
    </para>
    <para>
      After these lines have been created in the display, the user may use them
      as a visual reference to analyze the overlaps. A good practice is to erase
      geometry (e.g., the top-level item) and draw smaller subcomponents
      (perhaps just a few of the overlapping regions) to see more clearly where
      and what the problems are. When doing this, note that the zap (Z) and
      blast (B) commands should not be used until the evaluator is finished with
      the yellow lines as a visual reference. The user should also keep in mind
      that the rays are difficult to see from the azimuth/elevation orientation
      from which they were shot. To see them clearly, one should change the
      azimuth/elevation to another orientation.
    </para>
    <para>
      To get the output shown in Figure 20, the "all" assembly was displayed in
      the graphics window and "rtcheck" was typed in the command window.
    </para>
    <para>
      This command could also be run from outside of MGED. The command "rtcheck"
      is typed at a shell prompt, followed by the file name and the list of
      objects to be evaluated (in this case, "all"). Note that when running
      rtcheck from outside MGED, the default parameters include a top view and a
      grid size of 512 × 512 cells (which is the default size for all rt
      operations). For more details, see the on-line man page on rt.
    </para>

    <figure><info><title>Example of overlaps in the graphics window.</title></info>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig19.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <note>
      <para>
	When first checking larger assemblies, it is wise to use a relatively 
	low-resolution rtcheck grid size--say, 128 × 128 pixels. Often,      
	there are simple errors that produce large numbers of overlaps, and   
	reporting them all takes a long time. Starting with low resolution,   
	however, allows the user to quickly find and eliminate gross errors   
	and proceed to the insidious small overlaps using a tighter grid and  
	more specific view parameters.   
      </para>
    </note>

    <figure><info><title>Example of an overlap report in the command window.</title></info>
      
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata align="center" fileref="../../books/en/images/tutorial_series_volIII_fig20.png" format="PNG"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Another tool that can be useful for evaluating geometry, especially target
      descriptions, is rtweight. During or after model development, material
      codes and effective percentages can be assigned to the appropriate
      regions/ combinations based on the known materials and weights of actual
      components, subsystems, and systems. The rtweight feature can then be used
      to calculate volume and material densities and provide the overall weight
      of the model. This information can, in turn, be compared with the weight
      of the actual object to see if the two match. If they do not, chances are
      that there is a problem in the model's material property assignments or
      construction (e.g., a hollow component was modeled as solid). For a list
      of standard material codes and air codes and their associated densities,
      see Robertson et al. (1996) and Winner et al. (2002).
    </para>

    <para>
      In addition, the following are some general tips regarding the evaluation
   of geometry in BRL-CAD:
    </para>

     <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Evaluate early and often:</emphasis> As mentioned previously, evaluations should
	    be performed both on individual objects as they are built and on sections
	    of the model as they are assembled. In general, problems identified early
	    are more easily isolated and fixed than if "buried" in a host of other
	    problems. Early and continuous evaluation also reduces the amount of
	    evaluation that needs to be done at the end. Final evaluation at the end
	    helps ensure that the individual pieces are all working together in the
	    model.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Evaluate at low resolution before high resolution:</emphasis> Especially in large
	    and complex models, running rtcheck at high resolution can be computation-
	    and time-intensive. Therefore, it is recommended that the modeler
	    initially set a lower number of rays to be fired, fix any significant
	    overlaps, and then increase the number of rays and/or zoom in on
	    particular areas as fewer overlaps are found.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Use multiple views:</emphasis> Because rtcheck finds overlaps by firing individual
	    rays at geometry, it can miss overlaps that occur between rays (e.g., when
	    viewing a face edge-on or with low obliquity). Therefore, to ensure the
	    highest evaluation accuracy possible, it is a good idea to use several of
	    BRL-CAD's standard views (e.g., top; az 35, el 25; etc.) as well as at
	    least one arbitrary or randomly selected view (e.g., az 72, el 23).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Set the proper eye point:</emphasis>  It is also possible for a user to miss
	    detecting overlaps when the eye point is set in the middle or front of an
	    object (e.g., when Z clipping is turned on). This does not mean that
	    rtcheck is not catching them; it just means that they are not being
	    displayed. So, before an evaluation is run, it is recommended that Z
	    clipping be turned off and the eye point be sufficiently offset from the
	    geometry so that the rays intersect the entire breadth of geometry or
	    portion of geometry the modeler wants to evaluate and display.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Chunk big problems into smaller problems:</emphasis> Experienced modelers in
	    BRL-CAD know that "killing" overlaps is simply a part of the modeling
	    process. However, dealing with large amounts of overlaps can be
	    overwhelming, especially to a new modeler or a modeler who has carefully
	    built each piece and expects rtcheck to find few, if any, problems.
	    Fortunately, in many cases, what appears to be extensive overlapping might
	    just be one section of geometry (e.g., a wall of buttons and switches)
	    that is slightly out of position, and a simple translation or rotation can
	    simultaneously fix many problems. In other cases, overlaps are the result
	    of simple miscalculations (e.g., a 2-in vs. a 1.5-in radius) that are not
	    likely to be noticed until positioned with surrounding geometry. Whatever
	    the case, the best approach to extensive overlaps is not to try to fix
	    them all at once but to divide the problem into smaller problems,
	    concentrate on individual pieces, and use the display to help identify and
	    fix errors. For example, rather than starting with "all," start with, say,
	    "engine," and then add "chassis." One can then continue this process and
	    work up to evaluating the entire model.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
  </chapter>

  <chapter><info><title>Logging Documentation</title></info>
    
 
    <para>
      The final step in the modeling process--documentation--is extremely
      important and can mean the difference between models that are useful for a
      week and models that are useful for years to come. Thorough, well-planned
      documentation is key to the user/analyst being able to effectively use
      what the modeler has spent many hours building. Sloppy or incomplete
      documentation, on the other hand, is like finishing up an otherwise
      well-built house with a bad paint job. It can serve to cover up all the
      good work the modeler has done and give the end user the false impression
      that bad documentation is an indicator of bad measurement, organization,
      development, and/or evaluation.
    </para>

    <para>
      Fortunately, when included in the planning process, good documentation is
      easy to produce. Once again, the way one sets up and produces
      documentation is highly dependent upon the purpose of the model. There are
      several questions the modeler (who now takes on the role of technical
      writer) must address to assist the end user(s):
    </para>

     <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Who will be using the model?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    What are the user(s) going to do with the model and why?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    What information can I give about the model that might save the user
	    some time or frustration?
	  </para>
	</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

     <para>
       Documentation can exist in several different forms. It can be a
       comprehensive chronological or topical summary of the project as a whole.
       It can be attribute tags (which are available in
       BRL-CAD 6.0 and later releases) about individual shapes and regions. Or it
       can be just some notes to help the user work with the model (e.g., to
       explain how to show articulation).
     </para>

     <para>
       Regardless of the type of setup, the following recommendations are made to
       achieve effective model documentation:
     </para>

     <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell what it's got and what it's not:</emphasis> It is useful to record not only
	    what components have been included in the model but also what
	    components/details have not been included (and why). This will remove
	    doubt as to what the end user does and does not have.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell the purpose of the model:</emphasis> Although the primary end user may know
	    exactly what the intended application of the model may be, the documenter
	    should consider the possibility of other users becoming involved during a
	    model's lifetime. Furthermore, these users may not know the model's
	    original purpose and may try to use the model in a way in which it was not
	    intended. The documentation should explain the choices the modeler made as
	    well as identify, if applicable, ways in which the model has been designed
	    for articulation and/or animation.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell when it was built:</emphasis> This information identifies the time period
	    during which the model was built. This information can be especially
	    important when modeling developmental items with continuously changing
	    design or model specifications. If a model undergoes a radical redesign
	    during any stage of the development process, the period of performance can
	    help identify why the model does or does not reflect given redesigned
	    components as well as identify when changes were implemented.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell from what sources it was built:</emphasis> It is important to note the type
	    of data sources from which the model dimensions were collected (i.e.,
	    field measurements, special tools, mechanical drawings, or converted
	    geometry). If a modeler physically measures an object, it is also
	    important to note any specific manufacturing information (e.g., make and
	    model, year of production, factory, etc.), any special designators or
	    insignias, and any damaged or missing items.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell how it was built:</emphasis> This information records the significant
	    techniques and configurations that were used to build the given geometry
	    as well as any irregular or specialized constructions (e.g., for
	    articulation, an intended ballistic impact scenario, etc.). Also included
	    here are basic tree structures and any naming conventions used.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Tell the level of detail to which it was built:</emphasis> This information
	    documents the specific tolerances and level of accuracy used to construct
	    the model, as well as ways in which accuracy was checked (e.g., rtcheck
	    and rtweight).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>

     <para>
       Documentation is often written at the end of the modeling project and
       published as a formal technical or summary report. Another good method is
       to document significant items as they are encountered throughout the
       modeling process. This practice records important information while it is
       fresh in the mind of the modeler as well as reduces the amount of writing
       required at the end of the project (when energy and/or interest levels may
       be low).
     </para>

     <para>
       Finally, it is a good idea to imbed the documentation (e.g., as a text
       file) directly into the database so that it always remains connected to
       the geometry it addresses. For example, the command
       <literallayout class="normal">
dbbinary -i u c documentation /home/fred/doc.txt
       </literallayout>
       will create a BRL-CAD binary object named documentation, and the object
       will contain the text from the file named /home/fred/doc.txt.
     </para>

  </chapter>

 
  <bibliography><info><title>References</title></info>
    
    
    <biblioentry xreflabel="dummyentry1">
      <authorgroup>
	<author><personname><firstname>John</firstname><surname>Smith</surname></personname></author>
      </authorgroup>
      <copyright><year>1988</year>
      </copyright>
      :<publisher>
	<publishername>Somebody</publishername>
      </publisher>
      <citetitle>Placeholder until xincludes from bibliography file are set up</citetitle>
      <subtitle>sometitle</subtitle>
      <pagenums>000-999</pagenums>
    </biblioentry>


  </bibliography>


  <appendix label="A"><info><title>Using the Pipe Primitive</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/pipes.xml" xpointer="pipe_general_use"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/pipes.xml" xpointer="pipe_make_coil"/>

  </appendix>

  <appendix label="B"><info><title>Using the Projection Shader</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_general"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_getimage"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_resize"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_actframe"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_dispimage"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_overlayimage"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_savesettingsfile"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_applysettingsfile"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_render"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/projection_shader.xml" xpointer="projshader_projectfront"/>
  </appendix>
    
  <appendix label="C"><info><title>Using the Extruded Bitmap Primitive</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm1"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm2"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm3"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm4"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm5"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm6"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm7"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm8"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/ebm_primitive.xml" xpointer="ebm9"/>
  </appendix>

  <appendix label="D"><info><title>Setting Up a .mgedrc File</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc1"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc2"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc3"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc4"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc5"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc6"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc7"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc8"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc9"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc10"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc11"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc12"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc13"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc14"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc15"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/mgedrc.xml" xpointer="mgedrc16"/>
  </appendix>

  <appendix label="E"><info><title>Using the Build Pattern Tool</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_generalinfo"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_names"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_fields"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_stringsub"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_recpatterns"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_spherical"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_pattern.xml" xpointer="build_pattern_cylind"/>
  </appendix>

  <appendix label="F"><info><title>Using the build_region Command</title></info>
    
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region1"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region2"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region3"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region4"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region5"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region6"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region7"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region8"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region9"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region10"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region11"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region12"/>
    <xi:include href="../../articles/en/build_region.xml" xpointer="build_region13"/>
  </appendix>

</book>
