<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>The Overlap Tool</title>
  </info>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The overlap tool is an MGED GUI intended to make it easier to
      visualize and resolve overlaps between regions.
    </para>

    <para>
      The biggest assumption made by the overlap tool is that all matrices
      in the database are identity (e.g. they've been pushed using the <command>xpush</command> command).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Command Usage</title>
    <section>
      <title>Basic Steps to Launch the Overlaps Tool GUI</title>
      <para>
	In the mged command window:
	<screen>
mged&gt; overlaps_tool -F [.overlaps file]
	</screen>
	</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Invocation Details</title>
      <para>
	Running just <command>overlaps_tool</command> with no arguments launches the overlaps menu GUI.
      </para>

      <para>
	You can give the path of the <filename>.overlaps</filename> file as an argument if the
	database is in a different directory than the <filename>.ck</filename> results
	directory is in, or if you rename the database file after
	generating th results directory. This will cause the checker tool to get launched directly.
      </para>

      <para>
	The <literal>-F</literal> option tells the tool it's okay to make assumptions about
	overlaps when doing subtractions (see <xref linkend="subtraction_assumptions"/>).
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Overlaps Menu GUI</title>
      <para>
	The overlaps menu has two sections -- New File and Exisiting File.
      </para>
      <para>
	<screenshot>
	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject role="html">
	      <imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig01.gif" format="GIF" width="540"/>
	    </imageobject>
	    <imageobject role="fo">
	      <imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig01.gif" format="GIF" width="540"/>
	    </imageobject>
	  </mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
      </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>New File</title>
      <section>
	<title>Create New Overlaps File</title>
	<para>
	  The Overlap File Tool is launched, which is used to create new overlaps file.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <screenshot>
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject role="html">
		<imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig02.gif" format="GIF" width="636"/>
	      </imageobject>
	      <imageobject role="fo">
		<imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig02.gif" format="GIF" width="636"/>
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </screenshot>
	</para>
	<para>
	  A tree of objects in the database is listed on the left hand side. Pressing the folder icon reveals the
	  regions inside the objects. Double clicking on the items selects/deselects them.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The selected items are listed on the right hand side. Double clicking on the listed items deselects it.
	</para>

	<para>
	  There is also an option to manually type in the objects name to select/deselect them with add/remove buttons.
	  The text entry also supports wildcards like * ? for batch operations.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Clicking on <emphasis role="bold">check for overlaps</emphasis> button, the tool runs
	  <command>check overlaps</command> at grid-size of 1024 from 16 different views
	  (45 degree steps in az and el directions) and then runs <command>check overlaps -g1mm,1mm</command>,
	  which runs it for three views at 1mm grid spacing.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The tool produces an output directory in the current directory (i.e. not the model directory unless it's the same)
	  named <filename>&lt;model.g&gt;.ck</filename>.
	</para>

	<warning><para>
	  Running <command>check overlaps</command> command can take many hours for non-trivial
	  geometry.
	</para></warning>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Exisiting File</title>
      <para>
	These options are to launch the checker tool directly for a previously created overlaps file.
      </para>
      <section>
	<title>Use Last File</title>
	<para>
	  This option is activated when there is already a output directory named <filename>&lt;model.g&gt;.ck</filename>
	  from previous run of the overlaps_tool in the current directory.
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Browse Overlaps File</title>
	<para>
	  This option can be used when we want to browse an overlaps file from any location.
	  If the overlaps file was not made from the currently opened database then it may show a warning and not open the overlaps file.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section> <!-- command usage -->

  <section>
    <title>Using the geometry checker GUI</title>
    <para>
      <screenshot>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject role="html">
	    <imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig03.png" format="PNG" width="549"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <imageobject role="fo">
	    <imagedata align="left" fileref="../articles/images/overlap_tool_fig03.png" format="PNG" width="549"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Bounding-Box Volume Calculation</title>
      <para>
	When the geometry checker is run, the first thing that happens is
	the volume of the axis-aligned bounding box for each overlapping
	object is calculated. This can take several minutes depending on
	the size of the overlaps file.
      </para>

      <para>
	When this finishes, the GUI window will populate.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The Overlap List</title>
      <para>
	The main element of the GUI is the overlap list, which consists
	of four columns. The first column on the left is just a reference
	number for the overlap.
      </para>

      <para>
	The second and third columns are the paths of the overlapping
	regions. <emphasis role="bold">The region with the smaller bounding-box volume is
	always listed first</emphasis>, as the "Left" side of the overlapping pair.
      </para>

      <para>
	The rightmost column is an estimate of the overlapping volume in
	mm<superscript>3</superscript>. This is not a separately calculated value, but rather an
	estimate derived from the overlap data. It's not particularly
	accurate for any given overlap pair, but the relative
	relationship of the estimates is fairly accurate, so pairs with a
	higher volume estimate generally have a larger overlap volume
	than pairs with a lower volume estimate.
      </para>

      <para>
	By default, the overlap list is sorted by highest volume estimate
	first, but you can click any of the headers to sort
	ascending/descending by overlap number, left or right path name,
	or volume estimate.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Drawing Overlap Paths</title>
      <para>
	Clicking on an overlap will cause the left and right paths to be
	drawn as wireframes in the display window. The wireframes are
	colored red and blue respectively (matching the subtraction
	buttons at the bottom of the window).
      </para>

      <para>
	Below the overlap list is an option to draw only the first
	unioned solid in the region instead of the whole region. It's
	enabled automatically when using the <literal>-F</literal> option, because it shows
	just the two objects the <literal>-F</literal> mode assumes to be responsible for
	the overlap. However, this display option can be toggled whether
	you're using <literal>-F</literal> or not.
      </para>

      <para>
	To navigate through overlaps you can:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Use the up/down keyboard keys to draw each overlap in turn.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Use the scroll bar on the right side of the overlap list to
	find a specific overlap.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Use the Home and End keyboard keys to scroll all the way to the
	top or bottom of the list.
	</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


      <para>
	If you shift-select multiple paths, all those paths are
	drawn. For large regions, it can take a while for all paths to be
	drawn. There's a progress bar below the overlap list that shows
	how many of the selected paths have been drawn. The specific
	region being drawn appears above the progress bar.
      </para>

      <para>
	The "X" button to the right of the progress bar can be pressed at
	any time during drawing to stop any more regions from being
	drawn. On a shift-select, there's a short pause (about three
	seconds) before any drawing begins so you can hit the X button
	and prevent anything from being drawn at all.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Marking Overlaps</title>
      <para>
	You can right-click on selected overlaps and chose "Mark
	Selected" or "Unmark Selected" to indicate which overlap pairs
	you have reviewed or attempted a fix on.
      </para>

      <para>
	Marked overlaps are grayed out and moved to the bottom of the
	overlap list. The marked and unmarked sections independently
	maintain the current sorting of the overlap list.
      </para>

      <para>
	These markings are saved to the <filename>.ck</filename> directory, so they are
	maintained when you close and reopen MGED.
      </para>

    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Automatic Subtraction</title>
      <para>
	For each pair of overlapping objects, the overlap GUI can
	automatically rewrite the tree of one side of the pair to
	subtract the other side to attempt to resolve the overlap.
      </para>

      <para>
	Once you select one or more unmarked overlap pairs, the subtract
	buttons at the bottom of the window will enable and you can
	choose to subtract all the left-hand regions from the right-hand
	ones or vice versa.
      </para>

      <para>
	Each pair that's processed will be automatically marked in the
	overlap list.
      </para>

      <para>
	The progress bar and X button work the same for subtractions as
	for drawing.
      </para>
      <warning><para>Performing many subtractions at the
	same time can take a while and if MGED is killed for some reason
	(e.g. system restart), the overlap tool isn't guaranteed to
	handle that situation gracefully. It may corrupt the region it's
	currently re-writing or fail to mark a processed overlap pair.
      </para></warning>

      <para xml:id="subtraction_assumptions" xreflabel="subtraction assumptions">
	By default, the overlap GUI will refuse to
	subtract any combination that doesn't reduce to a single
	solid. That's because subtracting a non-trivial combination
	complicates the re-written tree, and can lead to cycles (a - b -
	a).
      </para>

      <para>
	Providing the <literal>-F</literal> ("first") option to the overlaps_tool command causes the
	overlap GUI to assume that the overlap between an overlapping
	pair only involves the first unioned solid in their respective
	trees. Subtracting a combination with the <literal>-F</literal> option enabled
	results in just the first unioned solid of that combination being
	subtracted from the first unioned solid in the other object's tree.
      </para>

      <para>
	For example, if <emphasis>a</emphasis> overlaps <emphasis>b</emphasis> and they look like this:
      </para>

      <screen>
a/R
  u <emphasis role="bold">adapter.s</emphasis>
  u alert.c
    u ac.s
  - ant.s

b/R
  u bottle.c
    u box.c
      u <emphasis role="bold">bend.s</emphasis>
  - blend.c
    u balance.s
      </screen>

      <para>
	Then subtracting <emphasis>b</emphasis> from <emphasis>a</emphasis> would rewrite <emphasis>a</emphasis> to:
      </para>

      <screen>
a/R
  u <emphasis role="bold">adapter.s</emphasis>
  - <emphasis role="bold">bend.s</emphasis>
  u alert.c
    u ac.s
  - ant.s
      </screen>
    </section> <!-- automatic subtraction -->
  </section> <!-- gui -->
</article>
