<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man+tkman by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='grab3'>

<!-- '\" Copyright (c) 1998\-2000 by Scriptics Corporation.
'\" All rights reserved.
'\" 
'\" RCS: @(#) $Id$
'\"  -->
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>Tk_Grab</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>Tk</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
<refname>Tk_Grab</refname>
<refname>Tk_Ungrab</refname>
<refpurpose>manipulate grab state in an application</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<funcsynopsis>
<funcsynopsisinfo>
#include &lt;tk.h&gt;

</funcsynopsisinfo>
<funcprototype>
<funcdef>int <function>Tk_Grab</function></funcdef>
<paramdef><parameter>interp</parameter></paramdef>
<paramdef><parameter>tkwin</parameter></paramdef>
<paramdef><parameter>grabGlobal</parameter></paramdef>
</funcprototype>
<funcprototype>
<funcdef>void <function>Tk_Ungrab</function></funcdef>
<paramdef><parameter>tkwin</parameter></paramdef>
</funcprototype>

</funcsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='arguments'><title>ARGUMENTS</title>
<para>Interpreter to use for error reporting</para>
<informaltable>
<tgroup cols='3'>
<tbody>

<row><entry>"Tk_Window"</entry><entry>"tkwin"</entry><entry>"in"</entry>
<entry>
<para>Window on whose behalf the pointer is to be grabbed or released</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row><entry>int</entry><entry>grabGlobal</entry><entry>in</entry>
<entry>
<para>Boolean indicating whether the grab is global or application local</para>
<!-- .BE -->
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>These functions are used to set or release a global or
application local grab.  When a grab is set on a particular window
in a Tk application, mouse and keyboard events can only be received by
that window and its descendants.  Mouse and keyboard events for
windows outside the tree rooted at <emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis> will be redirected to
<emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis>.  If the grab is global, then all mouse and keyboard
events for windows outside the tree rooted at <emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis> (even those
intended for windows in other applications) will be redirected to
<emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis>.  If the grab is application local, only mouse and
keyboard events intended for a windows within the same application
(but outside the tree rooted at <emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis>) will be redirected.</para>


<para><function>Tk_Grab</function> sets a grab on a particular window.  <emphasis remap='I'>Tkwin</emphasis>
specifies the window on whose behalf the pointer is to be grabbed.
<emphasis remap='I'>GrabGlobal</emphasis> indicates whether the grab should be global or
application local; if it is non-zero, it means the grab should be
global.  Normally, <function>Tk_Grab</function> returns <emphasis remap='B'>TCL_OK</emphasis>; if an error occurs
and the grab cannot be set, <emphasis remap='B'>TCL_ERROR</emphasis> is returned and an error message
is left if <emphasis remap='I'>interp</emphasis>'s result.  Once this call completes
successfully, no window outside the tree rooted at <emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis> will
receive pointer- or keyboard-related events until the next call to
Tk_Ungrab.  If a previous grab was in effect within the application,
then it is replaced with a new one.</para>


<para><emphasis remap='B'>Tcl_Ungrab</emphasis> releases a grab on the mouse pointer and keyboard, if
there is one set on the window given by <emphasis remap='I'>tkwin</emphasis>.  Once a grab is
released, pointer and keyboard events will start being delivered to
other windows again.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='keywords'><title>KEYWORDS</title>
<para>grab, window</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

