<article xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0'
  xmlns:xi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'
>
  <info><title>Standard (Core) Attributes List</title></info>
  <para xml:id='std_attr_info'>
    <variablelist remap='TP'>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>region:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The Region Flag identifies a particular geometric combination as being a solid material;in other words, any geometry below this combination in the tree can overlap without the overlap being regarded as a non-physical description, since it is the combination of all descriptions in the region object that define the physical volume in space.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>region_id:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The Region Identifier Number identifies a particular region with a unique number.This allows multiple region objects to be regarded as being the same type of region,without requiring that they be included in the same combination object.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>material_id:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The Material ID Number corresponds to an entry in a DENSITIES table, usually contained in a text file.  This table associates numbers with material names and density information used by analytical programs such as 'rtweight'.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>aircode:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>Any non-zero Air Code alerts the raytracer that the region in question is modeling air which is handled by specialized rules in LIBRT.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>shader:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>LIBRT can use a variety of shaders when rendering.  This attribute holds a text string which corresponds to the name and other details of the shader to be used.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
	      <term><emphasis remap='B' role='bold'>inherit:</emphasis></term>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>The Inherit Properties value, if true, indicate all child objects inherit the attributes of this parent object.</para>
	      </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </para>
</article>
