<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="bot_flip">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>BOT_EXTRUDE</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv xml:id="name">
    <refname>bot_extrude</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Generate a volumetric BoT to explicitly represent the volume claimed by plate mode BoT.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>bot extrude</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-h</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-q</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-i</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-R</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-C</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>-F</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"> <replaceable>input_bot</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"> <replaceable>output_bot</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection xml:id="description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

  <para>
    Given a BoT solid using "plate" mode to implicitly define a volume, generate
    an explicit volumentric BoT to approximately represent the same volume.  The
    default mode is to produce a BoT, but if the user prefers a CSG tree of
    implicit shapes that output can be generated with <option>-C</option>.  (Usually
    the resulting tree is quite large, since it uses one primitive for every mesh
    element, and typically <option>-C</option> is recommended only for debugging.)
    Note that the volumetric representation produces will typically not be an
    <emphasis>exact</emphasis> match to the original plate mode volume - cylinders
    are used to "fill in" mesh edges and this can produce small artifacts at outer
    vertex points.  Typically, especially with small thickness values for plates,
    these artifacts are not significant - the "cylinders" themselves are also facetized
    approximations of the "thickness volume" claimed by edges.  Just as spheres are
    approximated by a triangle mesh when facetized, a plate mode's "volume" is approximated
    when extruded.
  </para>

  <para>
    In order to avoid being destructive, the output produced must normally be
    written out to a different object name than that of the input BoT.  However,
    if the user wishes to replace a large number of plate mode BoTs in a CSG
    hierarchy, the <option>-i</option> option may be used to instruct the
    <command>bot extrude</command> command to replace the original input with
    the generated output.  This IS destructive, but also avoids the need to edit
    all of the comb entries referencing the original primitives.  Users should
    only perform a <option>-i</option> extrusion on an expendable copy of the original
    .g file until they are sure the result is satisfactory.
  </para>

  <para>
    By default outer edges of a plate mode BoT are not represented by cylinders.
    This is generally the intuitive expectation, but arguably the half cylinder
    at the outer edge could be considered volume claimed by the plate mode bot,
    depending on the incoming ray angle.  If the user DOES wish to "round" the
    outer edges of the conversion with cylinders, the <option>-R</option> option
    will apply those cylinders in the conversion process.
  </para>

  <para>
    The most problematic plate mode BoTs to represent as volumes are those with
    view dependent behavior - i.e., those with "face_mode" set.  In the strict
    sense such objects do not claim a well defined volume in space - in/out hit points
    and partitions will change for the same intersecting line segment depending on
    what direction the ray is coming from.  By default <command>bot extrude</command>
    will warn and exit when encountering such volumes, but if the user is willing
    to accept the differences between the original and a volumetric approximation they
    may instruct <command>bot extrude</command> to proceed with the <option>-F</option>
    option.
  </para>
  
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="dbconcat_options"><title>OPTIONS</title>

  <variablelist remap="TP">
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-h|--help</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Print help and exit.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-q|--quiet</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Suppress messages reporting the status of the generation process.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-i|--in-place</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Replace the input BoT with the generated volumetric output. (Destructive.)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-R|--round-edges</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Represent outer edges of plate mode BoT with cylinderical approximations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-C|--comb</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Return a CSG tree of implicit shapes rather than an evaluated BoT.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-F|--force</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Produce a volumetric BoT output even if the input BoT's parameters indicate it is a view dependent solid.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="examples"><title>EXAMPLES</title>

    <para>
      Generate a volumetric BoT from a plate mode BoT (standard case.)
    </para>
    <example><title>Basic example.</title>

      <para><prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>bot extrude input.bot output.bot</userinput></para>
      <para>
        Represents all triangle elements in input.bot with CSG implicits, approximates them with
	triangles, and unions them together to produce output.bot.
      </para>
    </example>

    <para>
      For a more advanced use, we combine <command>bot extrude</command> with <command>search -exec</command>
      to batch convert a large number of plate mode BoTs.
    </para>
    <example><title>Batch conversion of plate mode BoTs.</title>

      <para><prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>search -type bot -type plate -exec "bot extrude -F --in-place {}" ";"</userinput></para>
      <para>
        Uses the <option>--in-place</option> to replace plate mode BoTs in the .g file with their
	volumetric approximations. The <option>-F</option> option instructs <command>bot extrude</command>
	to proceed even if the BoT is view dependent.
      </para>
    </example>

  </refsection>
  
  <refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title>
    <para>BRL-CAD Team</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>

    <para>
      Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
      mail to <email>devs@brlcad.org</email>
    </para>
  </refsection>
</refentry>
