<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="facetize">

	<refmeta>
		<refentrytitle>FACETIZE</refentrytitle>
		<manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
		<refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
		<refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
	</refmeta>

	<refnamediv xml:id="name">
		<refname>facetize</refname>
		<refpurpose>
			Creates <emphasis>new_object</emphasis> using <emphasis>old_object</emphasis> as a
			guide, creating an evaluated NMG or BoT planar approximation of the original shape.
		</refpurpose>
	</refnamediv>

	<!-- body begins here -->
	<refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
		<cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
			<command>facetize</command>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-h</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-v</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-q</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-n</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-r</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-s suffix</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-p prefix</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--in-place</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--max-time #</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--max-pnts #</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--resume</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--methods m1,m2,...</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--method-opts METHOD opt1=val opt2=val...</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--no-empty</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--log-file filename</arg>
			<arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--disable-fixup</arg>
			<arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>old_object new_object</replaceable></arg>
		</cmdsynopsis>
	</refsynopsisdiv>

	<refsection xml:id="description">
		<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
		<para>
			The <emphasis>facetize</emphasis> operation in BRL-CAD is, broadly speaking,
			the processing of creating an explicit planar approximation of a CSG volume
			by evaluating the boolean expressions used to combine a set of explicit and
			implicit solid primitives.  It is the core operation necessary for creating triangle
			based meshes from BRL-CAD geometry.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <command>facetize</command> command can attempt to produce either triangle-only
			BoT objects, or N-Manifold Geometry (NMG) objects, but generally speaking BoT
			generation will have a higher success rate than NMG.  BoTs are also more useful when
			exporting to formats such as STL and OBJ - by default BoT output is what
			<command>facetize</command> will produce.
		</para>
		<para>
			In general Boolean evaluation of meshes is a very difficult problem, and there
      are also some specific considerations when it comes to preparing geometry
			for solid shotline raytracing that require more effort than producing a
			visualization mesh.  It is recommended to use the <command>lint</command> command, both
			to verify input objects are well behaved before facetization and to check <command>facetize</command>
			outputs for any potential issues.  Often times either the original CSG geometry
			definitions will need adjustment to avoid coplanar faces, or mesh editing is required
			to resolve problematic triangle configurations.
		</para>
		<para>
			By default all specified existing objects will be combined into a single mesh, but
			that is often undesirable when working within BRL-CAD - information stored on region
			combs such as color will be lost when converting in this fashion.  The
			<option>-r</option>	option will introspect into the specified objects and perform
			facetization on a per-region basis.  (If the specified input has no regions in its
			tree, a normal facetization to a single object is performed instead.)	The output
			will be a new hierarchy that references the facetized regions but retains the
			properties of parent regions.  Users looking to interact	visually with a shaded
			display of a model will likely find the <option>-r</option>	output useful for that
			purpose.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are a number of different verbosity levels available for the facetize command.
			One or multiple specifications of the <option>-v</option> flag will increase
			reporting detail.  Because full output from facetize can be quite verbose, the
			user has the option to specify a log file with the <option>--log-file</option>
			option - this will capture <emphasis>all</emphasis> output from the command and
			allow for more detailed scrutiny of what took place after a conversion has finished.
		</para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="facetize_output_modes">
		<title>Output Characteristics and Processing Controls</title>
		<para>
			By default the <command>facetize</command> command attempts to be non-destructive when operating on
			objects - it will not rename or replace any existing geometry in normal operational modes, and will
			adjust its naming accordingly when producing new objects.  However,
			if a user <emphasis>wants</emphasis> to replace objects with facetized replacements, this may be accomplished by specifying the
			<option>--in-place</option> option.  Note that this is a destructive operation - the original
			object definitions will be overwritten - so use with care!
		</para>
		<para>
			Users may be a bit startled to see empty (0 face, 0 vertices) BoTs produced by a facetize
      command, but this is in fact expected behavior when a boolean option
			legitimately results in an empty mesh.  For example, if a sphere in a comb is subtracted from
			itself, and no other geometry is referenced, the result is a zero (empty) volume.  The <command>lint</command>
			command can be used to identify such BoTs - if they <emphasis>are</emphasis> produced, it is
			often an indication the original CSG definition has some sort of problem.  These empty outputs
			can be suppressed by specifying the <option>--no-empty</option> option, but the recommended
			course is to determine what about the original geometry produced them and either correct any issues
			or (if the shapes truly are not intended to be present) remove the original CSG definitions producing them.
		</para>
		<para>
			It may happen that a conversion fails part way through the process.   This can
			happen due to user intervention, resource exhaustion, or simply as a consequence of
			a bug in the conversion logic.  If this happens, the intermediate state of the
			conversion will be stored by BRL-CAD in its cache directory, and the interrupted
			process may be resumed by re-running <command>facetize</command> with the
			<option>--resume</option> option.  (If a conversion fails and the command is re-run
			without specifying <option>--resume</option>, previous work will be cleared and the
			process will start over from the beginning.
		</para>
		<para>
			In normal operation, when converting to BoT output there are post-processing routines that try
			to identify and automatically fix certain categories of geometric flaws that can crop up during
			Boolean evaluation.  If a user finds that they are getting unexpected output for a particular
			input, and the log indicates the repair step was run, one option available is to repeat the
			conversion with these repair steps disabled via the <option>--disable-fixup</option>
			flag.  Repair should only be disabled if there is a problem - coplanar subtractions frequently result
			in thin triangle artifacts lingering after Boolean evaluation due to the imitations of floating
			point math, and in at least some cases the fixup routines are able to deal with these without
			requiring manual intervention.  (These routines will not <emphasis>always</emphasis> work, so
			checking of outputs after a conversion with the <command>lint</command> command to identify BoTs
			with potentially problematic features is still recommended - see the <command>lint</command>
			man page for more details.)
		</para>
		<para>
			Different tolerance settings will create finer or coarser meshes. See the <command>tol</command> man
			page for more details.
		</para>
	</refsection>


	<refsection xml:id="facetize_options"><title>Options</title>

		<variablelist remap="TP">

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-h, --help</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Print help and exit.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-v[v..], --verbose</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Prints extra (verbose) information in results.  May be overridden by
						the <option>--quiet</option> flag.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-q, --quiet</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Suppress all output (overrides verbosity flag.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold"></emphasis>-n, --nmg-output</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Instructs <command>facetize</command> to produce NMG solids rather than BoT
						solids.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-r, --regions</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Rather than converting all specified inputs to one top level object, walk
						specified trees and individually convert regions to facetized objects.  This
						mode is useful when wanting to display models in shaded mode while preserving
						color and region ID properties.  If no regions are present a normal conversion
						is performed instead.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-s, --suffix</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						User specified suffix to use avoiding naming conflicts (naming conflict
						avoidance is needed needed when creating objects in <option>-r</option> mode.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-p, --prefix</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						User specified prefix to use avoiding naming conflicts (naming conflict
						avoidance is needed needed when creating objects in <option>-r</option> mode.)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--in-place</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Replace the specified object(s) with their facetizations. (WARNING: this
						option is destructive and will change pre-existing geometry!)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--max-time #</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Maximum time to spend per object (in seconds).  Default is method specific.
						Note that specifying shorter times may cut off conversions (particularly using
						sampling methods) that could succeed with longer runtimes.  Per-method time
						limits can also be adjusted to allow longer runtimes on slower methods.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--max-pnts #</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Maximum number of pnts per object to use when applying ray sampling methods.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--resume</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Resume an incomplete facetization process (will utilize cached data from a
						previous run rather than starting from scratch.)  Re-running without this
						option will clear any old data and start from the beginning.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--methods</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Accepts a comma separated list of one or more facetization methods to use.
						The default is to try all algorithims available as needed, but if a user
						knows they want to try a specific methodology they can call it out using
						this option.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--method-opts</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This option can be used to pass parameter values to specific facetize
						methods.  The argument format is "METHOD opt1=val1 opt2=val2 ...".
						See the <option>--help</option> output for which methods and parameters
						are supported by <command>facetize</command>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--no-empty</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Do not write out empty BoT objects when a Boolean evaluation results
						in an empty mesh.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--log-file</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Specify a log file in which to store the full verbose output of a facetization
						process.  This is recommended for large or long running facetize runs to allow
						users to better understand what steps were taken and what problems might have
						arisen.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">--disable-fixup</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						By default, BoT facetization will attempt to clear certain categories of
						undesirable triangles from outputs.  Specifying this option will skip that
						repair attempt.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="methods">
		<title>Facetization Methods</title>
		<para>
			In broad, there are two stages to a facetization process.  The first stage is the generation of
			mesh representations for individual geometric primitives - implicit ELL, ARB8, TOR, etc. solids
			must be represented by mesh approximations before they can become part of an evaluated mesh.
			Additionally, inputs that are already meshes are checked for suitability - all input meshes, whether
			generated from implicit shapes or pre-existing as BoTs, must be properly manifold before they can
			be used for facetization.  Once all solids have been successfully converted, the next step is to
			evaluate the Boolean tree hierarchy by unioning, subtracting or intersecting the various meshes
			together to produce the evaluated shapes.
		</para>
		<para>
			The process of individual primitive to mesh conversion can sometimes be problematic - routines
			may take extremely long lengths of time trying to resolve a conversion problem.  In order to
			avoid the process hanging indefinitely with no progress, a timeout is established that limits
			how long each individual conversion process should take.  Various methods have defaults defined
			internally, so this isn't something the user normally needs to concern themselves with, but if
			they wish to set a limit themselves (either allowing more time or forcing shorter cycles) they
			can do so with the <option>--max-time</option> option.
		</para>
		<para>
			It can be difficult to produce a mesh from a primitive shape. Simply waiting longer for results
			often isn't practical or even the right answer - indeed, infinite looping has been observed in
			some primitive conversion cases. To work around these limitations, BRL-CAD provides multiple
			methods that can be used to attempt mesh production in case other methods fail.  We
			deliberately do not document those methods in detail here - they are subject to change as new
			alternatives are identified that can produce better results.  What we <emphasis>do</emphasis> document is how to
			use the facetize command to see what methods are currently available and control them.  The <option>-h</option>
			option will list, at the end of its output, information about all currently available methods and
			what controls they offer.  The facetize option <option>--methods</option> can be used to restrict
			the facetize command to a particular subset of the available methodologies, and the
			<option>--method-opts</option> option is used to pass specific parameters to a specific
			method.
		</para>
		<para>
			Because many of the facetization methods are sampling based (the raytracer is used to sample the
			volume) a top level control is available to specify the maximum number of points to use when
			generating inputs for such methods.  (More points generally means a better conversion at the
			expense of memory and runtime.)
		</para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="examples">
		<title>EXAMPLES</title>

		<example>
			<title>Create a facetized BOT version of an existing object.</title>
			<para>
				The example shows the use of the <command>facetize</command> command to create a facetized
				BOT version of an existing object (<emphasis>old_object</emphasis>) and renaming that facetized
				object (<emphasis>new_object</emphasis>).
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize region1.r region1.bot</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Facetize all regions in a hierarchy.</title>
			<para>
				This runs the per region conversion on all regions under the "model" assembly and creates
				a new conversion hierarchy under model_facetized.
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize -r model model.f</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Facetize all regions in a hierarchy, attempting only NMG conversion.</title>
			<para>
				This runs the NMG approach per region conversion on all regions, but in
				the case of failure will not attempt any fallback conversion methods.
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize -r --methods NMG model model.f</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Retry failed conversion objects in a previous facetization attempt with new methodology.</title>
			<para>
				This resumes a failed conversion of <emphasis>model</emphasis>.
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize -r --resume model model.f</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>


		<example>
			<title>Increase Decimation in CM Mode</title>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize --methods CM --method-opts feature_size=0.06 d_feature_size=2.0 ellipse.r ell.bot</userinput>
			</para>
			<para>
				The default settings on this object in CM mode will produce a little over 8000 faces in the final bot, but the addition of the <option>d_feature_size</option> option with a >1.5 value has dramatically reduced the count to 104.
			</para>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Decrease Decimation in CM Mode</title>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize --methods CM --method-opts feature_size=0.06 d_feature_size=0.01 ellipse.r ell.bot</userinput>
			</para>
			<para>
				If the intent is preserve a more detailed mesh, reducing <option>decimation-feature-size</option> will keep more of the original triangles - in the above example, almost 250 thousand of the original 6.9 million faces were retained.  NOTE:  use lower values here cautiously, as extremely large meshes can be very difficult for many tools to deal with.
			</para>
		</example>

	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="util">
		<title>USEFUL TRICKS</title>
		<para>
			These are some useful commands related to the facetization process.
		</para>

		<example>
			<title>List invalid BoT objects below a comb</title>
			<para>
				Use lint -I to report on invalid objects below a comb.
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput> lint -I model.f</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>

		<example>
			<title>Pre-extrude Plate Mode BoTs</title>
			<para>
				Use search -exec to extrude all plate mode bots before attempting a facetize operation.
			</para>
			<para>
				<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput> search model.f -type bot -type plate -exec "bot extrude -i {}" ";"</userinput>
			</para>
		</example>

	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="implementation_notes">
		<title>Implementation Details</title>
		<para>
			The current implementation of <command>facetize</command> launches primitive facetization operations
			in a subprocess, to allow for recovery if individual primitives crash, infinite loop, or otherwise
			trigger what would otherwise be catastrophic behavior.  This means that it is essential the operating
			environment allow the parent program to launch those subprocesses - otherwise, conversion will fail.
		</para>
		<para>
			Unlike previous versions of <command>facetize</command>, this version (in BoT mode) will only facetize
			each primitive once - if a primitive is instanced repeatedly in multiple combs, it will use the same
			BoT to represent all of those instances.  If for some reason this is not desired behavior, the user
			should first prepare the geometry by making all instances unique with <command>xpush</command>.
		</para>
	</refsection>


	<refsection xml:id="author">
		<title>AUTHOR</title>
		<para>BRL-CAD Team</para>
	</refsection>

	<refsection xml:id="bug_reports">
		<title>BUG REPORTS</title>

		<para>
			Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
			mail to <email>devs@brlcad.org</email>
		</para>
	</refsection>

</refentry>
