<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="facetize">

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>FACETIZE</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv xml:id="name">
    <refname>facetize</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      Creates <emphasis>new_object</emphasis> using <emphasis>old_object</emphasis> as a
      guide, creating an evaluated NMG or BoT planar approximation of the original shape.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>facetize</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-h</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-v</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-q</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-r</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-n</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-T</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--NMG</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--CM</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--SPSR</arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>old_object new_object</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>facetize --CM</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--feature-scale</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--feature-size</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--decimation-feature-size</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--max-time</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--max-pnts</arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>old_object new_object</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>facetize --SPSR</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-d</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-w</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--samples-per-node</arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>old_object new_object</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>facetize -r</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">standard_options</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--resume</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--retry</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">--in-place</arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>output_hierarchy_obj</replaceable></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection xml:id="description">
    <title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      Creates <emphasis>new_object</emphasis> as planar primitive shape (either an NMG or a BOT)
      approximating the 3D volume bound by <emphasis>old_object</emphasis>.  The <emphasis>-r</emphasis>
      option will operate per-region rather than on an entire object and produces a new hierarchy.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are a number of different verbosity levels available for the facetize command.  One or mulitple specifications
      of the <emphasis>-v</emphasis> flag will increase reporting detail about what the facetize command is doing in various
      steps. To silence all output
      specify the <emphasis>-q</emphasis> flag - this is generally not recommended as the messages produced by the
      facetize command often contain important information about conversion failures in addition to reporting incremental
      progress on large conversion tasks.
    </para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="regions">
    <title>PER-REGION FACETIZATION AND PARTIAL CONVERSIONS</title>
    <para>
      Often, it is desirable to perform facetization on each region individually within a
      geometry hierarchy, rather than trying for a single "all or nothing" shape.  This mode, available
      with the <emphasis>-r</emphasis> flag, has the advantage of allowing for partial conversion of complex models even when
      individual shapes within the model cannot be converted, as well as preserving all pre-existing
      region attributes such as color and region ID.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because multi-region hierarchy conversion is often a long process, the facetize command (when run in region mode) works
      in a way that allows an incomplete conversion to resume work.  For example, if a large model is
      to be converted it may be advantageous to attempt just the NMG conversion on the hierarchy first
      to get a sense of the work to be done.  After the initial attempt, global facetize parameters can
      be adjusted and a second NMG run attempted, perhaps this time with SPSR reconstruction also enabled.
      Note that this works only for a hierarchy generated with the <command>facetize</command>.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default the <command>facetize</command> command attempts to be non-destructive when operating on
      objects - it will not rename or replace any existing geometry in normal operational modes.  However,
      if a user needs to create a new version of an existing hierarchy which replaces geometry below regions
      with BoT objects but leaves all upper level names intact, this may be accomplished by specifying the
      <emphasis>--in-place</emphasis> option in combination with the <emphasis>-r</emphasis> option.
    </para>
  </refsection>

    <refsection xml:id="examples">
    <title>EXAMPLES</title>

    <example>
      <title>Create a facetized BOT version of an existing object.</title>
      <para>
	The example shows the use of the <command>facetize</command> command to create a facetized
	BOT version of an existing object (<emphasis>old_object</emphasis>) and renaming that facetized
	object (<emphasis>new_object</emphasis>).  It will try first NMG conversion, and if that fails
	attempts CM conversion.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput>facetize region1.r region1.bot</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Facetize all regions in a hierarchy.</title>
      <para>
	This runs the per region conversion on all regions under the "model" assembly and creates
	a new conversion hierarchy under model_facetized.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput>facetize -r model model.f</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Facetize all regions in a hierarchy, attempting only NMG conversion.</title>
      <para>
	This runs the per region conversion on all regions, but in the case of failure will not attempt
	any fallback conversion methods.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput>facetize -r --NMG model model.f</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>Retry failed conversion objects in a previous facetization attempt with new methodology.</title>
      <para>
	This retries the per region conversion on all regions that didn't originally succeed in the initial
	conversion attempt, attempting only CM reconstruction without first retrying NMG conversion.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput>facetize -r --resume model.f</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

  
    <example>
      <title>Increase Decimation in CM Mode</title>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize --CM --feature-size 0.06 --decimation-feature-size 2.0 ellipse.r ell.bot</userinput>
	<literallayout class="normal">
CM: completed in 16 seconds with size 0.06
CM: completed in 23 seconds with size 0.054
CM: timed out after 30 seconds with size 0.0486
CM: successfully created 6960500 faces, feature size 0.054
CM: decimation succeeded, final BoT has 104 faces
	</literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>
	The default settings on this object in CM mode will produce a little over 8000 faces in the final bot, but the addition of the <option>decimation-feature-size</option> option with a >1.5 value has dramatically reduced the count to 104.
      </para>
    </example>
    
    <example>
      <title>Decrease Decimation in CM Mode</title>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt; </prompt><userinput>facetize --CM --feature-size 0.06 --decimation-feature-size .01 ellipse.r ell.bot</userinput>
	<literallayout class="normal">
CM: completed in 16 seconds with size 0.06
CM: completed in 23 seconds with size 0.054
CM: timed out after 30 seconds with size 0.0486
CM: successfully created 6960500 faces, feature size 0.054
CM: decimation succeeded, final BoT has 247642 faces
	</literallayout>
      </para>
      <para>
	If the intent is preserve a more detailed mesh, reducing <option>decimation-feature-size</option> will keep more of the original triangles - in the above example, almost 250 thousand of the original 6.9 million faces were retained.  NOTE:  use lower values here cautiously, as extremely large meshes can be very difficult for many tools to deal with.
      </para>
    </example>
        
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="methodology">
    <title>METHODOLOGY</title>
    <para>
      Ideally users would not need to concern themselves with the details of how <command>facetize</command>
      works, but unfortunately there are a significant number of real world geometries which will cause problems
      for the current implementation.  In those cases, deeper understanding of what is happening can be
      very important to maximizing the success of a conversion.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default, conversions will first attempt a standard NMG facetization and boolean evaluation of
      the existing geometry.  When it succeeds, NMG's output is generally the best quality output that
      can be produced by any of BRL-CAD's available facetization methods.  If NMG booleans fail, a fall-back method based
      on Bloomenthal's continuation method (CM) polygonalizer will be attempted by default.Note
      that if any of the methodology flags (<emphasis>--NMG</emphasis>,<emphasis>--CM</emphasis>,
      or <emphasis>--SPSR</emphasis>) are explicitly enabled, the other methodologies will be disabled unless they
      too are explicitly enabled.
    </para>
    <para>
      While the <command>facetize</command> command does not itself expose options to adjust the behavior of
      the NMG boolean methodology, it will respect MGED's settings for absolute (<emphasis>abs</emphasis>),
      relative (<emphasis>rel</emphasis>), and normal (<emphasis>norm</emphasis>) tolerances which are set with
      the MGED <command>tol</command> command.  These settings may be changed between repeated runs of the
      facetize command to attempt different NMG evaluations.
    </para>
    <para>
      Bloomenthal's continuation method tends to be slower and exhibit artifacts around sharp corners - users
      are advised to inspect the output from this method manually to ensure it will meet their needs. (All objects
      created with this methodology in a multi-region hierarchical conversion are also included in a top level
      combination with CONTINUATION in the name to allow users to more easily inspect them.)  By default, the
      BRL-CAD raytracer is used to shoot pseudo-random rays at the object and accumulate an average observed
      thickness of the model.  This thickness is then used as the basis for an initial guess at the appropriate
      stepping size used by the CM walker (smaller means more triangles, and longer run times, but potentially
      better preservation of small features.)  The initial thickness is multiplied by a scale factor, which
      defaults to 0.15 but may be overridden by the user with the <emphasis>--feature-scale</emphasis> option.
      Alternately, if the user has some specific knowledge of what feature size they are likely to want, they
      may use the <emphasis>--feature-size</emphasis> option to directly set this parameter independent of the
      observed average thickness.
    </para>
    <para>
      Because CM tends to generate a very large number of triangles, it is necessary to post
      process its initial mesh with a decimation routine to remove triangles which are not necessary to actual
      feature representation.  This process is also feature-size based, and by default is set to 1.5x the feature size.
      However, if the user wishes to preserve more triangles than the default behavior they may manually
      override this parameter with the <emphasis>--decimation-feature-size</emphasis> option.  Generally
      speaking smaller values will lead to more meshes being retained in the final output mesh, but experimentation
      will likely be needed to zero in on desired results.  See CM examples above for an illustration using
      the moss.g ellipsoid region.
    </para>
    <para>
      Both NMG and CM assume a geometry hierarchy containing only
      valid solid objects.  Both methods will refuse to process any tree containing recognizably
      non-solid objects, as these tend to cause run-time problems and generate invalid outputs.  For non-solid
      objects, the "--SPSR" methodology may be enabled - it will apply the Kazhdan et. al. Screened Poisson Surface
      Reconstruction (SPSR) process to a pseudo-randomly sampled point set generated from <emphasis>old_object</emphasis>.  This
      methodology may not cope well with the type of points sets generated from CAD geometry and is off
      by default in normal <command>facetize</command> processing, but it is also the only currently available
      methodology in BRL-CAD which has a chance of generating a valid mesh from non-solid inputs.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are three parameters available for the SPSR methodology specifically:  maximum reconstruction depth
      (<emphasis>-d</emphasis>) will control the level of detail in the output mesh, point weight (<emphasis>-w</emphasis>)
      which impacts how much the output will attempt to interpolate the original inputs, and samples per node
      (see the Kazhdan et. al. paper for more information.)  For situations where the user wishes to experiment
      with different point sampling schemes, they are referred to the <command>pnts</command> command which offers
      more fine grained controls when it comes to generating point sets from BRL-CAD objects.
    </para>
  </refsection>



  
  <refsection xml:id="util">
    <title>USEFUL TRICKS</title>
    <para>
      These are some useful tricks for targeted manipulation of the facetization process.
    </para>
    <example>
      <title>Reset CM state of a subset of objects.</title>
      <para>
	Use search -exec to reset just the continuation method flag (will result in resume
	retrying CM on all missing objects, without triggering the full retry of all methods
	entailed by the --retry option.)  More targeted searches can do this reset for more
	narrow subsets of the .g database.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput>search -attr facetize:CM -exec attr rm "{}" facetize:CM ";"</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

    <example>
      <title>List invalid BoT objects below a comb</title>
      <para>
	Use lint -M to report on invalid objects below a comb.
      </para>
      <para>
	<prompt>mged&gt;</prompt> <userinput> lint -M model.f</userinput>
      </para>
    </example>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="author">
    <title>AUTHOR</title>
    <para>BRL-CAD Team</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="bug_reports">
    <title>BUG REPORTS</title>

    <para>
      Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
      mail to <email>devs@brlcad.org</email>
    </para>
  </refsection>

</refentry>
