<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="STATFORMAT" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>NPUSH</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv xml:id="name">
    <refname>npush</refname>
    <refpurpose>
      push matrices down a tree hierarchy
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command>npush</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-h</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-?</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-v</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-f</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-x</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-r</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-s</arg>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-d <replaceable>max_depth</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice="req">arg1 [arg2]...</arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  
  <refsection xml:id="npush_background"><info><title>Background: Matrices in BRL-CAD</title></info>

  <para>
    BRL-CAD uses a global coordinate system in which all objects are placed.  This means each region
    must uniquely occupy its own portion of that space in order to avoid overlapping with another
    region.  Naively, this means that all objects defined in a .g file need to individually
    describe distinct volumes using unique primitives.  While possible, such an approach is quite
    wasteful if different regions define the same shape and vary only in the positioning of that shape.
    A classic example is as a standard bolt used hundereds of times in assembling a machine - ideally
    such a shape should only need to be described once, and then <emphasis>instances</emphasis> of that
    shape are positioned to identify individual bolts in the overall model.
  </para>
  <para>
    COMB trees, which describe organized hierarchies of individual shapes (or other COMB trees) in
    BRL-CAD, are the standard mechanism used in .g files to reusing otherwise identical object definitions
    in <emphasis>different</emphasis> positions and orientations. Matrices associated with instances of
    objects listed in COMB trees position those individual parts, and matrices at different portions of
    the COMB tree hierarchy can position smaller or large components of the whole.
    For example, the tree:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
    sph3/
        u sph3_1.r/R
                u sph3.s
        u sph3_2.r/R
                u sph3.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    appears at first glance to define an overlap, since it includes two different regions both of which
    are defined using the same sphere object: sph3.s.  However, if we inspect sph3_1.r and sph3_2.r more
    closely, we see that their definitions incorporate matrices over the instances of sph3.s:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph3_1.r:  REGION id=1002 (air=0, los=100, GIFTmater=1) --
   u sph3.s [10, 0, 0] scale 1
sph3_2.r:  REGION id=1003 (air=0, los=100, GIFTmater=1) --
   u sph3.s [20, 0, 0] scale 1
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    The instance of sph3.s in sph3_1.r is offset in the X direction by 10mm, and the sph3_2.r instance is
    offset by 20mm.  In addition, if we inspect sph3's tree:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph3:  --
   u sph3_1.r
   u sph3_2.r [100, 0, 0] scale 1
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    we see that the instance of sph3_2.r in sph3 also has a matrix offsetting its position.  So the
    instance of sph.s defined by sph3/sph3_2.r/sph.s is offset in total by 120mm in the positive X direction
    relative to the global definition of sph.s
  </para>
  <para>
    As useful as these matrices are, users frequently need to consolidate multiple levels of positioning
    within a COMB tree, or even eliminate them completely if a client's code is not able to properly interpret
    the matrix information of a COMB hierarchy for its own processing.  Thus, specific logic is available in
    BRL-CAD to accomplish these tasks.
  </para>
  
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="npush_overview"><info><title>Overview</title></info>

  <para>
    The GED command <command>npush</command> defines logic for "moving" matrix operations within a COMB tree,
    without changing the position of individual object instances in the tree definition.
  </para>
  
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="npush_depth"><info><title>A Note on Depth</title></info>

  <para>
    It is worth taking a little time to define what we are referring to when we discuss the concept of
    depth when it comes to applying matrix pushing operations.  Consider the hierarchy:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_009/
        u [M1] sph9_g1/
                u [M2] sph9_g2/
                        u [M3] sph9_g3/
                                u [M4] sph9_g4/
                                        u [M5] sph9.r/R
                                                u [M6] sph9.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    M1, M2, etc. are matrices applied at each level of the hierarchy.  When discussing M1, we would refer
    to that matrix as being at "depth 1" in the hierarchy, as it is defined at one level below the top
    of the tree.  Similarly, M2 would be defined as being at depth 2, and so on.
  </para>
  <para>
    When discussing depth in push operations, pushing a matrix to a depth means we propagate the matrices
    down the tree to define a matrix at the specified depth.  For example, in the above example, a push
    of the matrices to depth 4 would result in:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_009/
        u sph9_g1/
                u sph9_g2/
                        u sph9_g3/
                                u [M1234] sph9_g4/
                                        u [M5] sph9.r/R
                                                u [M6] sph9.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    where M1234 is the accumulated application of M1, M2, M3 and M4.  Note the new matrix is applied at
    depth 4, the depth specified as the depth limit in the push.  Similarly, a depth limit of 6 would
    result in:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_009/
        u sph9_g1/
                u sph9_g2/
                        u sph9_g3/
                                u sph9_g4/
                                        u sph9.r/R
                                                u [M123456] sph9.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    where M123456 is the accumulated application of M1, M2, M3, M4, M5 and M6.  Note that the final step
    of eliminating the matrix by updating the parameters of sph.s was not taken.  That operation is defined
    conceptually as being at one depth lower than the matrix applied to the object.  Thus, it would require
    a depth limit of 7 to completely eliminate all the matrices in the example and update sph.s:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_009/
        u sph9_g1/
                u sph9_g2/
                        u sph9_g3/
                                u sph9_g4/
                                        u sph9.r/R
                                                u sph9.s (updated)
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    Note that if an object or comb exists at different levels of the hierarchy, depth limits may produce
    copies of an object even if there wouldn't otherwise be a need for those copies.  Take the following
    example:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_010/
        u [M1] sph10_f/
                u [M1] sph10_g/
                        u [M1] sph10.r/R
                                u [M2] sph10.s
        u [M3] sph10_a.r/R
                u [M3] sph10.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    where 3*M1+M2 = 2*M3 (i.e., the matricies on each branch of sph_010's tree individually evaluate out
    to the same result).  Since sph10.s ends up in the same place in both branches of sph_010, a full
    push of all matrices in this tree shouldn't need to create a copy of sph10.s with new paramenters.  However,
    if a push is limited to depth 3, we get a different outcome in that respect:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_010/
        u sph10_f/
                u sph10_g/
                        u [M1*3] sph10.r/R
                                u [M2] sph10.s
        u sph10_a.r/R
                u sph10.s_01 (updated sph10.s copy)
  </literallayout>   
  <para>
    Depth 3 is deep enough that the parameters of sph10.s in the second branch should be updated.  However,
    in the first branch, there is an instance of sph10.s that will remain unmodified with a depth limit of
    three.  Thus, the database needs to contain both the modified and unmodified sph10.s in order to define
    the requested comb tree.  A subsequent full push would result in sph10.s being identical to sph10.s_01,
    but (at least for now) logic to automatically recognize this case and simplify it is not built in to the
    push logic.
  </para>
  <para>
    The same phenomena can occur with comb trees.  Consider the following example:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_011/
        u sph11_f/
                u [M1] sph11_g/
                        u sph11.s
        u sph11_h/
                u [M2] sph11_g/
                        u sph11.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    If sph_011 is pushed to depth 3, the matrices will be pushed to the level of sph11_g's instance
    references (sph11.s, in this case.)  However, if M1 != M2, sph11_g would need to have two different
    matrices in its tree for the same instance.  Since a depth limit of 3 does not push the matrices
    down to parameter setting of sph11.s, a new comb must be created:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_011/
        u sph11_f/
                u sph11_g/
                        u [M1] sph11.s
        u sph11_h/
                u sph11_g_01/ (updated sph11_g copy)
                        u [M2] sph11.s
  </literallayout>
  
  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="npush_special_depths"><info><title>Pushing relative to Regions and Shapes</title></info>

  <para>
    In addition to numerical depth limits, <command>npush</command> offers two additional specifiers that
    are more aware of specific types of objects in trees.  The <option>r</option> option will push matrices
    down to a level just above region references, and the <option>s</option> option will push matrices to
    a level just above primitive shapes.  For example, using the following hierarchy:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_010/
        u [M1] sph10_f/
                u [M1] sph10_g/
                        u [M1] sph10.r/R
                                u [M2] sph10.s
        u [M3] sph10_a.r/R
                u [M3] sph10.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    a <option>r</option> push would result in the following:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_010/
        u sph10_f/
                u sph10_g/
                        u [M1*3] sph10.r/R
                                u [M2] sph10.s
        u [M3] sph10_a.r/R
                u [M3] sph10.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    A <option>s</option> push, on the other hand, will take the matrices in both branches deeper:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_010/
        u sph10_f/
                u sph10_g/
                        u sph10.r/R
                                u [M1*3+M2] sph10.s
        u sph10_a.r/R
                u [M3*2] sph10.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    Note that neither option alters the parameters of primitive shapes.
  </para>

  <para>
    Worse still is a case where multiple copies of identical objects are referenced at multiple levels.
    Consider the following example:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_016/
        u [M1] sph16a/R
                u [M2] sph16_1/
                        u sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
        u [M3] sph16a/R
                u [M4] sph16_1/
                        u sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    If we push to depth 3, we end up with four different versions of the sph16.c tree: 
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_016/
        u sph16a/R
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M12] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M1] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
        u sph16a/R
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M34] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M3] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    The first stage of the answer is to create three new combinations and redefine the sph16a tree:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_016/
        u sph16a/R
                u sph16_1_01/
                        u [M12] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M1] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
        u sph16a/R
                u sph16_1_02/
                        u [M34] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1_03/
                        u [M3] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    That addresses sph16_1, but the tree updates to sph16a created a new problem:   now we have
    two different versions of the sph16a tree.  To resolve that problem, we must create a new
    comb to replace one of the conflicting sph16a instances and redefine the sph_016 tree:
  </para>
  <literallayout>
sph_016/
        u sph16a/R
                u sph16_1_01/
                        u [M12] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1/
                        u [M1] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
        u sph16a_01/R
                u sph16_1_02/
                        u [M34] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
                u sph16_1_03/
                        u [M3] sph16.c/
                                u sph16.s
  </literallayout>
  <para>
    Unlike sph16a and sph16_1, sph_016 has not seen any changes to its volumetric definition.  sph_016
    is the "top level" object specified for this push, and as such constitutes a reliable termination point for
    any need to propagate tree changes.  Even if any combs elsewhere in the database reference sph_016,
    they will not see any volumetric changes as a consequence of the operation and do not need to redefine
    their trees to preserve original sph_016 trees for external use in copies of sph_016.
  </para>
  </refsection>
  
  <refsection xml:id="search_options"><title>OPTIONS</title>

    <variablelist remap="TP">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-h or -?</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Print help and exit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-v</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Verbose processing output (primarily used for debugging).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-f or -x</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Force creation of new objects if necessary to avoid conflicts while fully pushing matrices. (A.k.a "xpush" mode).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-r</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Halt push operations at the hierarchy level above regions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-s</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Halt push operations at the hierarchy level above solids.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis remap="B" role="bold">-d max_depth</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	    Halt push operations at the hierarchy level specified by <emphasis>max_depth</emphasis>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

  </refsection>

  <refsection xml:id="examples"><title>EXAMPLES</title>

    <example><title>Default</title>
      <para>
        <userinput>push sph1</userinput>
      </para>
      <literallayout>
      </literallayout>
    </example>
    
  </refsection>
  
</refentry>
