<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="pull">

<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>PULL</refentrytitle>
  <manvolnum>nged</manvolnum>
  <refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
  <refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD User Commands</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv xml:id="name">
  <refname>pull</refname>
  <refpurpose>Pulls the effects of all transformation matrices that appear in
	any combinations or primitives in the trees from the leaves up to the specified <emphasis>objects</emphasis> or node.
   </refpurpose>
</refnamediv>

<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
  <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
    <command>pull</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>objects</replaceable></arg>
  </cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsection xml:id="description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

  <para>Pulls the effects of all matrix transformations that appear in
	any combinations or primitives in the tree from the leaves up to the specified <emphasis>objects</emphasis>. This will restore the parameters of the <emphasis>primitive shapes</emphasis> if any of the transformation matrices were not identity matrices. All the transformation matrices visited will be set to the current transformation matrix as it moves up the tree. This command will fail, and no changes will be made, if the specified <emphasis>object</emphasis> is a primitive shape referenced by the list of <emphasis>objects</emphasis>.
   </para>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="examples"><title>EXAMPLES</title>

  <para>The example shows the use of the <command>pull</command> command to pull the effects of any transformation matrices from leaves(primitive shapes) of a tree up to the specified head objects.
  </para>

  <example><title>Pull the effects of any transformation matrices from the leaves(primitive shapes) of the tree up to the specified head nodes(objects).</title>

    <para>
      <prompt>mged&gt;</prompt><userinput>pull group1 regiona</userinput>
    </para>
    <para>Pulls the effects of any transformation matrices from the primitive shapes in the tree up to the root nodes specified by <emphasis>group1</emphasis> 	and <emphasis>regiona</emphasis>.
    </para>
  </example>

</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title><para>BRL-CAD Team</para></refsection>

<refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>

  <para>
    Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
    mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;, or via the "cadbug.sh" script.
  </para>
</refsection>
</refentry>
