<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='anim_time1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>ANIM_TIME</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>anim_time</refname>
<refpurpose>estimate appropriate time parameters for path</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>anim_time</command>
    <arg choice='opt'>-s <replaceable>start_speed_absolute</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-e <replaceable>end_speed_absolute</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-i <replaceable>initial_speed_relative</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-f <replaceable>final_speed_relative</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-m <replaceable>max_len</replaceable></arg>
    <group choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'>-v </arg><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>q</replaceable></arg></group>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>&lt;</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>in.table</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>&gt;</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>out.table</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>This filter is designed to estimate appropriate time parameters for
an animation curve in 3D space. Given a four-column table specifying
time and 3D position for an object,
<command>anim_time</command>
ignores all but the first and last time specifications and
calculates reasonable time values for each intermediate point in the table.
The
output time values are based on the distances between points and the
calculated speed of the object. Various options allow the user to
control the assumptions on the object's initial and final speeds, and the
form of the output.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Anim_time</emphasis>
is intended to be used in situations where the user knows what key points
an object should pass through and how long the entire motion should take,
but doesn't care exactly when the object
reaches each point. It is also useful for getting objects to accelerate
smoothly to and from rest.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='options'><title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-m</option>#</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the maximum number of points to be read. This default to 64, so
you must use this option if you want to use tables with more than 64
points.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-s</option>#</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the starting speed of the object. If this option is not
specified, then the object is assumed to be initially travelling on a
pace to negotiate the entire path in the given time at a constant rate.
The argument must be positive and no greater than three times the speed
needed to traverse the path at a constant rate.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-e</option>#</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the final speed of the object. If this option is not specified,
then the object is assumed to end up travelling on a pace to negotiate
the entire path in the given time at a constant rate. The argument must
be positive and no greater than three times the speed needed to traverse
the path at a constant rate.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-i</option>#</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the initial speed of the object, relative to the speed that
would negotiate the given path at a constant rate. For example, an
argument of 2.0 means twice the speed needed to traverse the path at a
constant rate. Must lie between 0.0 and 3.0.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-f</option>#</term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the final speed of the object, relative to the speed that would
negotiate the given path at a constant rate. Must lie between 0.0 and
3.0.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-v</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Verbose option. The output table will contain a time column and three
position columns. If this option is not specified, only the new time
column will be printed.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-q</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Query the total distance. If this option is specified, the only output
will be a number representing the total length of the input path.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>The algorithm fits a cubic polynomial to the distance vs time graph, and then
uses Newton's method to find the times corresponding to each given distance.
If for some reason convergence is not reached,
<command>anim_time</command>
will print a warning on standard error. If the
<option>-d</option>
option is specified, the results of each iteration will be printed.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>Carl J. Nuzman</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='copyright'><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<para>This software is Copyright (c) 1996-2014 by the United States
Government as represented by U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bug_reports'><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

