<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='anim_turn1'>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>ANIM_TURN</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>anim_turn</refname>
<refpurpose>make animation table for vehicle with front-wheel steering.</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>anim_turn</command>    <arg choice='plain'>-l <replaceable>length</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-a <replaceable>angle</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-r <replaceable>radius</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-f <replaceable>factor</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-p <replaceable>integer</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>&lt;</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>in.table</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>&gt;</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>out.table</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para>The motion of a front wheel steered vehicle is not simple - the
instantaneous velocity of the front wheels is in the direction they are
pointed, while the instantaneous velocity of the back wheels is the
direction the vehicle is pointed. The purpose of
<command>anim_turn</command>
is to
produce a complete animation table for such a vehicle, given a table
specifying the desired position of the front axle at each relevant
time step. The input table should contain four columns, specifying the
time and 3D position of the center of the front axle. Actually, the path
is assumed to be confined to an x-y plane, but the three columns are
included for consistency with other animation routines.</para>

<para>The output is normally a seven-column table which is a copy of
the input table with three extra columns specifying the yaw,
pitch, and roll of the truck at each time. The pitch and roll
are always zero, since the motion is assumed be in an x-y plane.</para>

<para>The
<option>-l#</option>
option is not optional, and is used to specify the length
of the wheelbase (from the front axle to the rear axle).</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='options'><title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-a#</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para><emphasis remap='I'>Track</emphasis>
assumes that the truck should initially be oriented
along the line defined by the first two positions in the input table.
Otherwise, the desired initial yaw of the truck can be specified with the
<option>-a#</option>
option.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-r#</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the radii of the front wheels. If this option is selected,
<emphasis remap='I'>track</emphasis>
will create an animation script to animate the front wheels. The output
table would contain four columns: time, swivel-angle, roll, and a zero
channel. These represent the orientation of the front wheels, in terms
of yaw, pitch, and roll, and the table can be piped directly to
<emphasis remap='I'>anim_script</emphasis>.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-f#</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify a factor to be used to animate a steering wheel. If this option
is selected, the output table will contain four columns: time, swivel,
and two zero columns. This table can be used directly by
<emphasis remap='I'>anim_script</emphasis>
to make an animation script for a steering wheel. The argument to the
option should be the factor by which to exaggerate the swiveling of
the wheels. For
example, on a typical truck, you may need to turn the steering wheel 360
degrees in order for the wheels to swivel 20 degrees. To model this
effect, a factor of 18 would be used.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-p#</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify the ratio of input rows to output rows,
which must be an integer. The default, of course, is one. The accuracy
of the output depends on having a large number of input lines, which is
not usually a problem in animations, which require a large number of
frames per second. However, if a test animation with a small number of
frames per second is being created, the user should give an input table
with a high number of input rows and reduce the output with the
<option>-p#</option>
option. For example, if
<emphasis remap='B'>in.table</emphasis>
contains 30 rows for each second of the
animation, then the command</para>

<para><emphasis remap='B'>anim_turn -l 3000 -p10 &lt; in.table &gt; out.table</emphasis></para>

<para>would produce an animation table containing 3 rows for each second of
the animation.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bugs'><title>BUGS</title>
<para>The algorithm used only works for motion in an x-y plane.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>Carl J. Nuzman</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='copyright'><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<para>This software is Copyright (c) 1994-2014 by the United States
Government as represented by U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bug_reports'><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

