<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='bot_shellvtk1'>
<refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>BOT_SHELL-VTK</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>bot_shell-vtk</refname>
<refpurpose>VTK polydata converter (BRL-CAD to VTK)</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>bot_shell-vtk</command>    <arg choice='opt'>-m </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-n </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-d <replaceable>debug_level</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-g <replaceable>cell_size</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'>-o <replaceable>vtk_polydata_output</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>brlcad_database.g</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>object1</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'><arg choice='plain'><replaceable>object2</replaceable></arg><arg choice='plain' rep='repeat'><replaceable>object3</replaceable></arg></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><command>bot_shell-vtk</command>
uses raytracing to extract the exterior triangles from a model made up
of BOT primitives. The default operation is to fire a single ray at each
triangle of each BOT primitive in the specified objects. The rays are fired
anti-normalward towards the center of each triangle from outside the model
bounding box. If the triangle currently under consideration appears as the
first object hit along the ray, then that triangle is included in the
VTK polydata output (thus retaining only exterior triangles). Non-BOT
primitives encountered along the rays may hide BOT triangles, but non-BOT
primitives do not contribute to the output.
The
<option>-m</option>
option may be specified to enable both the first and last triangles along
each ray to be added to the output. This can improve performance, by reducing
the number of rays fired, but may reduce performance for complex models
because it requires processing each ray completely through the model.
If the
<option>-n</option>
option is specified, the output will include vertex normals in the
VTK output. If the BOT primitives of the input BRL-CAD model do not
have vertex normal information, this option will not add any information
to the output, but will greatly increase the size of the output file.
If the
<option>-g</option>
option is specified, then the rays are fired from a uniform grid for
three orthogonal directions rather than at each individual triangle. This
can give a fairly rapid result for larger cell sizes, but is likely to miss
some triangles. The
<emphasis remap='I'>cell_size</emphasis>
must be specified in millimeters.
The
<option>-d</option>
option may be used to get debug output during processing. This is likely to
only be useful for developers.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='example'><title>EXAMPLE</title>
<synopsis>
$ <emphasis remap='I'>bot_shell-vtk  -o output.vtk  sample.g  the_exterior</emphasis>
</synopsis>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='diagnostics'><title>DIAGNOSTICS</title>
<para>Error messages are intended to be self-explanatory.</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='author'><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>BRL-CAD Team</para>

</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='copyright'><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<para>This software is Copyright (c) 2003-2014 by the United States
Government as represented by U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bug_reports'><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

