<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id="rlefb1">
<refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>RLE-FB
</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>rle-fb</refname>
<refpurpose>decode run-length encoded image onto a frame buffer</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id="synopsis">
<cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
  <command>rle-fb</command>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-Ocd </arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-F <replaceable>framebuffer</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-C <replaceable>r/g/b</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-S <replaceable>squarescrsize</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-W <replaceable>scr_width</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-N <replaceable>scr_height</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-X <replaceable>scr_xoff</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">-Y <replaceable>scr_yoff</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat"><replaceable>file.rle</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsection xml:id="description"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><command>rle-fb</command>
decodes a University of Utah
standard (Edition-3, or "Utah Raster Toolkit")
Run-Length Encoded (RLE) format file
(saved with
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>fb-rle</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
or a similar program)
to a frame buffer.
If
<emphasis remap="I">file.rle</emphasis>
is not specified, standard input is read.</para>

<para>Each RLE file contains an <emphasis remap="I">image rectangle</emphasis>.
The Utah Raster Toolkit semantics specify that the
<command>rle-fb</command>
program is to clip the RLE image rectangle to the screen of the current
framebuffer, only modifying pixels in that area.
In the case where the RLE file contains a rectangle of size greater
than or equal to that of the current screen, then all pixels on the screen
are modified.
In the case where the RLE file contains a rectangle smaller than the
screen, or where a portion of that rectangle has been positioned
outside the bounds of the screen, then this program will only modify those
screen pixels underneath the RLE image rectangle.
While this is behavior can be a great boon when creating a montage of
smaller images, it behooves the user to arrange for a suitable background.</para>

<para>If the screen size is explicitly specified by a command line option,
the framebuffer is opened with exactly that size, and the RLE image
rectangle is clipped to that size, even if the framebuffer hardware
could support a larger size.
If the screen size is not specified, then this program attempts to
open the framebuffer with a size large enough to hold the entire
RLE image rectangle.  If the open succeeds, but the full size request
is not honored, then the RLE image rectangle is silently clipped to
the available screen.
The RLE image rectangle can be repositioned on the screen with the
<option>-X</option>
and
<option>-Y</option>
command line options, as well as by using
<emphasis remap="I">repos(1)</emphasis>.</para>
<variablelist remap="TP">
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-W </option><replaceable>scr_width</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>specifies the desired width of the screen, in pixels.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-N </option><replaceable>scr_height</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>specifies the desired height of the screen, in scanlines.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-S </option><replaceable>squarescrsize</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>sets the screen width and height to the indicated value.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-F </option><replaceable>framebuffer</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>This option specifies which framebuffer the image is to be displayed on.
If not given, the environment variable
<acronym/><emphasis remap="B">FB_FILE</emphasis>
is used to select the display device (see
<emphasis remap="I">brlcad(1)</emphasis>).
If
<acronym/><emphasis remap="B">FB_FILE</emphasis>
has not been set, the default device for your system will
be used.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-c</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>The crunch colormap option.
If the RLE file contains a colormap, rather than loading that colormap
into the framebuffer and allowing the framebuffer to apply the colormap
to produce the final image, this option causes the colormap to be applied
to the pixel data before it is sent to the framebuffer.
In this case, the colormap in the framebuffer is undisturbed.
This can be useful to preserve dramatic images created with weird color maps
such that Gamma correction (e.g., for film) can also be applied.
This option is recommended when producing images for export to other
display systems, so that variations in the interpretation of color maps
between different types of display hardware do
not affect the displayed image.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-d</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Debug option; provides a verbose description of the input file structure and
image decoding process, written on standard error.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-O</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Restores the image data in <emphasis remap="I">overlay</emphasis> mode.
Only areas of the original image which were not the background color are
decoded.  The rest of the image already in the frame buffer is undisturbed.
Note that this mode uses twice as many DMAs to the frame buffer as
the normal mode.
This is because each scanline of the
previous image must be read from the framebuffer,
the overlay portions of the new image must be written on top,
and the composite scanline must be written back to the framebuffer.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-C </option><replaceable>r/g/b</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>If the image is not being decoded in overlay mode, the background is
normally set to the value recorded in the RLE file.
This option permits
the user to specify an alternate background color
as a red/green/blue triple, separated by slashes (/).
The color intensity in each channel ranges from 0 (dark) to 255 (bright).</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-X </option><replaceable>scr_xoff</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify a screen X offset, which will offset the file onto the screen
by the given amount.  (i.e.,
<option>-X</option><literal>10</literal>
would place (0,0) in the RLE image rectangle at screen coordinate (10,0).
The offset may be negative or positive.
The RLE image rectangle will be clipped to the screen, as required.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-Y </option><replaceable>scr_yoff</replaceable></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Specify a screen Y offset, which will offset the file onto the screen
by the given amount.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis remap="I">file.rle</emphasis></term>
  <listitem>
<para>Name of file to decode, in RLE format.
If not specified, standard input is used instead.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>The run length encoded image format is best used for the long-term
storage of images, as it uses less disk storage than a
<emphasis remap="I">pix(5)</emphasis>
file, at the expense of requiring more processing
for the encoding and decoding.
This program is also useful when using the Utah Raster Toolkit
utilities, which only operate on RLE encoded files;
this program will display their results on a framebuffer.</para>

<para>Simple compositing of images can be done with the
<option>-O</option>
overlay flag on
<emphasis remap="I">rle-fb(1)</emphasis>.
More sophisticated compositing can be achieved using some of the
other tools.
For RLE files,
<emphasis remap="I">comp(1)</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap="I">crop(1)</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap="I">repos(1)</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap="I">rlepatch(1)</emphasis>,
and
<emphasis remap="I">rlebox(1)</emphasis>
can be used.
For
<emphasis remap="I">pix(5)</emphasis>
files,
<emphasis remap="I">pixrect(1)</emphasis>,
<emphasis remap="I">pixscale(1)</emphasis>,
and
<emphasis remap="I">pixmerge(1)</emphasis>
are used.</para>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="examples"><title>EXAMPLES</title>
  <blockquote remap="RS">
<para>rle-fb truck.rle</para>
<para>rle-fb -O text.rle</para>
<para>rle-fb -C 0/255/0 &lt;car.rle</para>
 </blockquote> <!-- remap='RE' -->
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="diagnostics"><title>DIAGNOSTICS</title>
<variablelist remap="TP">
  <varlistentry>
  <term>rle-fb: excess arguments ignored.</term>
  <listitem>
<para>More than one RLE file name was specified.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>rle-fb: Error reading setup information.</term>
  <listitem>
<para>The subroutine
<function>rle_get_setup()</function>
returned an error code.
Either the file is not in Edition-2 or Edition-3 RLE format,
or the file has been damaged or truncated.
If the file is in Edition-1 RLE format, the
<emphasis remap="I">orle-fb(1)</emphasis>
program can be used to display the file.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>rle-fb: Warning: RLE image rectangle entirely off screen</term>
  <listitem>
<para>The combined effects of the RLE image rectangle definition stored in the
RLE file and any
<option>-X</option>
and
<option>-Y</option>
command line options have resulted in the RLE image rectangle being
shifted entirely off the screen.
While this is not an error, no screen pixels were changed.
This may not have been the intent of the user, so the message is printed.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>rle-fb: correcting for old style colormap.</term>
  <listitem>
<para>The only change between the Edition-2 and Edition-3 RLE file formats
that is not upwards compatible is the format of the colormap.
Edition-2 stored eight bits of data right justified in a 16-bit field,
while Edition-3 stores a full 16-bit field.
In order to allow this program to decode images stored in the Edition-2
format, any colormap which has the upper eight bits all zero in all
colormap entries is assumed to be an Edition-2 colormap, and is adjusted
for suitable display.
While this heuristic may be tricked with an Edition-3 colormap
with degenerate values, the picture would have been very dark,
and the benefits of full upwards compatibility from Edition-2 format files
were deemed worth this risk.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="see_also"><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para><citerefentry><refentrytitle>brlcad</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>fb-rle</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rle-pix</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pix-rle</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>pixrect</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pixscale</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>pixmerge</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>comp</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>crop</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>repos</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rlepatch</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>, <citerefentry><refentrytitle>rlebox</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>librle</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>.</para>

</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="author"><title>AUTHOR</title>
<para>BRL-CAD Team</para>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="copyright"><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<para>This software is Copyright (c) 1988-2014 by the United States
Government as represented by U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
</refsection>

<refsection xml:id="bug_reports"><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.</para>
</refsection>
</refentry>
