<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- lifted from troff+man by doclifter -->
<refentry xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en' xml:id='scriptsort1'>
<refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>SCRIPTSORT
</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class='source'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class='manual'>BRL-CAD</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>

<refnamediv>
<refname>scriptsort</refname>
<refpurpose>sort an rt/mged animation script or scripts</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<!-- body begins here -->
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id='synopsis'>
<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>scriptsort</command>
    <arg choice='opt'>-fsq </arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-b <replaceable>base</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>-o <replaceable>frame_offset</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>&lt;</replaceable></arg>
    <arg choice='plain'><replaceable>unsorted.script</replaceable></arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>


<refsect1 xml:id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<para><emphasis remap='I'>Scriptsort</emphasis>
reads an rt/mged animation script from standard input and sorts it.
Typically this program is used to combine several scripts by sorting
their concatenation. Or, it can be used to change the ordering of the
frames.</para>

<para><emphasis remap='I'>Scriptsort</emphasis>
organizes the input script into three different categories.
The first category consists of
numbered frames. Each frame begins with a
<emphasis remap='B'>start</emphasis>
<emphasis remap='I'>frame_num</emphasis>;
command, and ends with an
<emphasis remap='B'>end</emphasis>;
command. All of the text between those two commands makes up the body of
the frame. When two frames with the same frame number are found in the
input, they are merged into a single frame. The body of the merged frame
is the concatenation of the two original frames, except that only one
<emphasis remap='B'>clean</emphasis>;
command is ever printed in a single frame.</para>

<para>The second category consists of shell commands. Any line in the
animation script which is not inside a frame and which begins with an
exclamation mark is considered to be a shell command.
Typically, each frame of an animation script might have an associated
shell command following it to process the image just computed.
The third category
is "everything else". These are assumed to be global animation commands that
don't belong to any frame and should be executed before the first frame.</para>

<para>Once the input has been sorted by category, output is produced according
to the following method. First, all of the global animation commands
that didn't belong to any frame are printed. Next,
<command>scriptsort</command>
determines the order in which to print the frames. This
might be in ascending numerical order, or in a scrambled order which
incrementally increases the time resolution of the script, depending on
the
<option>-b</option>
option. Then
<command>scriptsort</command>
prints the frames in order. After each frame, the
shell command
<emphasis remap='B'>!</emphasis>end_of_frame.sh frame_num
is added if any of the input frames which contributed to the frame had
an associated shell command. When the animation script is run
as input to
<emphasis remap='I'>rt,</emphasis>
the user should create a shell script called "end_of_frame.sh" to
perform any desired shell commands. The argument to "end_of_frame.sh" is
the frame number.</para>

<para>The order in which the frames are printed out depends on an integer
called the base integer, which must always be a power of two. By
default, the base integer is one, which causes the frames to be output
in order of increasing frame number. Larger powers of two cause the
frames to be ordered in such a way that the time resolution of the
animation script is incrementally increased.
The following algorithm defines the order corresponding to a given base
integer:</para>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>1. List all of the frames in order of increasing frame</term>
  <listitem>
<para>number. Then give each frame an index according to its position in the
list. For example, if there are 61 frames numbered from 45 to 105, then the
index of frame 45 is 0, and the index of frame 105 is 60.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>2. Print all of the frames whose indexes are multiples of the base</term>
  <listitem>
<para>integer, beginning with the frame indexed by zero.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term>3. If the base integer is one, stop here. Otherwise, go to step 4.</term>
  <term>4. Divide the base integer in half and print all of the frames whose</term>
  <listitem>
<para>indexes are odd multiples of the new base integer. Go to step 3.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>The base integer can be set with the
<option>-b#</option>
option. If the specified integer is negative or zero, then the base
integer is set to the largest power of two which is less than the number
of frames being printed. Otherwise, if the specified integer is not a
power of two, a warning is printed and the integer is set to 1. If the specified integer is not a power of two, then a warning
is printed and the integer is set to the default value, which is one.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='other_options'><title>OTHER OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist remap='TP'>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-f</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>forces a shell command to be printed after every frame, regardless of
whether or not shell commands were found in the input script.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-s</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>suppresses shell commands. No shell commands are printed, regardless of
whether or not shell commands were found in the input script.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-q</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>enables quiet mode. The status messages normally printed on standard
error are suppressed.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
  <term><option>-o</option></term>
  <listitem>
<para>frame_offset specifies an integer which should be added to all of the frame
numbers. For example, suppose that the user wants to concatenate
two animation scripts which begin at frame zero and are 300 frames long.
He or she should run one script through
<command>scriptsort</command>
with an offset of 300 before doing the concatenation.</para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='authors'><title>AUTHORS</title>
<para>Christopher T. Johnson</para>

<para>Carl J. Nuzman</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='copyright'><title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<para>This software is Copyright (c) 1994 Geometric Solutions, Inc.
Contributed to the US Army for unlimited distribution.
This software is Copyright (c) 1996-2014 by the United States
Government as represented by U.S. Army Research Laboratory.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 xml:id='bug_reports'><title>BUG REPORTS</title>
<para>Reports of bugs or problems should be submitted via electronic
mail to &lt;devs@brlcad.org&gt;.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

